<page pageNumber="408"> <text><![CDATA[Florida Topic 7 Assessment KEY TERMS AND IDEAS
SS.912.E.1.12
1. What is the relationship between aggregate supply,
aggregate demand, and gross domestic product?
2. How is nominal GDP different from real GDP?
3. What are the four main phases of the business cycle?
4. How is capital deepening related to economic growth?
5. What are the four main categories of unemployment?
6. How would inflation and deflation affect purchasing
power?
7. How is the poverty rate linked to income distribution?
8. How are cash transfers different from in-kind
benefits?
CRITICAL THINKING
LAFS.1112.WHST.1.2, SS.912.E.1.12, SS.912.E.2.5,
SS.912.E.2.7, SS.912.E.3.1
9. Identify Central Issues Why is it important for
economists to determine factors influencing real GDP?
10. Identify Cause and Effect Besides lower business
investment, what can reduce aggregate demand?
11. Synthesize The graph below shows U.S.
unemployment from 1996 to 2012. How do you think
the graph reflects business cycles?
12. Summarize What are the key features of each phase
of the business cycle?
13. Apply Concepts Which point in the business cycle
offers the greatest opportunity for a business? Explain.
14. Identify Cause and Effect How do capital
investments tend to affect productivity and economic
growth?
15. Identify Patterns How is expansion related to
inflation?
16. Summarize How has inflation historically affected
American society and world economies?
17. Support a Point of View With Evidence Are
government programs to reduce poverty effective?
Provide evidence to support your response.
18. Integrate Information What are the causes of
income inequality? What steps, if any, do you think
should be taken to reduce it? Explain.
19. Writing Activity Write an informative essay explaining
the history of a recent business cycle. Select the most
significant and relevant facts, extended definitions,
concrete details, quotations, or other information to
explain the causes of the expansion and contraction,
use graphics as appropriate to support your argument,
use varied transitions and sentence structures, use
precise language, domain-specific vocabulary and
techniques such as metaphor, simile, and analogy, and
write a conclusion that follows from your argument.Unemployment and Underemployment, 1996–2012 Percentage of Labor Force 14
12
10
16
18
8
6
4
2
0 1996 1998 2000 2002 2004 2006 2008 2010 2012 Unemployment Rate
UE plus Discouraged Workers
UE plus Discouraged plus
Involuntary P-T Workers 342 TOPIC 7 Economic Performance and Challenges ]]></text>
   </page>
<page pageNumber="409"> <text><![CDATA[DOCUMENT-BASED QUESTIONS
LAFS.1112.RH.1.1, LAFS.1112.RH.1.3, LAFS.1112.RH.2.6,
LAFS.1112.RH.3.9
In the United States, the federal and state governments
assist the poor. People disagree on whether helping
the poor should be the job of government or private
organizations.
DOCUMENT A
Before becoming President, Barack Obama expressed his
opinion about the role of government in helping the poor.
What’s most overwhelming about urban poverty
is that it’s so difficult to escape–it’s isolating and it’s
everywhere….
When you’re in these neighborhoods, you can see
what a difference it makes to have a government that
cares. You can see what a free lunch program does for
a hungry child. You can see what a little extra money
from an earned income tax credit does for a family
that’s struggling. You can see what prenatal care does
for the health of a mother and a newborn. So don’t tell
me there’s no role for government in lifting up our cities.
—Senator Barack Obama, speech, July 18, 2007
DOCUMENT B
Ron Paul, a long-time member of Congress, strongly
believed that the federal government had grown too big
and powerful.
Voluntary charities and organizations, such as
friendly societies that devoted themselves to helping
those in need, flourished in the days before the welfare
state turned charity into a government function….
Releasing the charitable impulses of the American
people by freeing them from the excessive tax burden
so they can devote more of their resources to charity,
is a moral and constitutional means of helping the
needy. By contrast, the federal welfare state is neither
moral nor constitutional. Nowhere in the Constitution
is the federal government given the power to levy
excessive taxes on one group of citizens for the benefit
of another group of citizens.
—Representative Ron Paul in the U.S. House of
Representatives, February 13, 2003
DOCUMENT C
Food stamps are a major form of government aid to the
poor. This graph shows how participation in food stamp
programs has changed over recent years. Number of Recipients (in millions)2005
2006
2007
2008
2009
2010
2011
2012
Year
25.6
26.5
26.3
28.2
33.5
40.3
44.7
46.6
 SOURCE: United States Department of Agriculture
 20. In Document A, Obama argues that
A. ending poverty is too costly.
B. there is a simple solution to the problem of poverty.
C. the government should fight poverty.
D. government policies are a leading cause of poverty.
21. In Document B, what does Paul say would be a better
alternative to federal welfare programs?
A. state welfare programs
B. private charitable organizations
C. state welfare programs
D. increased federal taxation
22. Analyze Graphs What conclusion does Document C
support?
A. Food stamps do not help poor people.
B. The food stamp program has not reduced poverty.
C. Food stamps are needed because poverty is
increasing.
D. The food stamp program should be privatized.
23. Writing Task In a two- to three-paragraph essay,
evaluate the points of view in Documents A And
B. Assess the authors’ claims and reasoning and
determine which source best confirms what you have
learned in your text. Integrating information from these
sources and your text, state your own conclusion
about whether government should take the lead in
helping the poor.Savvas.com/FloridaSS Go ONLINE to practice ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>