<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <eBook>
    <page pageNumber="480"> <text><![CDATA[rates encourage greater investment spending by business firms. This is because a firm’s cost of borrowing, or of using its own funds, decreases as the interest rate decreases. Higher interest rates discourage business spending.
Firms find that lower interest rates give them more opportunities for profitable investment. If a firm has to pay 15 percent interest on its loans, it may find few profitable opportunities. If interest rates fall to 6 percent, however, the firm may find that some opportunities become profitable.
If the macroeconomy is experiencing a contraction—declining income—the Federal Reserve may try to stimulate, or expand, it. The Fed will follow an easy money policy. That is, it will increase the money supply. An increased money supply will lower interest rates, thus encouraging investment spending. Of course, such a policy comes with some risk. For example, it may encourage overborrowing and overinvestment, followed by layoffs and cutbacks.
If the economy is experiencing a rapid expansion that may cause high inflation, the Fed may introduce a tight money policy. That is, it will reduce the money supply. The Fed reduces the money supply to push interest rates upward. By raising interest rates, the Fed causes investment spending to decline. This brings real GDP down, too.
Even though it can only alter the money supply, the Fed can have a great impact on the economy. The money supply influences interest rates, and interest rates influence the level of aggregate demand. Recall that aggregate demand represents the relationship between price levels and quantity demanded in the overall economy. Thus, the level of aggregate demand helps determine the level of real GDP.
IdENTIfy CAUSE ANd EffECT How are money supply and interest rates connected?
Timing Monetary Policy
Monetary policy, like fiscal policy, must be carefully timed if it is to help the macroeconomy. Properly handled, monetary policy can help the nation’s economy grow at a steady, sustainable pace. If policies are enacted at the wrong time, they could actually intensify the business cycle rather than stabilize it.
The Results of Good Timing To see why, consider Figure 9.28. Graph A shows the business cycle with a properly timed stabilization policy. The purple curve, which shows greater fluctuations, represents a normal business cycle. The goal of stabilization policy is to
HOW MONETARY POLICY WORKS
STEP 1
MONETARY
POLICY
IS ADJUSTED.
STEP 2
OR
THE SUPPLY
OF MONEY IN THE ECONOMY
    CHANGES.
STEP 3 %
INTEREST RATES
GO UP OR DOWN.
STEP 4 SPENDING
AND
INVESTMENT
INCREASE OR DECREASE.
MONETARY POLICY CAN CAUSE ECONOMIC
ACTIVITY TO INCREASE OR DECREASE.
>> Figure 9.27 Monetary policy affects the economy by altering money supply and interest rates. Summarize Explain in your own words the basic mechanism by which monetary policy affects the larger economy.
Bounce to Activate Chart
414 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="481"> <text><![CDATA[Business Cycles and Stabilization Policy
 Real GDP
A
Business cycle with properly timed stabilization policy
 Business cycle
   B
   Real GDP
Business cycle with poorly timed stabilization policy
 Business cycle
Time Time
>> Figure 9.28 Poorly timed policy can create more instability than the normal business cycle. Analyze Graphs Which scenario shown in these graphs represents the least stable economy?
smooth out those fluctuations—in other words, to make the peaks a little bit lower and the troughs not quite so deep. This will minimize inflation in the peaks and the effects of recessions in the troughs. Properly timed stabilization policy smooths out the business cycle, as shown by the orange curve.
The Results of Bad Timing If stabilization policy is not timed properly, however, it can actually make the business cycle more extreme, not smoother. The orange line in Graph B in Figure 9.28 shows the result of a poorly timed monetary policy, producing higher peaks and lower valleys than might otherwise occur. This can happen if, as GDP begins to fall from its peak, government economists fail to recognize that a contraction is occurring until the economy is already deeply into it.
By the time they enact expansionary policies and have those policies take effect, the economy might already be coming out of the recession on its own.
In such a situation, the expansionary effects of an easy money policy would boost the economy while
it is already expanding. This could result in a larger expansion—but also very high inflation.
Being late in implementing expansionary policies can have other effects, too. Suppose, for example, the economy has slowed down so much that businesses are reluctant to borrow at any rate for new investment. In that case, easy money would have little effect.
As you can see, properly timing monetary policy is important. It is also difficult. Figure 9.29 shows some of many indicators economists study in their effort to understand the economy. There are two basic problems in the timing of any macroeconomic policy. These are called policy lags.
Inside Lags The inside lag is the time it takes
to implement monetary policy. Such lags, or delays, occur for two reasons. First, it takes time to identify a problem. Although economists have developed sophisticated computer models for predicting economic trends, they still cannot know for sure
that the economy is headed into a new phase of the business cycle until it is already there. Statistics may conflict, and it can take up to a year to recognize a serious economic downturn.
A second reason for inside lags is that once a problem has been recognized, it can take additional time to enact policies. This problem is more severe for fiscal policy than for monetary policy. Fiscal policy, which includes changes in government spending and taxation, requires actions by Congress and the President. Since Congress must debate new plans and get the approval of the President, it takes time to get a new policy enacted. The enactment of monetary policy, on the other hand, is streamlined. The Federal Open Market Committee (FOMC) meets eight times per year to discuss monetary policy— more often if necessary. Once it has decided that
9.5 The Effects of Monetary Policy 415]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="482"> <text><![CDATA[changes are called for, the FOMC can enact policy almost immediately through open market operations or discount rate changes.
Outside Lags Once a new policy is determined, it takes time to become effective. This time period, known as the outside lag, also differs for monetary and fiscal policy. For fiscal policy, the outside lag lasts as long as is required for new government spending or tax policies to take effect and to begin to affect real GDP and the inflation rate. This time period can be relatively short, as with a tax rebate that returns government revenues to households eager for spending money. One statistical model concluded that an increase in government spending would increase GDP after just six months.
Outside lags can be much longer for monetary policy, since they primarily affect business investment plans. Firms may require months or even years to make large investment plans, especially those involving new physical capital, such as a new factory. Thus, a change in interest rates may not have its full effect on investment spending for several years. This conclusion is supported by several studies that suggest that more than two years may pass before the maximum impact of monetary policy is felt.
Given the longer inside lag for fiscal policy and the longer outside lag for monetary policy, it is difficult to know which policy has the shorter total lag. In practice, partisan politics and budgetary pressures often prevent the President and Congress from agreeing on fiscal policy. Because of the political difficulties of implementing fiscal policy, we rely to a greater extent on the Fed to use monetary policy to soften the business cycle.
APPLy CONCEPTS What problem can result from expansionary monetary policy that takes effect after the economy has already begun to expand following a period of contraction?
Anticipating Business Cycles
The Federal Reserve must do more than react to current trends. It must also anticipate changes in the economy. How should policymakers decide when to intervene in the economy?
How Monetary Policy Affects Inflation You have already read that expansionary policy, if enacted
at the wrong time, may push an economy into high
Components of the Index of Leading Economic Indicators®
1
Average weekly hours, manufacturing
2
Average weekly initial claims for unemployment insurance
3
Manufacturers’ new orders for consumer goods and materials
4
Manufacturers’ new orders for nondefense capital goods excluding aircraft orders
5
Institute of Supply Management’s Index of New Orders—another measure of manufacturing activity
6
Building permits, new private housing units
7
Stock prices, 500 common stocks
8
Leading Credit IndexTM, a measure of credit and lending
9
Interest rate spread between the 10-year Treasury bonds rate and the federal funds rate
  10 Average consumer expectations for business conditions (measure of consumer confidence)
  SOURCE: The Conference Board
 
>> Figure 9.29 Monitoring the economy means watching developments in manufacturing, labor, housing, the stock market, credit markets, and more. Identify Central Issues What does this list suggest about the challenge of managing the economy?
416 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="483"> <text><![CDATA[Recessions: 1950 – Present
July 1953–May 1954
Apr. 1960–Feb. 1961
Nov. 1973–Mar. 1975
Public protests erupted during a serious recession that was triggered by disruption of world oil supplies.
         July 1990–Mar. 1991
Mar. 2001–Nov. 2001
                 
1950 1955 1960 1965 1970 1975 1980 1985 1990 1995 2000 2005 2010 2015
                 Aug. 1957–Apr. 1958
This recession hit the U.S. auto industry hard. Here unemployed workers in Detroit line up to obtain financial assistance.
July 1981–Nov. 1982 Jan. 1980–July 1980
Dec. 1969–Nov. 1970
SOURCE: National Bureau of Economic Research
Dec. 2007–June 2009
Falling U.S. housing prices caused huge losses for many financial firms.
    
          >> Figure 9.30 Recessions have occurred with regularity over the recent decades. Analyze Information What is the longest interval between recessions shown?
Bounce to Activate Gallery
inflation. This is the chief danger of using an easy money policy to get the economy out of a recession.
An inflationary economy can be tamed by a tight money policy, but the timing is again crucial. If the policy takes effect as the economy is already cooling off on its own, the tight money could turn a mild contraction into a full-blown recession.
The decision of whether to use monetary policy, then, must be based partly on expectations of the business cycle. Some recessions are mild and likely to end quickly even without any policy intervention. The same is true of some periods of inflation.
Given the timing problems of monetary policy, it may be wiser in some cases to allow the business cycle to correct itself rather than run the risk of an ill-timed policy change. If a recession is expected to turn into an expansion in a short time, the best course of action may be to let the economy correct itself. On the other hand, if we expect a recession to last several years, then most economists would recommend an active policy. So, the question
most policymakers face is this: How long will this recessionary (or inflationary) period last?
How Quickly Do Economies Self-Correct?
Economists disagree on the answer to this question. Their estimates for the U.S. economy range from
two to six years. Figure 9.30 shows the timing and
duration of the recessions in recent U.S. history. Since the economy may take quite a long time to recover on its own from an inflationary peak or a recessionary trough, policymakers have time to help the economy return to stable levels of output and prices.
ANALyzE INfORMATION How would the Fed most likely respond if it predicted that a recession would soon turn into an expansion?
Debating Monetary Policy
In practice, the lags discussed here make monetary and fiscal policy difficult to apply. The lags and the general complexity of the national economy also make it difficult to sort out how different policies have affected the economy in the past. Economists have debated these matters for many years.
Some economists believe that governments should emphasize fiscal policy more than monetary policy. These economists are in the tradition of John Maynard Keynes. According to them, government spending should be used to smooth out the peaks and valleys of the business cycle.
Other economists are more in tune with the ideas of Milton Friedman. That is, they have greater faith in monetary policy. These proponents
 9.5 The Effects of Monetary Policy 417]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="484"> <text><![CDATA[of monetarism believe that adjusting the money supply is the most useful tool to improve macroeconomic performance.
Other economists, such as Friedrich Hayek, have taken different views. Hayek questioned economists’ ability to influence the economy effectively and had faith in a free economy’s ability to self-adjust. Though Hayek died in 1992, his ideas continue to exert a strong influence. Like-minded economists today will usually recommend against enacting new policies, arguing that government intervention disrupts the proper functioning of a free market economy.
This debate over which approach to take with monetary policy will probably never be settled to the satisfaction of all economists. If you follow the news, you will hear politicians carrying on the debate nearly every day.
ChECK UNdERSTANdINg What do monetarists believe about monetary policy?
ASSESSMENT
1. Apply Concepts How might the proper use of monetary policy affect economic stability?
2. Compare Why would the Federal Reserve enact an easy money policy? Why would it enact a tight money policy?
3. Analyze Information What is an inside lag, and why does it sometimes occur when using GDP to measure the business cycle?
4. Describe Why does monetary policy have such long outside lags?
5. Express Problems Clearly Why is it difficult to time the use of monetary policy in controlling business cycles?
418 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="485"> <text><![CDATA[Primary Sources
LAFS.1112.SL.1.3
The Role of Monetary Pollicy: Milton friedman
Milton Friedman was one of the leading economists of the 20th century. He disagreed with Keynes’s belief in government intervention in the economy. In this 1968 speech to the annual convention of American economists, he presents his point of view on monetary policy, or the role of the Federal Reserve System in regulating the money supply.
>> Economist Milton Friedman advocated a limited economic role for government.
There is wide agreement about the major goals of economic policy: high employment, stable prices, and rapid growth. There is less agreement that these goals are mutually compatible . . . There is least agreement about the role that various instruments
of policy can and should play in achieving the several goals.
My topic for tonight is the role of one such instrument—monetary policy. What can it contribute? And how should it be conducted
to contribute the most? . . . In the first flush of enthusiasm about the newly created Federal Reserve System, many observers attributed the relative stability of the 1920s to the System’s capacity for fine tuning . . . The Great Contraction destroyed this naive attitude. Opinion swung to the other extreme. Monetary policy was a string. You could pull on it
to stop inflation but you could not push on it to halt recession. You could lead a horse to water but you could not make him drink. . . .
dETERMINE MEANINg By raising interest rates, monetary policy discourages borrowing. By lowering interest rates, monetary policy encourages borrowing. What do you think Friedman means when he says “You could lead a horse to water but you could not make him drink”?
Keynes offered simultaneously an explanation
for the presumed impotence of monetary policy to stem the depression, a nonmonetary interpretation of the depression, and an alternative . . . —fiscal policy [policy on the government’s budget]. Government spending could make up for insufficient private investment. Tax reductions could undermine stubborn thriftiness. . . .
These views produced a widespread adoption
of cheap money policies after the war. And they received a rude shock when these policies failed
in country after country. . . Inflation, stimulated by cheap money policies . . . turned out to be the order of the day. The result was the beginning of a revival of belief in the potency [power] of monetary policy. . . .
dETERMINE MEANINg What does Friedman mean by “cheap money”?
The revival of belief in the potency of monetary policy was fostered also by a re-evaluation of the role money played from 1929 to 1933. Keynes . . . believed that the Great Contraction in the United States occurred despite aggressive expansionary policies by the monetary authorities—that they did their best but their best was not good enough. Recent studies have demonstrated that . . . the U.S. monetary authorities followed highly deflationary policies. . . . The Great
  9.5 The Effects of Monetary Policy 419]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="486"> <text><![CDATA[Primary Sources
Contraction is tragic testimony to the power of monetary policy—not, as Keynes and so many of his contemporaries believed, evidence of its impotence [powerlessness]. . . .
I. What Monetary Policy Cannot Do
From the infinite world of negation, I have selected two limitations of monetary policy to discuss: (1) It cannot peg interest rates for more than very limited periods; (2) It cannot peg the rate of unemployment for more than very limited periods . . .
II. What Monetary Policy Can Do
Monetary policy cannot peg these real magnitudes . . . But monetary policy can and does have important effects on these real magnitudes. The one is in no way inconsistent with the other.
The first and most important lesson that history teaches about what monetary policy can do . . . is that monetary policy can prevent money itself from being a major source of economic disturbance. . . .
A second thing monetary policy can do is provide a stable background for the economy—keep the machine well oiled . . . Our economic system will work best when producers and consumers, employers and employees, can proceed with full confidence that the average level of prices will behave in a known way in the future—preferably that it will be highly stable. . . .
Finally, monetary policy can contribute to offsetting major disturbances in the economic system arising from other sources. If there is
[a too-rapid expansion of investment,] monetary policy can . . . help to hold it in check by a slower
rate of monetary growth than would otherwise be desirable. If, as now, an explosive federal budget threatens unprecedented deficits, monetary policy can hold any inflationary dangers in check by a slower rate of monetary growth than would otherwise be desirable. . . .
dETERMINE AUThOR’S POINT Of VIEw Which monetary policy tool does Friedman seem to prefer: raising interest rates or lowering interest rates?
III. How Should Monetary Policy Be Conducted?
The first requirement is that the monetary authority should guide itself by magnitudes that it can control, not by ones that it cannot control. If, as the authority has often done, it takes interest rates or the current unemployment percentage as the immediate criterion of policy, it will be like a space vehicle that has taken a fix on the wrong star. . . .
A second requirement for monetary policy is that the monetary authority avoid sharp swings in policy. . . .
By setting itself a steady course and keeping to it, the monetary authority could make a major contribution to promoting economic stability. . . . That is the most that we can ask from monetary policy at our present stage of knowledge. But that much—and it is a great deal—is clearly within our reach.
ASSESSMENT
1. Identify Cause and Effect What does Friedman suggest results from trying to use monetary policy to reduce unemployment?
2. Determine an Author’s Purpose What was Friedman’s likely purpose in making this speech? Consider his audience.
3. Assess an Argument What is Friedman’s point of view on monetary policy? What reasoning, evidence, word choices, and speaking techniques does he use? How does he link ideas? What is his tone? Do you find his argument convincing or not? Explain.
Go ONLINE for primary sources
Savvas.com/FloridaSS
ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="487"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Go online to Savvas.com/FloridaSS and use the texts, quizzes, interactivities, Interactive Reading Notepads, Flipped Videos, and other resources from this Topic to prepare for the Topic Test. Etexts Quizzes Interactivities Interactive Reading Notepads Flipped Videos While online you can also check the progress you&apos;ve made learning the topic and course content by viewing your grades, test scores, and assignment status. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="488"> <text><![CDATA[Florida Topic 9 Quick Study Guide
LESSON SUMMARIES
Use these lesson summaries, and the longer versions available online, to review the key ideas for each lesson in this topic.
Lesson 1: The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy
ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1, SS.912.E.1.10
Fiscal policy is the use of taxes and government spending to influence the economy. The basic tool of fiscal policy is the federal budget, which lists income and planned spending. The federal budget requires approval by Congress and the President. Expansionary fiscal policy aims to increase output by raising spending, cutting taxes, or both. Contractionary policy aims to decrease output by cutting spending, raising taxes, or both. Issues such as the fixed amount of entitlements, political conflicts and difficulty forecasting the economy also make effective fiscal policy difficult.
Lesson 2: Fiscal Policy Options LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9, SS.912.E.1.10
Classical economics holds that, since free markets regulate themselves, there is little reason for fiscal policy. Keynesian economics argues for fiscal policy to increase or decrease demand, making use of the multiplier effect, where every dollar of government spending translates into several dollars spent in the economy. Supply-side economics focuses instead on stimulating supply by cutting taxes. The U.S. government has followed both approaches at different times.
Lesson 3: The National Debt and Deficits
LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, SS.912.E.2.9
When the government spends less than it receives in taxes, there is a budget surplus. When it spends more than it receives, there is a budget deficit. The government finances deficits by borrowing money, generally by
selling bonds. Deficits contribute to the national debt. Government debt carries risks. Policymakers have sought to reduce the national debt, but terrorism and financial crisis caused the debt to rise again during the 2000s.
Lesson 4: Monetary Policy Options LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, SS.912.E.1.11
Banks create money by lending it into existence. A multiplier effect increases the money supply by a multiple of the original loan. The Fed uses three main monetary policy tools to increase or decrease the money supply. The Fed can raise or lower the minimum reserve banks are required to keep. It can adjust the interest rate it charges banks. It can also use open market operations to buy or sell bonds on the market, thereby pushing interest rates down or up and enlarging or reducing the money supply. Open market operations are the main tool the Fed uses today.
Lesson 5: The Effects of Monetary Policy
SS.912.E.1.11, SS.912.E.3.6
Increasing the supply of money lowers its price, or interest rate. Lower interest rates encourage borrowing, investment, spending, and economic expansion. If the economy faces overexpansion or inflation, the Fed can push interest rates up to decrease the money supply. Because monetary policy changes have a delayed effect, timing those changes is difficult. Fed policymakers try to anticipate business cycles. Economists differ on whether fiscal policy or monetary policy is a better tool.
Go ONLINE for lesson summaries
        Savvas.com/FloridaSS
AUDIO READING GAMES ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="489"> <text><![CDATA[VISUAL REVIEW
Use these graphics to review some of the key terms and ideas from this topic.
Effects of Expansionary Fiscal Policy
To expand the economy, the government buys more goods and services.
Companies that sell goods to the government earn profits, which they use to pay their workers and investors more and to hire new workers.
Workers and investors have more money and spend more in shops and restaurants.
Shops and restaurants buy more goods and hire more workers to meet their needs.
In the short term, government spending leads to more jobs and more output.
Responsibilities of the Federal Reserve Board
  Responsibilities that serve government
  Maintain checking account for the Treasury Department Serve as financial agent for the Treasury Department Issue currency
Responsibilities that serve the banking system
Maintain check clearing system
Monitor bank reserves Approve or disapprove proposed bank mergers Lend money to banks Regulate the banking system
Responsibility for a stable monetary system
Regulate the money supply to stabilize the economy Alter the discount rate
Alter the federal funds rate Buy or sell government securities on the open market
Expansionary Fiscal Policy
GOAL
To raise the level
of economic output
INCREASE GOVERNMENT SPENDING
Spending increases aggregate demand, causing prices to rise and suppliers of goods and services to produce more.
To do this, firms will hire more workers.
TAX CUTS
Individuals keep more of their income and businesses keep more of their profits. Consumers and firms have more money
to spend.
423]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="490"> <text><![CDATA[Florida Topic 9 Assessment
KEY TERMS AND IDEAS
SS.912.E.1.10, SS.912.E.1.11, SS.912.E.3.6
1. What role does the federal budget play in fiscal policy?
2. Contrast expansionary policy with contractionary policy.
3. How do classical economics, Keynesian economics, and supply-side economics differ on fiscal policy?
4. How does the multiplier effect work?
5. What is the relation between a budget deficit and the
national debt?
6. What roles do the discount rate and open market
operations play in monetary policy?
7. How does the required reserve ratio, or reserve
requirement, affect the money multiplier formula?
8. How does monetarism differ from Keynesian
economics or supply-side economics?
CRITICAL THINKING
SS.912.E.1.10, SS.912.E.1.11, SS.912.E.2.9, SS.912.E.3.6
9. Identify Cause and Effect How do entitlement programs affect the creation of the federal budget?
10. Apply Concepts Which kind of fiscal policy do you think policymakers would use if GDP is down and the unemployment rate has increased? Explain.
11. Identify Steps in a Process How can the government use fiscal policy to promote price stability, full employment, and economic growth?
12. Compare Points of View Considering the policies advocated by classical economists, Keynesian economists, and supply-side economists and what you’ve learned about economic history, which approach do you think is most effective, and why?
13. Determine Point of View According to supply-side economists, how do tax cuts lead to economic growth?
14. Identify Cause and Effect How do changes in federal spending and taxation affect budget deficits and surpluses and the national debt?
15. Infer Why doesn’t the government simply increase the money supply to cover budget deficits?
16. Apply Concepts The equation below shows the effect of the required reserve ratio on the money supply. If the required reserve ratio is lowered, how does that affect the money supply?
17. Identify Steps in a Process What are the main tools of monetary policy, and how does the Fed use them to promote price stability, full employment, and economic growth?
18. Synthesize How does the required reserve ratio affect banks’ profits?
19. Contrast What is the key difference between
the views of monetarist economists and those of Keynesian or supply-side economists? Explain which view you think is correct.
20. Support Ideas With Examples What will happen if a monetary policy is chosen based on existing trends, but those trends reverse before the monetary policy takes effect? Support your argument with an example.
21. Writing Activity In this topic, you learned about the views of different economists on fiscal and monetary policy. Using reliable sources, research the views of one of the economists mentioned in your text and policy debates about a current economic issue. Explain what policies you think this economist would have advocated to deal with the issue.

MONEY MULTIPLIER FORMULA
       INITIAL CASH DEPOSIT
1 INCREASE
REQUIRED RESERVE       IN MONEY
RATIO (RRR)
 SUPPLY
         424 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy
EXAMPLE   $1,000
1
0.1
$10,000
INCREASE IN MONEY SUPPLY
424 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="491"> <text><![CDATA[DOCUMENT-BASED QUESTIONS
LAFS.1112.RH.1.3, SS.912.E.1.11
In 2007, the nation was hit by a severe recession. The federal government applied monetary policy tools.
DOCUMENT A
This timeline highlights key steps in the government’s response to the beginnings of the Great Recession.
 September 2007
January 2008
February 2008
March 2008
April 2008
October 2008
December 2008
February 2009
Federal Open Market Committee (FOMC) lowers federal funds fate to 4.75%.
FOMC lowers federal funds rate to 3%.
President Bush signs Economic Stimulus Act, giving tax rebates and breaks to many.
Federal Reserve offers up to $200 billion in loans to financial institutions.
FOMC lowers federal funds rate to 2%.
Bush signs law creating $700 billion fund to help financial institutions.
FOMC says federal funds rate will be 0-0.25% until further notice.
President Obama signs Recovery and Reinvestment Act, with $787 billion in federal spending.
DOCUMENT B
In 2008, President George W. Bush signed the Economic Stimulus Act into law with this statement.
The bill I’m signing today is large enough to have an impact—amounting to more than $152 billion this year, or about 1 percent of GDP. The bill provides temporary tax incentives for businesses to make investments in their companies so that we create new jobs this year. The bill provides individual tax relief in the form of tax rebates. These rebates will amount to as much as $600 for individuals and $1,200 for married couples, with additional rebates for families with children.
—President George W. Bush, February 13, 2008
DOCUMENT C
One of the most controversial federal actions was passage of the Troubled Asset Relief Program, or TARP, a bailout plan for financial institutions. This editorial in a noted news magazine supported TARP.
The economics behind this is sound. Government support to the banking system can break the cycle of panic and pessimism that threatens to suck the economy into deep recession. Intervention may help taxpayers,
because they are also employees and consumers. Although $700 billion is a lot—about 6% of GDP—some of it will be earned back and it is small compared with the 16% of GDP that banking crises typically swallow . . .
—The Economist, September 25, 2008
DOCUMENT D
This attack on TARP came from an organization that opposes government interference in the economy.
The TARP was crooked from the very start, using taxpayer funds to bail out some of the world’s richest people from their own foolish investments. The claims that it made taxpayers money are unfounded. Even worse, TARP taught investment bankers an important lesson: During a boom, make as much money as
you can, no matter how short-term the profits will be. When the bubble pops, the Treasury and Fed will be there with a taxpayer-funded pillow.
—Robert P. Murphy, “Was TARP Good for the Taxpayers?” Ludwig Van Mises Institute, October 7, 2010
22. According to Document A, what type of government intervention in the economy did the actions in 2007 by the FOMC represent?
A. tax policy
B. business regulation C. monetary policy
D. fiscal policy
23. Based on Document B, what steps did the Bush Administration support for stimulating the economy and providing jobs?
A. raising taxes
B. doing away with Fanny Mae and Freddie Mac C. supporting massive new government spending D. providing tax incentives and rebates
24. Which document most clearly supports the idea that government action during the recession mainly benefited the wealthy?
A. Document A
B. Document B C. Document C D. Document D
25. Writing Task In a brief essay, contrast points of view on federal government responses to the Great Recession. Assess the authors’ claims, reasoning, and evidence. Determine which source best confirms what you have learned in your text, noting where the text leaves matters uncertain. Finally, explain which viewpoint you find more convincing.
Go ONLINE to practice 
Savvas.com/FloridaSS
ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="492"> <text><![CDATA[ Go ONLINE for digital resources
         Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO AUDIO ETEXT ACTIVITY WRITING GAMES PDF ASSESSMENT
[ ESSENTIAL QUESTION ] How might scarcity divide our world or bring it together?
 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="493"> <text><![CDATA[Next Generation Sunshine State Standards
SS.912.E.2.12, SS.912.E.3.2, SS.912.E.3.3, SS.912.E.3.4, SS.912.E.3.5, SS.912.G.2.2, SS.912.G.3.3, SS.912.G.4.4, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.SL.1.2, LAFS.1112.SL.1.3, LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10
Enduring Understandings
• Asglobaltradeincreases,nationshavebecome economically interdependent.
• Nationsusetradebarriersandagreementsto protect their economic interests.
• Nationsuseeconomicdatasuchasexchange rates to guide decision making.
• Thelevelofeconomicdevelopmentaffectsevery nation’s standard of living, as measured by such standards as the adequacy of diet and shelter.
• Inrecentdecades,theeconomiesofmany countries have been growing and changing in critical ways.
• Globalizationpresentsopportunitiesfor economic growth around the world, but it also presents social and economic challenges.
>> Cranes and freight containers move huge amounts of goods in today’s globalized economy.
 To compare market and command economies in action.
 Bounce to Activate My Story Video
 427]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="494"> <text><![CDATA[Florida Topic 10 Overview
In this topic, you will learn about how trade and globalization affect the world. Look at the lesson outline and explore the map. As you study this topic, you’ll complete the quest team project.
LESSON OUTLINE
10.1 Why Nations Trade SS.912.E.2.12, SS.912.E.3.2, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10
10.2 Trade Barriers and Agreements SS.912.E.3.3
10.3 Exchange Rates and Trade SS.912.E.3.5, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10
10.4 Development
SS.912.E.3.4, SS.912.E.3.5, SS.912.G.2.2
10.5 Growth, Resources, and Development
SS.912.G.2.2, SS.912.G.4.4
10.6 Changing Economies LAFS.1112.RH.4.10
10.7 Globalization SS.912.G.3.3, SS.912.G.4.4, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10
Top 10 U.S. Trading Partners, 2010
 SOUTH KOREA
$87.7
CHINA
$456.8

TAIWAN
$61.9

JAPAN
$181.0

CANADA
$526.8
UNITED STATES
MEXICO
$393.4
UNITED KINGDOM $98.2
GERMANY
$130.6
BRAZIL
$59.4
FRANCE
$65.3
KEY
Volume of U.S. Imports and
Exports in $U.S. billions
428 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="495"> <text><![CDATA[TEAM PROJECT
 Civic Action Project
The chances are good that at least one item you are wearing or carrying was manufactured in another country and shipped to the United States. In this quest, you will conduct a service project on the ways in which global trade affects our world today.
    STEP 1
What is an issue you
care about? Research an economic issue
at the local, state,
or federal level, then analyze existing public policy solutions. Are they sufficient?
STEP 2 Brainstorm! Come up with some new ways to address the issue. Seek out experts or reliable sources on this issue and get their input. How can you improve the situation?
STEP 3 Ramp up interest!
Raise awareness through opinion polls, a web site, social media, or fliers. Try
to get your local newspaper, radio, and television to cover the issue.
STEP 4 Make something
happen! Build support for your plan with
a petition, panel discussion, and letters to or meetings with public officials.
NGSSS
ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1, ELD.K12.ELL.SS.1, LAFS.1112.SL.2.4
Go ONLINE for complete Quest materials
Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO ETEXT WRITING RUBRIC PDF ASSESSMENT 429 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="496"> <text><![CDATA[  10.1
Have you used a computer or bought a pair of jeans lately? The chances are good that the computer and the jeans were made outside the United States. But why do Americans buy so many goods from overseas? Wouldn’t it make a lot more sense for us to produce everything we need ourselves?
>> The United States is a major exporter of crops. The use of labor-saving machines and sophisticated technology combine with good soil and climate to make American farms among the world’s most productive.
NGSSS
SS.912.E.2.12, SS.912.E.3.2, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10
>> Objectives
Evaluate the impact of the unequal
distribution of resources.
Analyze the concepts of specialization and comparative advantage to explain why nations trade.
Summarize the position of the United States in world trade.
Describe the effects of trade on employment.
>> Key Terms export
import
absolute advantage comparative
advantage
law of comparative
advantage interdependence

Why Nations Trade
Resource Distribution and Specialization
The answer to these questions lies in two economic ideas you already know about: factors of production and scarcity. By looking at two odd products—birdhouses and T-shirts—you can better understand why nations trade.
As you learned earlier, the resources that are used to make goods and services are called the factors of production. They include land (natural resources), labor, and capital (both physical and human). Because these resources are scarce, countries have to choose how to use their factors of production to produce particular goods.
Because they cannot produce all goods with their scarce resources, they need to obtain those they do not produce somehow. Trade is how countries obtain those goods they do not produce.
Natural Resources Natural resources, along with climate and geographic location, help determine what goods and services
an economy produces. Fertile soil and a good growing climate allowed the central United States to develop an economy based on agriculture. Much of Southwest Asia—with scarce farmland and water but large reserves of oil and natural gas—has an economy 
Go ONLINE for digital resources
                    Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="497"> <text><![CDATA[based on extracting and selling these energy resources.
Capital and Labor Capital and labor also shape
a region’s economy. Physical capital includes the things that people make in order to produce final goods and services. Machinery, tractors, computers, and factories are examples of physical capital, as are the transportation and communication networks that allow the flow of goods and information. Capital also includes the money needed to invest in businesses and use natural resources.
Human capital differs from labor. Labor refers
to the size of a nation’s workforce. Human capital
is the knowledge and skills a worker gains through education and experience. Every job requires human capital. A surgeon must learn anatomy and how to use a scalpel. A taxi driver must memorize the layout of a city’s streets.
One way to measure a nation’s human capital is to look at the general educational level of the populace. A country whose citizens have more schooling than those of another country has more human capital.
Unequal Resource Distribution As Figure 10.1 shows, the availability of resources differs greatly
from one country to another. For example, Nigeria has less than three quarters the land area of Peru but more than ten times the arable land and six times the population. This suggests that Nigeria has more human capital and land that can be farmed than Peru does.
A nation’s ability to exploit, or use, its physical resources is affected by culture and history. For example, prolonged warfare may severely damage a nation’s farms, forests, and transportation systems. History and culture affect human resources as well. In colonial America, a labor shortage led to the establishment of slavery. Today, a culture that bans education of women wastes much of its potential human capital.
Specialization and Trade Unequal distribution of resources creates a need for specialization. (As you have read, specialization occurs when individuals, businesses, or nations produce only certain goods and services.) In the United States, we grow wheat, corn, and other crops for which we have suitable soil and climate conditions. However, we cannot grow large quantities of coffee or bananas.
When nations specialize in certain goods, they obtain the goods they do not or cannot produce through importing and exporting. An export is a good or service sent to another country for sale.
Resource Distribution
Total area (sq km)
Arable land (%)
Natural resources
Population
Labor force
Literacy rate
Telephones
Airports
INDIA
3,287,263 sq km
47.9%
coal, iron ore, manganese, mica, bauxite, rare earth elements, titanium ore, chromite, natural gas, diamonds, petroleum, limestone, arable land
1,220.8 million
486.6 million
62.8%
Main: 31.1 million Cellular: 893.9 million
346
NIGERIA
923,768 sq km
39.0%
natural gas, petroleum, tin, iron ore, coal, limestone, niobium, lead, zinc, arable land
174.5 million
51.53 million
61.3%
Main: 418,200 Cellular: 112.8 million
54
PERU
1,285,216 sq km
2.8%
copper, silver, gold, petroleum, timber, fish, iron ore, coal, phosphate, potash, hydropower, natural gas
29.8 million
16.2 million
89.6%
Main: 3.4 million Cellular: 29.4 million
191
UNITED STATES
9,826,675 sq km
16.3%
coal, copper, lead, molybdenum, phosphates, rare earth elements, uranium, bauxite, gold, iron, mercury, nickel, potash, silver, tungsten, zinc, petroleum, natural gas, timber
316.4 million
155 million
99%
Main: 139 million Cellular: 310 million
13,513
SOURCE: CIA World Factbook
>> Figure 10.1 Analyze Charts Which factors of production does India have in abundance? Which factors of production does it lack in comparison to the United States?
Bounce to Activate Gallery
10.1 Why Nations Trade 431]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="498"> <text><![CDATA[An import is a good or service brought in from another country for sale. For example, Costa Rica specializes in growing and exporting coffee. The nation uses the money earned from selling coffee to import goods that it does not produce.
In some cases, more than 70 percent of a nation’s export trade depends upon a single resource. Examples include Kuwait (petroleum and natural gas), Guinea-Bissau (cashews), and the Marshall Islands (fish).
SUMMARIzE Why are scarcity and choice basic economic problems faced by every country?
Absolute and Comparative Advantage
Suppose a nation enjoys an abundance of resources, including a rich natural environment, an educated workforce, and the latest technologies. In theory, such a nation could be self-sufficient, producing almost all that it needs by itself. Why, then, would it choose to engage in foreign trade?
Although self-sufficiency may sound appealing, it is actually better for countries to specialize in some products and trade for others. To see why, you need to look at two related concepts—absolute advantage and comparative advantage. A person or nation has an absolute advantage when it can produce more of a given product than another person or nation using a given amount of resources.
Explaining Absolute Advantage A simple example can illustrate the idea of absolute advantage. Suppose that two people, Jenny and Carlos, work at making both birdhouses and printed T-shirts. In one hour, Carlos can either print six T-shirts or make two birdhouses. (See Figure 10.2.) Jenny can print one T-shirt or make one birdhouse per hour. In other words, Carlos is more productive than Jenny in making both T-shirts and birdhouses. In economic terms, Carlos has an absolute advantage over Jenny in producing both goods.
Because Carlos enjoys an absolute advantage
in both goods, should he remain self-sufficient? Or would he be better off specializing in either T-shirts or birdhouses? What about Jenny? Should she make T-shirts, birdhouses, or both?
Countries have to face the same sorts of questions. Should a wealthy country with many resources be self-sufficient, or should it specialize in producing a few products and trade for the others? How does a poorer nation decide what to produce? The answers to these questions lie with the concept of comparative advantage.
Explaining Comparative Advantage Early in the nineteenth century, British economist David Ricardo argued that the key to determining which country should produce which goods is opportunity cost. Remember that opportunity cost is what you give up in order to produce a certain product.
A country has a comparative advantage in the product that it can produce most efficiently given all the products it could choose to produce. It is the nation with the comparative advantage—not necessarily the one with the absolute advantage— that should specialize in producing that good.
According to the law of comparative advantage, a nation is better off when it produces goods and services for which it has a comparative advantage. Each nation can then use the money it earns selling those goods and services to buy those that it cannot produce as efficiently.
Opportunity Cost and Comparative Advantage
To see how comparative advantage works, look again at Figure 10.2. It shows the opportunity costs of producing T-shirts and birdhouses for both Carlos and Jenny.
• Carlos’s opportunity costs In an hour, Carlos can make either six T-shirts or two birdhouses. He therefore sacrifices three T-shirts for every birdhouse he produces. In terms of opportunity cost, the opportunity cost of a birdhouse is the three T-shirts
he could have produced instead. The opportunity cost of a T-shirt is one third of a birdhouse.
Productivity and Opportunity Cost
 
CARLOS
JENNY
T-shirts per hour
6
1
Birdhouses per hour
2
1
Opportunity cost of one T-shirt
13 birdhouse
 1 birdhouse
 
 Opportunity cost of one birdhouse
3 T-shirts
1 T-shirt
>> Figure 10.2 Analyze Charts How many T-shirts can Carlos make in the time it takes Jenny to make five T-shirts?
432 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization
]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="499"> <text><![CDATA[ DAVID RICARDO ON COMPARATIVE ADVANTAGE
   “England may be so circumstanced, that to produce the cloth may require the labor of 100 men for one year; and if she attempted to make the wine, it might require the labor of 120 men for the same time.
England would therefore find it in her interest to import wine, and to purchase it by the exportation of cloth.
To produce the wine in Portugal, might require only the labor of 80 men for one year, and to produce the cloth in the same country, might require the labor of 90 men for the same time.
It would therefore be advantageous for
her to export wine in exchange for cloth . . . notwithstanding that the commodity imported by Portugal could be produced there with less labor than in England.”
— David Ricardo,1817
>> Analyze Information Why does Ricardo think Portugal should import cloth from England and produce wine rather than producing both?

Jenny’s opportunity costs In an hour, Jenny
can make either one T-shirt or one birdhouse. Therefore, her opportunity cost for one birdhouse is one T-shirt, and her opportunity cost for one T-shirt is one birdhouse.
According to the law of comparative advantage,
each person should produce the good for which he or she has a lower opportunity cost than other producers. Carlos’s opportunity cost for producing a T-shirt (one third of a birdhouse) is lower than Jenny’s (one birdhouse), so it is sensible for Carlos to produce T-shirts. Jenny’s opportunity cost for producing a birdhouse (one T-shirt) is lower than Carlos’s (three T-shirts), so Jenny should produce birdhouses.
The Mutual Benefits of Specialization If Carlos wants a birdhouse, he can either make it himself or make T-shirts and trade some of them to Jenny for a birdhouse. Suppose Carlos and Jenny agree to trade two T-shirts for one birdhouse. In this case, Carlos is clearly better off producing T-shirts and trading for a birdhouse. After all, in the time he would have used to make his own birdhouse, he can make three T-shirts. Since he pays Jenny only two T-shirts for
a birdhouse, he has a T-shirt left over. Trade makes Carlos better off by one T-shirt.
Jenny is also better off as a result of trade. She can make two birdhouses in the time she would need to produce two T-shirts for herself. Since
she only pays one birdhouse to Carlos for the two T-shirts, she will still have one birdhouse left over. Trade makes her better off by one birdhouse.
Carlos and Jenny both benefit from trade. Each person specializes in producing the good for which he or she has a comparative advantage. Since both producers are operating at greater efficiency, more total goods are produced overall. After the trade, each of them is left with an extra unit of the good originally produced, which can be used to trade for other goods.
APPLy CONCEPTS How is opportunity cost related to comparative advantage?
Comparative Advantage and World Trade
The lessons from the example of Carlos and Jenny also apply to trade between nations. As you read, David Ricardo argued that the nation having the lower opportunity cost in producing a good has a comparative advantage in producing that good. It is the nation with the comparative advantage in
 10.1 Why Nations Trade 433]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="500"> <text><![CDATA[producing a good—not necessarily the absolute advantage—that should specialize in producing that good. It carries out that trade by shipping its goods to other countries and allowing them to ship goods to it.
Comparative Advantage in Action Suppose two countries, A and B, are capable of producing both bananas and sugar. However, Country A’s climate and land are somewhat more suitable for growing bananas. For Country A, the opportunity cost of a ton of bananas is two tons of sugar.
For Country B, the opportunity cost of a ton of bananas is three tons of sugar. Since Country A
has a lower opportunity cost than does Country
B, Country A has a comparative advantage in producing bananas. It should therefore specialize
in growing bananas and exporting them to the world market. Trade allows countries to obtain goods for which they might have a high opportunity cost. Thus, Country A can use the money it earns from exporting bananas to import other goods and services that it cannot produce for itself as efficiently as other countries. If a country focuses its resources on producing certain goods, it can make more of
them. This is one way that trade causes economic growth.
Growing Interdependence The growth of international trade has led to greater economic interdependence among nations. Interdependence is the shared need of countries for the resources, goods, services, labor, and knowledge supplied by other countries.
Because countries are interdependent, changes in one country’s economy influence other economies. For example, a drought in Brazil would hurt that country’s coffee growers. Coffee growers in Costa Rica or Colombia may benefit, though, because they would be able to sell more of their product on the world market.
Another example of interdependence can be seen when one country experiences economic growth. Suppose that Mexico’s economy grows, resulting in more jobs and higher wages for Mexican workers. With more income, these workers are likely to have greater demand for goods. By buying some of those goods from other countries, Mexico would be helping the economies of its trading partners to grow.
IdENTIfy CENTRAL ISSUES How does comparative advantage explain why countries trade?
The United States and Its Trading Partners
The United States enjoys a comparative advantage in producing many goods and services. What, then, is its position as an importer and exporter, and what is the impact of that trade?
The Impact of U.S. Exports The United States exports more goods than any other country except China. (The 28-nation European Union exports more than the United States, but less than China.) One reason is the wide range of its export products, from soybeans to telecommunications equipment. Another reason is that the United States excels
in technologically sophisticated goods such as software, chemicals, and medical testing supplies.
Goods make up the bulk of international trade, but the United States is also the world’s leading exporter of services. These include education, computer and data processing, financial services, and medical care. Exports of services have grown rapidly in recent decades. U.S. cultural exports such as movies, television shows, and popular music have an economic impact. American movies
>> Cities, as well as countries, produce goods in which they have a comparative advantage. The skilled weavers in Cuenca, Ecuador, make Panama hats that sell for hundreds of dollars overseas.
434 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="501"> <text><![CDATA[Top U.S. Exports
   49.0%
9.2% 26.8% 15.0%
SOURCE: CIA World Factbook
Capital goods
(transistors, aircraft, motor vehicle parts, computers, telecommunications equipment)
Industrial supplies (organic chemicals)
Consumer goods (automobiles, medicines)
Agricultural products (soybeans, fruit, corn)
>> Figure 10.3 Analyze Graphs What two categories make up more than
three quarters of U.S. exports?
Bounce to Activate Map
capture about two thirds of ticket sales in Western Europe, creating difficulties for domestic production companies. These pop culture exports also have a cultural impact. They can convey particular images of the American lifestyle and values, introducing new ideas to people of other cultures.
The leading trading partners for U.S. exports
are Canada, Mexico, China, and Japan. Nearly
half of all exports are capital goods—transistors, aircraft, motor vehicle parts, computers, and telecommunications equipment. Another quarter are industrial supplies, with the remainder coming from consumer goods and agricultural products. Sometimes these exports provide goods that the country could not produce on its own. Sometimes, though, U.S. products compete with locally produced goods, and low-cost U.S. products have an impact on local suppliers. For instance, U.S. exports of corn to Mexico have surged in recent years. Competition from these products has cut the income of as many as 3 million Mexican farmers, according to some estimates.
The Impact of U.S. Imports The United States is also the world’s top importing country—by a significant amount. U.S. imports total nearly $2.3 trillion, $600 billion more than China, the next biggest importer.
Where do most goods imported into the United States come from? As you might expect, Canada and Mexico provide a significant share of U.S. imports. These neighbors and trading partners have
Bounce to Activate Map
a significant impact on the U.S. economy, literally helping to fuel it. Canada and Mexico are the second and third leading suppliers of energy to the United States, after Saudi Arabia.
While Canada and Mexico account for a quarter of U.S. imports, China has become the leading source of U.S. imports. Chinese imports give consumers access to goods they want at lower prices than they would have to pay if made in the United States or imported from another source. Rising U.S. imports from China have also helped fuel China’s economic growth.
CONNECT What impact do you think the United States has had on China’s manufacturing sector? Why?
The Impact of Trade on Jobs
Trade allows nations to specialize in producing a limited number of goods while consuming a greater variety of goods. However, specialization can also dramatically affect a nation’s employment patterns.
Specialization and Job Loss To help you better understand the effects of international trade on employment, think back to the example of Carlos and Jenny. Remember that Carlos can make six T-shirts or two birdhouses by himself in an hour. Suppose
10.1 Why Nations Trade 435]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="502"> <text><![CDATA[he hires Amy to help him build birdhouses. He later realizes that he should specialize only in T-shirts since that is where his comparative advantage lies. Since he no longer needs Amy to help him make birdhouses, he fires her.
Up to this point, Amy has specialized in the skills needed to make birdhouses. These skills are no longer in demand where she lives.
• Amy can gain new job skills that are more in demand. She might and learn to make T-shirts or some other product.
• Amy can move to another location where her existing skills are still in demand.
• Amy can stay where she is and take a job that calls for lesser skills. In this case, she might well earn less money than she did making birdhouses.
• If Amy takes none of these three options, she will be unemployed.
Trade and Employment in the United States
Carlos’s decision to focus on his comparative advantage and specialize in making T-shirts had an impact on Amy’s economic well-being. In the same way, the comparative advantage of nations affects the economic well-being of workers living in those nations.
International trade has led to significant changes in U.S. employment patterns. During the 1970s,
for example, high worker productivity and new technologies like robotics helped give Japan a comparative advantage in making automobiles. American car companies lost business. Falling sales led them to reduce their workforce, costing many American autoworkers their jobs.
Businesses and government often provide help to retrain laid-off workers or assist them in relocating. In some cases, however, retraining or relocation is not possible. Some workers may be forced to take lower-paying jobs or face prolonged unemployment.
Trade can also result in the creation of new
jobs. If American exports grow, there will be
more demand for workers to make those products. President Obama said in his 2010 State of the Union Address:
The more products we make and sell to other countries, the more jobs we support right here in America.
—President Barack Obama
SyNThESIzE What advantages does a person who is retrained for a new industry have versus a person who relocates to get a job?

PRODUCT MARKET
Households
Non-Financial Firms
Expenditures
Foreign Firms and Households
 Expenditures
Government
  
Taxes         Taxes
Financial Institutions
         FACTOR MARKET
           >> Figure 10.4 Analyze Charts How might international trade contribute to economic growth?
436 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="503"> <text><![CDATA[ A Circular Flow Model
Including Finance and
Trade
Earlier, you learned how a circular flow model of a mixed economy can show transactions between firms, households and governments. See Figure 2.10 for a model of these flows.
Now that you have learned how financial institutions function and how international trade affects the economy, you will see how a circular flow model for an open-market economy can show flows between households, firms, government, financial institutions, and product and factor markets. The model can also show flows between domestic and international firms through international trade.
Financial Institutions and the Circular Flow
As you have learned, financial institutions operate mainly in the factor market for capital. Financial institutions take in savings from households, government and firms.
Financial institutions put these savings to work in the form of investments in firms and lending to households and governments. Figure 10.4 shows the flows of savings to financial institutions in purple and investments by financial institutions in black.
International Trade and the Circular Flow The circular flow of products and factors also includes international trade. Exports are products that move from firms in this country to foreign firms and households. Imports are products that move from foreign firms to firms in this country, and from them to households.
Foreign firms and households also send savings to financial institutions. In turn, financial institutions
put those savings to work in the form of investments in foreign firms and lending to foreign households. Figure 10.4 also shows these flows.
In fact, international trade helps to increase
the flow of goods and factors through a country’s markets. It does this by increasing the size of the market in which that country’s firms and households can participate and through the principle of comparative advantage.
Comparative advantage increases these flows by enlarging markets for goods and services in which a country’s firms have a comparative advantage and by creating savings when that country imports goods and services in which another country has a comparative advantage.
dRAW INfERENCES How do financial institutions promote international trade, according to the circular flow model?
ASSESSMENT
1. Apply Concepts How does the unequal distribution of resources help explain why nations specialize in producing certain goods?
2. Contrast How does comparative advantage contrast with absolute advantage?
3. Make Generalizations Why do countries trade, and what determines what they trade?
4. Identify Central Ideas What is the impact of U.S. exports on the United States and its trading partners?
5. Identify Central Ideas What is the impact of U.S. imports on the United States and its trading partners?
10.1 Why Nations Trade 437]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="504"> <text><![CDATA[ 10.2
Would you take part in marches and strikes to protest against a trade policy? That’s what more than 200,000 citizens of Colombia did in a nationwide strike in August 2013. Blocking roads, the marchers voiced opposition to the U.S.–Colombia Trade Promotion Agreement. To these protesters, trade policy was not just an economic idea; it had a major impact on their lives. And the same is true of you—whether you know it or not.
>> In 2013 demonstrators in Thailand protested talks on a free trade agreement between Thailand and the European Union. Farmers feared that extended patents on plant varieties would force them to pay more for seeds.
 Bounce to Activate Flipped Video
 NGSSS
SS.912.E.3.3
>> Objectives
Describe the policies nations use to control
or direct international trade.
Analyze the effects of international trade agreements.
Summarize the arguments for and against free international trade.
Explain the role of multinational corporations in the process of globalization.
>> Key Terms trade barrier
tariff
import quota sanctions embargo
trade war protectionism infant industry free trade
free trade zone World Trade
Organization
Trade Barriers and
Agreements
Free Trade and Trade Barriers
Today, many people favor increased foreign trade, while others fear its effects. To understand why, you need to understand the kinds of barriers that nations sometimes erect to trade. In this section, you will also see how trade policies may affect what you pay for dozens of products, from chocolate to cars.
A trade barrier, or trade restriction, is a means of preventing a foreign product or service from freely entering a nation’s territory. Trade barriers take several forms and may be used for various purposes.
Tariffs One common trade barrier is a tariff, or a tax on imported goods. Until the early 1900s, tariffs were a major tool of fiscal policy in the United States and the main source of revenue for the federal government. As you can see from Figure 10.5, however, tariffs today are much lower. Still, the United States continues
to collect tariffs on steel, foreign-made cars, and many other products.
If you have traveled abroad, you may have had to pay a tax on foreign goods you brought back to the United States. These customs duties are another form of tariff.
Go ONLINE for digital resources
                    Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="505"> <text><![CDATA[Quotas and VERs Another kind of barrier is an import quota. Import quotas place a limit on
the amount of a good that can be imported. For example, the United States limits the annual amount of raw cotton coming into the country from other nations. Many import quotas are now illegal under international trade laws.
Tariffs and quotas are laws set by the importing country. By contrast, a voluntary export restraint (VER) is a voluntary limit set by the exporting country, restricting the quantity of a product it will sell to another country. A nation that adopts a VER seeks to reduce the risk that the importing country will impose damaging trade barriers itself.
Other Barriers to Trade Other government actions may also create trade barriers. For example, a government may require foreign companies to obtain a license to sell goods in that country. High licensing fees and slow licensing processes act as informal trade barriers.
Health, safety, or environmental regulations can also act as trade barriers. Suppose a nation treats
the fruit it grows with a particular insecticide. Another nation might ban any fruit treated with that insecticide in order to discourage imports of foreign fruit. The U.S. antipollution standard that requires cars to be equipped with catalytic converters
is another example. Cars that do not meet this requirement cannot be exported to the United States.
Finally, a nation may impose trade barriers and other economic sanctions for political reasons. Sanctions are actions a nation or group of nations takes in order to punish or put pressure on another nation. For example, in the 1960s, the United States banned all trade with Cuba. The purpose of this trade embargo was to cause economic strain that might weaken Cuba’s communist dictatorship.
An embargo is an official ban on trade or other commercial activity with a country.
COMPARE ANd CONTRAST How are voluntary export restraints and import quotas different?
Effects of Trade Barriers
By limiting supply, trade barriers can have very different effects on domestic producers and consumers. Trade barriers may also create tense relations between importing and exporting countries.
Higher Prices for Foreign Goods Trade barriers can help domestic producers compete with foreign firms. By limiting imports from those firms, or by making the prices of those imports higher, trade barriers give a competitive advantage to domestic companies.
Although domestic producers may benefit, consumers can lose out. Restrictions on imports result in higher prices. For example, suppose the
Average Tariff Rates, 1900–2010
Rate (as a percentage of total imports)
 60
50
40
30
20
10
0
1900 1910
1920 1930
1940
1950 1960 1970
Year
1980 1990
2000 2010
>> Figure 10.5 Analyze Graphs Describe what has happened to tariff rates since 1950 versus the period from 1900 to 1950.
10.2 Trade Barriers and Agreements 439]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="506"> <text><![CDATA[ market price of an imported car is $20,000. If the government places a 10-percent tariff on all imported foreign cars, the price of the average imported car would increase from $20,000 to $22,000. Consumers who bought such a vehicle would be paying a higher price than if there had been no tariff. Also, with foreign competition limited, domestic carmakers would have no incentive to keep prices low.
Trade Wars Trade barriers may also fuel international conflict. When one country restricts imports, its trading partner may retaliate by placing its own restrictions on imports. If the first country responds with further trade limits, the result is a trade war, a cycle of escalating trade barriers. Trade wars often cause economic hardship for both sides.
Probably the most damaging trade war
in American history began during the Great Depression. In 1930, Congress passed the Smoot- Hawley Act, raising average tariff rates on all imports to 50 percent. Congress hoped the tariff would protect American workers and businesses from foreign competition and help the economy rebound.
The reverse effect took place, though.
Other countries responded by raising tariffs on American-made goods. The resulting trade war decreased international trade and deepened the worldwide depression. Most economists blame
the Smoot-Hawley tariff for increasing American unemployment.
Trade wars still occur, but they usually involve
a few products rather than all imports. In 2002,
the United States placed temporary tariffs on imported steel to help American steelmakers recover from bankruptcy. European nations threatened
to retaliate. This “steel war” ended when an international panel ruled that the tariffs were illegal.
IdENTIfy CAUSE ANd EffECT Why are trade wars harmful?
Arguments for Protectionism
Why does a nation impose trade barriers? One reason is protectionism, the use of trade barriers to shield domestic industries from foreign competition. Protectionists have generally used three main arguments to support their view: saving jobs, protecting infant industries, and safeguarding national security.
Protecting Jobs One argument for protectionism is that it shelters workers in industries that may be hurt by foreign competition. Suppose that certain East Asian nations had a comparative advantage in producing textiles. If the United States cut tariffs
Beef Wars: Protectionism or Health Concern?
1985
EU bans import of beef treated with growth hormones.
2012
An agreement is reached to end the U.S. tariffs and allow U.S. beef to be imported to the EU.
2010 2015
  1996
World Trade Organization orders the EU to remove the beef ban.
          
1985 1990 1995 2000 2005
          SOURCE: CNN, Library of Congress, BBC
1989
U.S. imposes tariffs on
1999
EU refuses to lift ban. U.S. doubles tariffs on: • Truffles • Liver pate • Jam
• Tomatoes • Roquefort cheese • Mustard
• Tomatoes • Citrus fruits
• Pasta • Ham
>> Analyze Charts How long did the Beef Wars last? Who do you think won the wars?
440 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="507"> <text><![CDATA[on textile imports, domestic manufacturers might find it hard to compete with imports from East Asia. They would have to close their factories and lay off workers.
Ideally, the laid-off workers would take new jobs in other industries. In practice, however, many of these workers would find retraining or relocation difficult. In addition, few industry or political leaders want to see existing industries shut down or large numbers of people lose their jobs. For this reason, public officials might favor protectionism to keep companies alive and people working.
Protecting Infant Industries Another argument for protectionism is that industries in the early stages of development need time and experience to become efficient producers. Tariffs that raise the price of imported goods provide a period of time for these infant industries to become more competitive. Once that happens, the tariff can be eliminated.
In the early years of the United States, Alexander Hamilton favored using tariffs to protect young American industries from European competition. Today, many developing nations adopt protectionist policies for similar reasons:
Global economic competition is
a game of unequal players. It pits against each other countries that range from Switzerland to Swaziland. . . . It is only fair that we ‘tilt the playing field’ in favor of the weaker countries. In practice, this means allowing them to protect . . . their producers more vigorously.
—Ha-Joon Chang, “Protecting the Global Poor”
Three problems may arise with such protective tariffs, however. First, a protected infant industry may lack the incentive to “grow up,” that is, to become more efficient and competitive. Second, once an industry has been given tariff protection, lawmakers may find it difficult for political reasons to take the protections away. Third, a protected industry can keep its prices relatively high, increasing costs to consumers.
Safeguarding National Security Certain industries may require protection because their products are essential to defending the country. In the event of a war, the United States would need an
>> The slogan “Buy American” is used to encourage Americans to spend their money on products made in the U.S. This more directly supports American industries and workers.
 >> Analyze Political Cartoons What do the size and the attitude of the baby tell about the pitfalls of protecting infant industries?
 10.2 Trade Barriers and Agreements 441]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="508"> <text><![CDATA[uninterrupted supply of steel, energy, and advanced technologies. For this reason, the government wants to ensure that such domestic industries remain active.
Foes of trade barriers agree that protecting defense industries is important. They argue, however, that some industries that seek protection are not really essential to national security.
SUPPORT A POINT Of VIEW WITh EVIdENCE What are the three arguments given for protectionism?
Trade Agreements
In opposition to protectionism is the principle of free trade. Free trade involves the lowering or elimination of protective tariffs and other trade barriers between two or more nations. Supporters argue that free trade is the best way to pursue comparative advantage, raise living standards, and further cooperative relationships among nations.
To encourage free trade, a number of countries in recent decades have signed international free trade agreements. Some of these pacts involve dozens
of nations. Nations form and join free trade zones because, according to the rules of comparative
advantage, free trade will increase a nation’s exports and lower prices for consumers on imported goods.
Roots of Free Trade Today’s free trade movement began in the 1930s. The Smoot-Hawley Act caused a rapid decline in international trade. To encourage trade, Congress passed the Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act of 1934. It gave the president the power to reduce tariffs by as much as 50 percent.
That law also allowed Congress to grant most- favored nation (MFN) status to U.S. trading partners. Today, MFN status is called normal trade relations status, or NTR. All countries with NTR status pay the same tariffs, though imports from non-NTR nations may be taxed at a higher rate.
In 1948, after World War II had disrupted world trade, many nations reached an agreement called the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT). Its goal was to reduce tariffs and stabilize world trade.
World Trade Organization In 1995, the World Trade Organization (WTO) was founded with the goal of making global trade more free. The WTO works to ensure that countries comply with GATT, to negotiate new trade agreements, and to resolve trade disputes. Various conferences, or rounds, of tariff negotiations have advanced the goals of GATT and the WTO. For example, the Uruguay round of
 OPPOSING VIEWS ON TRADE
 For Trade Barriers
• Jobs: Trade barriers protect jobs from going to other countries
• Industries: Trade barriers protect domestic industries from competition
• Security: Trade barriers protect industries essential to national security
• Multinationals: Trade barriers limit the political power of multinationals in host nations
For Trade Agreements
• Competition: Trade agreements allow and enhance competition
• Prices: Trade agreements lower prices for foreign goods
• Efficiency: Free trade is the best way to pursue comparative advantage
• Risk: Trade agreements lessen risk of trade wars
>> Analyze Charts Using the chart, name one way trade barriers benefit workers and one way trade agreements benefit consumers.
442 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="509"> <text><![CDATA[negotiations, completed in 1994, decreased average global tariffs by about a third.
Today, the World Trade Organization also acts
as a referee, enforcing the rules agreed upon by the member countries. WTO decisions resolved the beef war and the steel tariff disputes between the United States and the European Union.
IdENTIfy CAUSE ANd EffECT What effect does a free trade agreement have on the countries that sign it?
Regional Trade Organizations
In addition to the WTO, there are smaller regional trade organizations, often made up of several countries in the same general geographic area. These trade organizations seek to enhance free trade among member nations.
The European Union In recent years, many countries have signed agreements to abolish tariffs and trade restrictions among member nations and adopt uniform tariffs for all countries that are not members. One example is the European Union (EU).
The European Union developed slowly over several decades. In 1957, six western European nations set up the Common Market to coordinate economic and trade policies. In the years that followed, more countries joined the Common Market. In 1986, the member nations agreed to eliminate tariffs on one another’s exports. They created
a single market, called the European Economic Community (EEC).
In 1993, the EEC nations formed the European Union. This new organization became the largest trading bloc in the world. By 2013, the EU included 28 countries—almost all of Europe.
Some member nations signed the European Monetary Union, agreeing to adopt a single currency and monetary system. In 2002, 12 member nations replaced their individual currencies with a single currency called the euro. As of 2013, 18 countries used the euro. The EU also adopted political ties, forming a parliament and council that make laws all member nations must follow. Still, many Europeans feared such measures threatened each nation’s right to make decisions in its own interest.
NAFTA Other nations have created free trade zones, where a group of countries agrees to reduce or eliminate trade barriers. One such pact, the North
 >> Analyze Political Cartoons Americans use imported products every day. What products do you use that you could add to the cartoon caption?
 >> Secretary of State John Kerry and German Foreign Minister Guido Westerwelle met in 2013 to discuss a free trade agreement between the U.S. and the EU. This would create the largest free trade zone in the world.
 10.2 Trade Barriers and Agreements 443]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="510"> <text><![CDATA[  >> Analyze Political Cartoons NAFTA has both benefits and drawbacks. How do the workers in the cartoon feel about NAFTA? Why?
 >> Electronics are a major export from the United States to Mexico. This computer is being assembled in Texas to be sold in Mexico.
 American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), created a free trade zone linking the United States, Canada, and Mexico.
NAFTA aroused controversy in the United States. Opponents worried that American companies would move factories to Mexico, where wages were lower and environmental regulations were less strict. As a result, they said, American workers would lose jobs. Supporters of NAFTA claimed that the measure would instead create more jobs in the United States, because it would increase exports to Mexico and Canada.
After a spirited debate, the Senate ratified NAFTA in 1993. Major provisions include:
• Elimination of tariffs on farm products
• Elimination of auto tariffs
• Truck access across borders
• Special judges to resolve trade disputes
More than 20 years after it went into effect, the agreement has remained controversial. Many studies suggest that NAFTA has had its intended economic benefits. Yet, other studies suggest these benefits have come at a cost to U.S. workers.
What is clear is that trade between the member nations has increased. U.S. trade with Canada and Mexico has tripled since 1993.
CAFTA-DR and FTAA In 2003, the United States government reached a free trade agreement with nations in Central America. At the time, the deal was called the Central American Free Trade Agreement (CAFTA). The next year, when the Dominican Republic joined the pact, the name was changed to CAFTA-DR. Congress approved the agreement in July 2005, and the other nations formally approved it as well.
Case Study: The FTAA After NAFTA went into effect on January 1, 1994, the United States proposed extending many of its provisions to other countries in North and South America. The proposed free trade zone was called the Free Trade Area of the Americas, or FTAA. Negotiations began in 1998. Negotiations were scheduled for completion by January 2005 with a goal of implementing the FTAA by the end of 2005.
However, negotiators failed to reach an agreement by this deadline. Brazil and Argentina, the leading members of the Mercosur trade union, objected to U.S. agricultural subsidies, which made it harder for crops from Mercosur countries to compete. Latin American countries were also unwilling to meet U.S. demands for intellectual
444
TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="511"> <text><![CDATA[Major Trade Organization Members
ARCTIC OCEAN
 PACIFIC OCEAN
ATLANTIC OCEAN
PACIFIC OCEAN
INDIAN OCEAN
>> Analyze Maps What geographic feature do the nations belonging to APEC have in common? What advantage might that feature give to trade among those nations?
property rights protection. These would have made it illegal to sell cheaper generic versions of patented drugs made by U.S. pharmaceutical firms in Latin American countries.
Because it was impossible to resolve these disagreements, the United States gave up on the FTAA. Instead, the United States began seeking trade agreements with individual Latin American countries.
Other Regional Trade Agreements About 100 regional trading organizations operate in the world today. They include the following:
APEC The Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation is an economic forum that includes 21 countries along the Pacific Rim, including the United States. They have signed a nonbinding agreement to reduce trade barriers.
MERCOSUR The Southern Common Market is similar to the EU in its goals. Its members are the South American nations of Brazil, Paraguay, Uruguay, Argentina, and Venezuela.
CARICOM The Caribbean Community and Common Market includes countries from South America and the Caribbean.
ASEAN The ten-member Association of Southeast Asian Nations has taken steps to establish a free trade zone similar to the EU.
The Debate Over Free Trade While the
world’s economies have moved toward free trade, controversy on trade continues. Debates over the impact of NAFTA became a campaign issue in the American presidential election of 2008. As you saw, protests across the Americas slowed negotiations on the FTAA.
Meetings of the World Trade Organization have also spurred large protests. A 1999 WTO meeting
in Seattle, Washington, drew as many as 50,000 angry demonstrators. Not all of these protesters were opposed to free trade. Rather, they were concerned that current free trade agreements gave too much economic power to large multinational corporations.
SUPPORT A POINT Of VIEW WITh EVIdENCE
Why do you think NAFTA stirred such debate in the United States?
The Role of Multinationals
As you read earlier, a corporation is a legal entity that is owned by shareholders and run by managers. Its stockholders have limited liability. A corporation can grow very large and merge with other corporations. A large corporation that sells goods and services throughout the world is a multinational. For example, an automobile company might design its cars in the
10.2 Trade Barriers and Agreements 445
]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="512"> <text><![CDATA[Multinationals with Largest Foreign Assets, 2011
 Foreign assets Domestic assets
General Electric (U.S.) Royal Dutch Shell (Netherlands/Britain) BP (Britain) Exxon Mobil (U.S.) Toyota (Japan) Total (France) GDF Suez (France) Vodafone (Britain) Enel (Italy) Telefónica (Spain)
SOURCE: The Economist
Note: Graph does not include financial companies.
0 150
300 450 600 750
Dollars (in billions)
>> Analyze Graphs What is true about foreign assets compared to domestic assets for each of the multinationals on the graph?
Bounce to Activate Illustration
United States and import parts made in Asia to an assembly plant in Canada. Even if you purchase the car from an American company, it is not a purely domestic product.
Many goods besides cars are produced globally. Some brands of athletic shoes are designed in the United States but are produced in East Asia. Some personal computers are designed in the United States and assembled abroad with parts and components from the United States.
The decision to build production facilities in a foreign country benefits both the multinational and the host nation. By locating abroad, the corporation avoids some shipping fees and tariffs. It may also benefit from cheaper labor. The host nation benefits by gaining jobs and tax revenue.
Still, host nations worry about the effect of multinationals on their countries. In a small country with a fragile economy, multinationals can gain excessive political power. In addition, host nations fear that multinationals could drive out domestic industries and exploit local workers. To protect domestic industries, some host nations have created
rules requiring multinationals to export a certain percentage of their products.
IdENTIfy CENTRAL ISSUES Why are some nations concerned about the negative effects of multinationals?
ASSESSMENT
1. Support a Point of View With Evidence
Describe a way that trade barriers can affect you as a consumer.
2. Identify Cause and Effect What is the difference between an import quota and a tariff?
3. Categorize What are the positive effects of international trade agreements?
4. Express Problems Clearly What is one negative effect of participating in free trade agreements?
5. Summarize Who owns multinational corporations?
446 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="513"> <text><![CDATA[ 10.3
It’s happened to everyone.
You buy something in a store. You hand over a couple of bills. The clerk hands you your change. When you get outside, you notice something funny about one of the quarters. Instead of the familiar profile of George Washington, you see a caribou with a large pair of antlers. You’ve been given a Canadian quarter.
>> A depreciating dollar makes American goods less expensive for tourists visiting the United States, such as these visitors to Miami.
Bounce to Activate Flipped Video
Exchange Rates and
Trade
Foreign Exchange and Currencies
Maybe you feel cheated. But should you? Is this Canadian quarter worth less than a U.S. quarter—or more? How would you find out? These questions may seem unimportant when you’re dealing with just a single quarter. But if you were dealing with hundreds or thousands of dollars, the questions might be very important indeed!
The difference in value between an American dollar and a Canadian dollar—or a British pound or a Japanese yen or a Saudi Arabian riyal—does not stay the same from day to day. In this text, you will see how these fluctuations have a huge impact on imports and exports. Nevertheless, currency is a good means for trading between countries.
International trade is more complex than buying and selling within one country because of the world’s many currencies and their changing values. If you want to buy a newspaper in Beijing, you will need to change your American dollars for Chinese yuan. If a Mexican family visiting New York wants to buy lunch, they must change their pesos to dollars.
NGSSS
SS.912.E.3.5, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10
>> Objectives
Analyze the effects of changes in exchange
rates on world trade.
Define balance of trade.
Summarize the effects of international trade
on the United States and its trading partners.
Analyze the role of the United States in international trade.
>> Key Terms exchange rate
appreciation depreciation foreign exchange
market
fixed exchange-rate
system
flexible exchange-
rate system balance of trade trade surplus
trade deficit
balance of payments
Go ONLINE for digital resources
                    Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="514"> <text><![CDATA[Exchange Rates Changing money from one nation’s currency to another’s is never a simple matter of exchanging, say, one yuan or one peso
for one American dollar. A dollar might be worth 8 yuan or 11 pesos. The value of a nation’s currency in relation to a foreign currency is called the exchange rate. Understanding how exchange rates work enables you to convert prices in one currency to prices in another currency.
Daily exchange rates are listed in major newspapers and on the Internet. Figure 10.6 shows a sample table of exchange rates. If you read down the first column, you will see that one U.S. dollar can be exchanged for more than one (1.10) Australian dollar, for less than one (0.74) euro, and so forth.
An exchange-rate table shows what one U.S. dollar is worth on one particular day. Remember, the rates change daily, so it is important to keep checking, especially if you are visiting a foreign country or doing business overseas.
Converting Prices A simple formula allows you to convert the price of an item from foreign currency to American dollars. Just divide the price by the value of the currency per one dollar according to the exchange rate.
Look at the following example:
Suppose your family is planning a trip to Mexico and that the exchange rate is as shown in Figure 10.6.
If a hotel room in Mexico costs 500 pesos per night, the price in U.S. dollars is $38.20.
500 pesos ÷ 13.09 pesos/dollar = $38.20. Now suppose your family decides to go to Mexico next year instead, and the exchange rate has risen to 15.0 pesos per dollar. Assuming that the room rate is still 500 pesos, the hotel room will cost only $33.33 per night:
500 pesos ÷ 15.0 pesos/dollar = $33.33
Appreciating Currency You have probably heard newscasters talk about a “strong” or “weak” dollar or a currency like the Japanese yen “rising” or “falling.” What do these terms mean? Do they indicate good news or bad news for the United States economy?
An increase in the value of a currency is called appreciation. When a currency appreciates, it becomes “stronger.”
If the exchange rate between the dollar and the yen increases from 100 yen per dollar to 120 yen
per dollar, each dollar can buy more yen. Since the dollar has increased in value, we say that the dollar has appreciated against the yen. This appreciation means that people in Japan will have to spend more yen to purchase a dollar’s worth of goods from the United States. On the other hand, Americans who travel to Japan can buy more goods and services for the same amount of money than they could before the dollar appreciated.
Foreign Exchange Rates
If a hotel room in Mexico costs 500 pesos per night, the price in U.S. dollars is $38.20.
500 pesos ÷ 13.09 pesos/dollar = $38.20. Now suppose your family decides to go to Mexico next year instead, and the exchange rate has risen to 15.0 pesos per dollar. Assuming that the room rate is still 500 pesos, the hotel room will cost only $33.33 per night:
500 pesos ÷ 15.0 pesos/dollar = $33.33
Appreciating Currency You have probably heard newscasters talk about a “strong” or “weak” dollar or a currency like the Japanese yen “rising” or “falling.” What do these terms mean? Do they indicate good news or bad news for the United States economy?
An increase in the value of a currency is called appreciation. When a currency appreciates, it becomes “stronger.”
If the exchange rate between the dollar and the yen increases from 100 yen per dollar to 120 yen
per dollar, each dollar can buy more yen. Since the dollar has increased in value, we say that the dollar has appreciated against the yen. This appreciation means that people in Japan will have to spend more yen to purchase a dollar’s worth of goods from the United States. On the other hand, Americans who travel to Japan can buy more goods and services for the same amount of money than they could before the dollar appreciated.
 
      
U.S. $
Aust. $
1
U.S. $
1.10
1.05
.62
101.42
.74
13.09
6.09
AUST. $
.91
1
.96
.56
92.46
.67
11.93
5.55
CANADIAN $
.95
1.04
1
.59
96.31
.70
12.43
5.79
1
U.K. £
1.62
1.77
1.70
163.98
1.19
21.16
9.85
JAPANESE ¥EN
.010
.011
.010
.006
1
.129
.060
€URO
1.35
1.49
1.43
.84
MEXICAN PESO
.08
.08
CHINESE YUAN
.16
.18
Canadian $
.08
.17
U.K. £
.05
.10
Japanese ¥en
137.40
8.25
7.75
.47
16.64
€uro
.007
1
.06
.12
Mexican peso
17.73
1
2.14
1
Chinese yuan
SOURCE: x-rates.com accessed on Tuesday, November 26, 2013. Note: These data are highly time sensitive and can change hourly.
>> Figure 10.6 This chart shows exchange rates on a single day. Analyze Charts If you had 100 euros, would it buy more Australian or U.S. dollars?
448 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="515"> <text><![CDATA[HOW THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MARKET WORKS
MAIN
FOREX TRADING
CENTERS
Traders buy and sell foreign currency in financial centers using the foreign exchange market, or Forex.
Sources: forextraders.com, businesstech.co.za, www.forextribe.com
FOREIGN EXCHANGE
TRADING DAILY TRANSACTION AMOUNT (BILLIONS)
1992 $880
1995 $1,150
1998 $1,650
2001 $1,420
2004 $1,950 2007 $3,210
2010 $3,981
MOST TRADED
CURRENCIES
Around 80% of the trading is done with the seven major currencies below. The percentages add up to 200 because each transaction involves two currencies.
BRITISH POUND
11.8%
SWISS FRANC
5.2%
OTHER 26.4%
U.S. DOLLAR
87%
EURO 33.4%
YEN 23%
AUS DOLLAR 8.6%
CANADIAN DOLLAR 4.6%
>> The foreign exchange market assists international trade by converting currencies. Analyze Charts Which two currencies are the most frequently traded? Why do you think this is so?
When a nation’s currency appreciates, its products become more expensive in other countries. For example, a strong dollar makes American
goods and services more expensive for Japanese consumers. Japan will therefore probably import fewer products from the United States. As a result, total United States exports to Japan will likely decline. On the other hand, a strong dollar makes foreign products less expensive for consumers in the United States. A strong dollar is therefore likely to lead consumers in the United States to purchase more imported goods.
Depreciating Currency A decrease in the value of a currency is called depreciation. You might also hear depreciation referred to as “weakening.” If the dollar exchange rate fell to 80 yen per dollar, you would get fewer yen for each dollar. In other words, the dollar has depreciated against the yen.
When a nation’s currency depreciates, its products become cheaper to other nations. A depreciated, or weak, dollar means that foreign consumers will be able to better afford products made in the United States. A weakened dollar probably results in increased exports. At the same time, other nations’ products become more
expensive for consumers in the United States, so they will buy fewer imports.
Exchanging Currency Suppose that a company
in the United States sells computers in Japan. That company is paid in yen. It must, however, pay its workers and suppliers back in the United States in dollars. The company must therefore exchange its yen for U.S. dollars. This exchange takes place on the foreign exchange market. International trade would not be possible without this market.
The foreign exchange market consists of about 2,000 banks and other financial institutions that facilitate the buying and selling of foreign currencies. These banks are located in various financial centers around the world, including such cities as New York, London, Paris, Singapore,
and Tokyo. These banks maintain close links to one another through telephones and computers. This technology allows for the instantaneous transmission of market information and rapid financial transactions.
ChECK UNdERSTANdINg What are the likely effects of the dollar becoming stronger?
10.3 Exchange Rates and Trade 449]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="516"> <text><![CDATA[Determining the Value of Currency
As you read earlier, currencies varied in value from state to state in early America. In the United States today, of course, it doesn’t matter which state you live in. All prices are in dollars, and all dollars have the same value.
Think how much more complicated it would be to do business if each state still had its own currency. To buy goods from a mail-order company in Indiana, for instance, someone in Texas would have to find out the exchange rate between a Texas dollar and
an Indiana dollar. The economy would become less efficient as individuals and businesses spent time keeping track of exchange rates.
Such complications do not exist within the United States. They do, however, apply to international trade.
Fixed Exchange-Rate Systems Of course, it would be simpler if all countries either used the same currency or kept their exchange rates constant. Then no one would have to worry about rate shifts. A system in which governments try to keep the values of their currencies constant against one another is called a fixed exchange-rate system.
In a typical fixed exchange-rate system, one country with a stable currency is at the center. Other
countries fix, or peg, their exchange rates to this currency. Normally, the fixed exchange-rate is not a single value, but is kept within a certain specified range (for example, plus or minus 2 percent). If
the exchange rate moves outside of this range, governments usually intervene to maintain the rate.
How do governments intervene to maintain an exchange rate? The exchange rate is essentially the price of a currency. Like the price of any product
or service, the exchange rate relies on supply and demand.
To preserve its exchange rate, a government may buy or sell foreign currency in order to affect a currency’s supply and demand. It will follow this course of action until the exchange rate is back within the specified limits.
The Bretton Woods Conference In 1944, as World War II was drawing to a close, representatives from 44 countries met in Bretton Woods, New Hampshire. Their purpose was to make financial arrangements for the postwar world.
The Bretton Woods conference resulted in the creation of a fixed exchange-rate system for the United States and much of western Europe. Because the United States had the strongest economy and most stable currency, conference participants agreed to peg their currencies to the United States dollar.
Fixed Exchange Rates, Selected Countries
   
 
COUNTRY
REGION
CURRENCY NAME
PEG CURRENCY
PEG RATE
RATE SINCE
  
Benin
Africa
West African CFA Franc
Euro
655.957
1999
  
Cameroon
Africa
Central African CFA Franc
Euro
655.957
1999
  
Hong Kong
Asia
Dollar
US Dollar
7.75–7.85
1998
  
Cuba
Central America
Convertible Peso
US Dollar
1
2011
  
Panama
Central America
Balboa
US Dollar
1
1904
  
Latvia
Europe
Lats
Euro
0.702804
2004
  
Denmark
Europe
Krone
Euro
7.46038
1999
  
Jordan
Middle East
Dinar
US Dollar
0.709
1995
Saudi Arabia
Middle East
Riyal
US Dollar
3.75
2003
South America
Bolivar
US Dollar
6.3
                  
Venezuela             
2013
SOURCE: www.investmentfrontier.com
>> These countries have adopted the fixed-exchange rate system to ensure stability. Analyze Charts Which country in the chart has had the same pegged currency rate the longest?
450 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="517"> <text><![CDATA[To make the new system work, the Bretton Woods conference established the International Monetary Fund (IMF). Today, the IMF promotes international monetary cooperation, currency stabilization, and trade.
Flexible Exchange-Rate Systems Although
fixed exchange-rate systems make trade easier, they depend on countries maintaining similar economic policies as well as similar inflation and interest rates. By the late 1960s, worldwide trade was growing
and changing rapidly. At the same time, the war in Vietnam was causing inflation in the United States. These factors made it increasingly difficult for many countries to rely on a fixed exchange rate.
In 1971, the Netherlands and West Germany abandoned the fixed exchange-rate system. Other countries followed. By 1973, even the United States had adopted a system based on flexible exchange rates. Under a flexible exchange-rate system, the exchange rate is determined by supply and demand rather than according to any preset range.
Today, the countries of the world use a mixture of fixed and flexible exchange rates. Most major currencies—including the U.S. dollar and the Japanese yen—use the flexible exchange-rate system. This system accounts for the day-to-day changes in currency values that you read about earlier in this section.
When the current flexible exchange-rate system was first adopted, some economists worried that changes in the exchange rate might interrupt the flow of world trade. In actual fact, trade has grown rapidly since the flexible exchange-rate system was adopted. Today, more nations trade than ever before.
The Euro Although the flexible exchange-rate system works well, some countries whose economies are closely tied together want the advantages of fixed rates. One way to enjoy the advantages but avoid some of the difficulties of fixed exchange rates is to abolish individual currencies and establish a single currency.
This is what 11 countries of the European Union did by adopting the euro. Use of this common currency requires countries to coordinate their economic policies, but it also simplifies trade. People traveling from, say, Germany to France do not need to exchange marks for francs at the border. They simply use their euros. However, having one currency has had its disadvantages. During the financial crisis that started in 2007, a number of countries, including Greece, Spain, and Italy, faced
economic difficulties and became less competitive on world markets.
Because they were part of the single currency block, they could not depreciate their own currency or use monetary policy to help alleviate their economic problems. Instead, they were forced to suffer through a deep and prolonged recession to reduce their wages and prices in order to restore their competitiveness. These adjustments not only caused economic strife for those countries, but also created tensions within the entire group of nations using the euro.
IdENTIfy CAUSE ANd EffECT Has the flexible exchange-rate system prevented or enabled an increase in world trade?
Balance of Trade
The value of a nation’s currency is affected by the overall flow of goods and services into and out of the country. In turn, exchange rates can affect a nation’s balance of trade, the relationship between the value of its exports and the value of its imports.
>> Global leaders met at the Mount Washington Hotel in Bretton Woods, NH, to stabilize the world’s financial system. They instituted policies that were designed to prevent practices that could lead to severe economic downturns.
10.3 Exchange Rates and Trade 451]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="518"> <text><![CDATA[ Surpluses and Deficits The importing and exporting of goods and services can have a significant impact on the United States and its trading partners. A trade imbalance, which occurs when a large difference between a nation’s imports and exports arises, is one example. A nation that exports more goods and services than it imports has a positive trade balance, or a trade surplus. A nation that imports more goods and services than it exports has a negative trade balance, or a trade deficit.
Nations seek to maintain a balance of trade. That is, they hope the value of imports is roughly equal to the value of exports.
By balancing trade, a nation can protect the value of its currency on the international market. When a country has a continuing negative balance of trade, importing more than it is exporting over an extended period of time, the value of its currency falls.
For example, in the 1980s, the United States imported considerably more than it exported. As a result of this trade imbalance, the foreign exchange market was glutted with U.S. dollars. Because the supply of dollars was so high, the value of the dollar fell. The prices of imports increased, and American consumers had to pay more for imported goods.
A negative balance of trade can be corrected either by limiting imports or by increasing the number or value of exports. Both of these actions
affect trading partners, of course, who may then retaliate by raising tariffs. Maintaining a balance of trade thus requires international cooperation and fair trade practices.
Balance of Payments and Circular Flow Model
Balance of trade measures the flow of goods and services among nations. Economists get a more complex picture of international trade by looking at the balance of payments. Balance of payments is the value of all monetary transactions between all sectors of a country’s economy—households, firms, and government—and the rest of the world.
Recall the circular flow model of a mixed economy (Figure 10.4) that you saw earlier. It shows the movement of money and goods within a global economy. For example, if an American financial institution invested in a foreign company, the capital it invested would be part of the monetary flow going overseas. Any returns from the investment would be part of the monetary flow coming into the country. Income from foreign companies, government aid
to foreign countries, borrowing from foreign banks, exchange rates—all of these must be factored into the balance of payments.
IdENTIfy CENTRAL IdEAS What impact did the United States trade imbalance in the 1980s have on the cost of imported goods?
 EFFECT OF EXCHANGE RATES ON TRADE
 Effect of Appreciating Currency
• Value of currency rises, making goods produced in country more expensive.
• Exports: Costs of exports rises for foreign buyers, causing sales of exports to fall.
• Imports: Cost of imports falls, making sales of imports rise.
Effect of Depreciating Currency
• Value of currency falls, making goods produced in country less expensive.
• Exports: Cost of exports falls for foreign buyers, causing sales of exports to rise.
• Imports Costs of imports rises, making sales of imports fall.
>> Analyze Charts What effect would a depreciating U.S. dollar have on American exports and the trade deficit?
Bounce to Activate Chart
452 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="519"> <text><![CDATA[U.S. Balance of Trade, 1965–2012
U.S. Dollars (in billions)
 3,000 2,500 2,000 1,500 1,000
500
0
1965 1970
SOURCE: www.census.gov
1975 1980 1985 1990
Year
1995 2000
2005 2010 2015
SOURCE: www.census.gov
>> Figure 10.7 This graph traces the relationship of United States imports to exports for over four decades. Analyze Graphs In which year was the trade deficit greatest?
Bounce to Activate Chart
A Growing Trade Deficit
Although the United States sells many goods abroad, it generally imports more than it exports. As a result, the United States currently runs a trade deficit. (See Figure 10.7)
Causes of the Trade Deficit The U.S. trade deficit began to take shape in the 1970s, when the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) dramatically raised the price of oil. The United States, which depends heavily on foreign oil, thus had to increase the money spent on this vital resource. As a result, the total cost of imports to the United States began to exceed the income from its exports.
The United States suffered record trade deficits in 1986 and 1987. In the early 1990s, the trade deficit began to fall. By the late 1990s, however, the deficit had skyrocketed to record levels, largely as a result of a new increase in oil prices and an economic boom that fueled consumer buying of imported goods.
In 2012, the trade deficit totaled over $530 billion, with the largest amounts owed to China, the European Union, Japan, Germany, Mexico, Canada, and oil exporting nations such as Venezuela. Energy imports, including petroleum, accounted for 40 percent of the deficit.
Effects of the Trade Deficit When Americans import more than they export, more dollars end up
in the hands of foreigners. They can then use these extra dollars to purchase American land, stocks, bonds, and other assets. As a result of America’s trade deficits, people from other countries now own a large piece of the U.S. economy. Many people fear this trend threatens national independence and even national security.
Some economists worry that foreign financial investment might not always support the trade deficit. They worry that, with U.S. imports on the rise and American foreign debt growing, overseas investors might become reluctant to purchase American assets.
As a result, that monetary flow into the United States would slow down. In 2000, a federal commission formed to study the deficit concluded that “maintaining large and growing trade deficits is neither desirable nor likely to be sustainable for the extended future.”
Can Balance of Trade Be Restored? To reduce the trade deficit, the government could depreciate the exchange rate. As you saw, when the dollar is weak, American products become cheaper to buy on the world market, and other countries’ goods become correspondingly more expensive. As a result, exports rise and imports fall. The head of the nation’s largest steelmaker noted this process at work in 2008:
10.3 Exchange Rates and Trade 453]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="520"> <text><![CDATA[The opportunities for exporting are definitely greater than they
were a year or two years ago. We have folks who were bringing in steel for decades coming to us and saying we’d like to talk to you about exporting. That is a huge change. It’s because of the dollar.
—Dan DiMicco, interview
The federal government could also cut back spending by adjusting its monetary or fiscal policy. Individuals could voluntarily purchase fewer foreign goods, despite the higher price of certain domestic items. Or American companies could try to sell more domestic products overseas. All of these approaches involve sacrifices or risk, but they would result in fewer surplus dollars ending up in foreign hands.
MAKE gENERALIzATIONS What has been the trend of the United States balance of trade in recent decades?
ASSESSMENT
Recall What is an exchange rate?
Explain How do a fixed exchange-rate system
and a flexible exchange-rate system differ?
Distinguish How does the balance of payments differ from the balance of trade?
Predict Consequences How do you think a nation’s balance of trade might be affected if its government instituted policies to support science education and give tax breaks to high- tech industries?
Identify Cause and Effect What effect does a decrease in demand for goods exported from the United States have on the trade deficit?
454 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="521"> <text><![CDATA[ 10.4
Have you ever given money for world famine relief? Or taken part in a fund-raising drive to build a school in a foreign country? Each year, Americans of all ages donate money and time to such efforts.
And the need is very real. About
1.2 billion people around the world live in extreme poverty. More than a third of them are children under the age of 13.
>> Volunteers and interns work with students at NairobiBits, a youth-based organization in Kenya that teaches Information Communication Technology (ICT) skills to children who have little access to education.
Bounce to Activate Flipped Video
Development
Development Around the World
There are vast differences between prosperous nations—such as the United States or Canada—and poorer nations such as Ethiopia or El Salvador. In this Lesson, you will examine what some of these differences are and why they exist.
Economists divide the world’s nations into different categories according to their level of development. Development is the process by which a nation improves the economic, political,
and social well-being of its people. It is important to remember that development refers to a nation’s material well-being. It is
not a judgment of the worth of a nation or its people. The level of development does not indicate cultural superiority or inferiority. It simply indicates how well a nation is able to feed, clothe, and shelter its people.
Nations with a relatively high average of material well-being are called developed nations. The United States, Canada, Japan, Australia, New Zealand, and the nations of Western Europe fall into this category.
Most nations, however, have relatively low levels of material well-being. These less developed countries (LDCs) include the world’s poorest countries, such as Bangladesh, Nepal, Albania, and nations of central and southern Africa.
NGSSS
SS.912.G.2.2, SS.912.E.3.4, SS.912.E.3.5
>> Objectives
Summarize the concept of economic
development.
Identify the characteristics of developed and less developed countries.
Explain the use of GDP and other measurements of economic development.
>> Key Terms development
developed nation less developed
country
newly industrialized
country
per capita GDP industrialization literacy rate
life expectancy infant mortality rate subsistence
agriculture
Go ONLINE for digital resources
                    Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="522"> <text><![CDATA[One group of LDCs has made great progress toward developing their economies. These newly industrialized countries (NICs) include Mexico, Brazil, Saudi Arabia, South Korea, and several countries in Eastern Europe. Some NICs are rich in resources, especially oil. Saudi Arabia, for example, has made a great deal of money from selling oil and oil products. Others have turned to manufacturing. Although the NICs have pulled ahead of the poorer LDCs, they have yet to achieve the high standard of living of developed nations.
CONTRAST How do NICs differ from both developed nations and LDCs?
Indicators of Development
Economists use many different factors to measure
a nation’s level of development. These economic indicators include production of goods and
services, energy consumption, distribution of the workforce, availability of consumer goods, and social conditions.
Per Capita GDP As you read earlier, gross domestic product (GDP) is the total value of all final goods
and services produced within an economy in a year. GDP alone, however, is not adequate to compare
the living standards of nations. Instead, economists use per capita GDP, a nation’s GDP divided by its population. As Figure 10.8 shows, per capita GDP can vary widely from nation to nation.
Why is per capita GDP considered to be a more accurate measure of development than GDP by itself? Look at two nations, Spain and India.
Both have high GDPs—about $1.32 trillion for Spain and about $1.84 trillion for India. Yet Spain enjoys a high standard of living, while India is relatively poor.
The reason for this discrepancy is population size. Spain’s $1.32 trillion is shared by more than 46.2 million people. Thus, its per capita GDP is around $28,751. India’s $1.84 trillion is shared by about 1.2 billion people, so its per capita GDP is only around $1,530. These figures indicate that the average person in Spain is better off, in material terms, than the average person in India.
Of course, per capita GDP does not take into account distribution of income. Within every nation, some people are wealthier than most, while others are poorer than most. In many LDCs, the gap between rich and poor is especially wide.
The World Bank, an international economic organization that studies development, uses a similar measure called per capita gross national income (GNI). Using this yardstick, the World Bank
Per Capita GDP of Selected Nations, 2012
                Singapore United States United Kingdom New Zealand Israel Saudi Arabia South Korea Russia Argentina Mexico South Africa Iran China Albania Philippines Mali
0 5 10 15 20 25 30 35 40 45 50 55 60
U.S. Dollars (in thousands)
SOURCE: United Nations database
>> Figure 10.8 Economists use per capita GDP as a measure of development. Analyze Graphs What does this graph show about the material well-being of people in Israel as compared with people in Albania?
Bounce to Activate Gallery
456 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="523"> <text><![CDATA[Per Capita GNI of Selected Countries, 2004–2012
GNI Per Capita (U.S. dollars)
14,000 12,000 10,000
8,000
6,000
4,000
2,000
0
Brazil
 Russia India
    China
South Africa
2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012
SOURCE: The World Bank Databank
High-income economies:
$12,616 or more
Upper-middle income economies: $4,086–$12,615
Lower-middle income economies: $1,036–$4,085
 Low-income economies:
 $1,035 or less
 >> These fast-growing LDCs are known as the BRICS, from the first letter of each country’s name. Analyze Graphs Which one reached the “high-income economy” level during this period?
 classifies nations as high income, middle income,and low income.
Energy Use Energy use is another good way
to measure development. The amount of energy
that a nation consumes is closely linked to its
level of industrialization. Industrialization is
the organization of an economy for the purpose of manufacture. Because industrial processes generally require large amounts of energy, high levels of energy use tend to indicate high levels of industrial activity. They also indicate a high level of development.
Conversely, a low level of energy consumption tends to indicate that a nation has a low level of industrial activity. Most of the people work with simple tools rather than machines.
Workforce Another sign of low-level development is that a large share of the population works in agriculture. Why is that the case?
If most people are raising food just for themselves, few are available to work in industry. As a result, there is little opportunity for workers to specialize. As you read earlier, specialization makes an economy more efficient and productive. It also allows workers to focus on particular jobs, which enables them to earn cash income.
Social Indicators Three social indicators also measure a nation’s level of development. The first is literacy rate, the proportion of the population over age 15 who can read and write. In general, a high percentage of people attending school suggests a high level of development. An educated population has the potential to be more productive and to use or produce advanced technology.
Another indicator is life expectancy, the average expected life span of an individual. It indicates how well an economic system supports life. People who are well nourished and housed and have access to medical care live longer. A population that lacks food and adequate housing and is exposed to poor sanitation and disease will have a shorter life expectancy.
A country’s infant mortality rate indicates
the number of deaths that occur in the first year of life per 1,000 live births. For example, in the United States, out of every 1,000 infants born alive in a given year, 5.9 of them die before they reach their first birthdays. This means that the United States has an infant mortality rate of 5.9. Generally speaking, the lower a nation’s infant mortality rate, the higher its level of development.
Development and the Environment As nations develop, positive and negative externalities
10.4 Development 457
 
]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="524"> <text><![CDATA[connected with development have an impact
on the environment. For example, cutting down rainforests in Brazil has increased GDP but harmed the environment. Burning rainforests to create palm plantations in Indonesia has increased GDP but spread pollution internationally across Southeast Asia.
Industrialization boosts development, but by increasing energy consumption, it has the negative externality of increasing air pollution. On the
other hand, as economies grow more developed, they can afford energy-saving technologies that create positive externalities for the environment by reducing pollution.
IdENTIfy CENTRAL IdEAS How is energy use related to development?
Indicators of Developed Nations
Developed nations have high per capita GDPs, and the majority of the population is neither very rich nor very poor. In general, people in these nations enjoy
a greater degree of economic and political freedom than do those in less developed countries.
Quality of Life Levels of consumer spending are high in developed nations. For example, in the United States, almost 75 percent of households have computers.
The populations of developed nations are generally healthy, with low infant mortality rates and high life expectancy. Literacy rates are high as well. People tend to receive schooling well into their teens, and many go on to college.
High Productivity In most developed nations, agricultural output is high, but relatively few people work on farms. For example, with the equipment available today, a single farmer in the United States can feed 155 people. Agriculture has largely become a high-tech big business:
New technologies are making the profession of farming more efficient, less risky, and less labor-intensive. . . . [Big farmers] are automating the entire farming process using GPS technology, genetically modified
 STAGES OF ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT
 1 PRIMITIVE EQUILIBRIUM
Society has a traditional economy, with no formal economic organization or monetary system.
2 TRANSITION
Industries are introduced, people adopt new economic activities, and traditional markets begin to disappear.
3 TAKEOFF AND SEMI-DEVELOPMENT
The economy expands as new industries grow, profits are reinvested, and society enters international markets.
4 HIGH LEVEL OF DEVELOPMENT
The economy, focused on consumer goods and public services, easily meets basic human needs.
>> Countries go through stages of economic development. Analyze Charts At which stage would you expect that the fewest number of workers are involved with agriculture?
Bounce to Activate Chart
458 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="525"> <text><![CDATA[crops, automated irrigation systems, specialized fertilizers.
—Bob Baddeley, “Farm Technology: Applying High Tech for High Yields”
Since only a small portion of the labor force is needed in agriculture, more people are available to work in industry and services. Widespread use of technology increases the productivity of this workforce, too.
Urbanization and Infrastructure Developed nations tend to be urban rather than rural. Most of their populations live in cities and towns and have done so for many years. Major cities such as New York, London, and Tokyo are centers of finance and trade.
Hand-in-hand with urbanization goes a solid infrastructure. Power plants enhance a nation’s capacity to produce goods. Transportation and communication systems allow easier transfer of products, services, people, and ideas. Schools increase a nation’s literacy rate and productive capacity. Banks allow for secure transfer of financial assets.
SUPPORT IdEAS WITh ExAMPLES What forms of infrastructure support urbanization?
Indicators of Less Developed Nations
Less developed countries generally have low per capita GDPs. Their per capita energy consumption is also low, which is an indicator of their limited level of industrialization. These characteristics affect LDCs’ ability to produce goods efficiently and to provide their citizens with a satisfactory standard of living.
Low Productivity Many people in LDCs engage in subsistence agriculture, raising only enough food to feed themselves and their families. Subsistence agriculture requires heavy labor, leaving fewer workers available for industry or services.
Unemployment rates are high in less developed countries, often around 20 percent. In addition, much of the labor force in these nations is underemployed. Often people who are underemployed have work, but not enough to support themselves or their families because they work less than full time.
Quality of Life Even if an LDC could produce a large quantity of consumer goods—which they generally do not—most of the population would be unable to buy them. Subsistence-level agriculture and underemployment do not provide families with enough income to buy these goods. Consumer goods that are produced are often shipped out of the country and sold in more developed nations.
A less developed country has trouble educating its populace. Resources for schools are limited. In addition, children are often needed to work on the family farm, limiting the amount of time they can spend in school. As a result, literacy rates in LDCs are very low. In Afghanistan, for example, only about 28 percent of the people over 15 years old can read and write. Compare this figure with the United States, where the literacy rate is nearly 100 percent.
In the world’s poorest countries, housing and
diet are of poor quality. Along with limited access to healthcare, these factors lead to high infant mortality rates and short life expectancy.
There are additional characteristics common to most LDCs. In the next Lesson, you will read about some of the difficult issues challenging less developed countries.
INfER Why do most people in LDCs have few consumer goods?
ASSESSMENT
1. Make Generalizations What are some characteristics of the newly industrializing countries (NICs)?
2. Apply Concepts Why can two countries with similar GDPs have greatly differing average levels of material well-being?
3. Draw Conclusions What social indicator would you expect to be low in a country with poor nutrition and a lack of clean water?
4. Support Ideas With Evidence Explain how literacy, human capital, and economic development are interrelated.
5. Support Ideas With Examples Why would establishing an agricultural college be a way to enhance a country’s rate of development?
10.4 Development 459]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="526"> <text><![CDATA[ 10.5
Even in a developed nation like ours, there are people who can’t read or don’t eat a healthy diet. But imagine that you never even had a chance to go to school. Imagine that a severe shortage of food reduced your chances of living to adulthood. For many people your age, such conditions are a grim reality.
>> A growing number of Bolivia’s women are exercising their voting rights and participating in politics because of funding from the United Nations Development Programme.
 Bounce to Activate Flipped Video
 NGSSS
SS.912.G.2.2, SS.912.G.4.4
>> Objectives
Summarize major issues that affect
international economic development.
Describe the role of government in promoting or hindering national economic development.
Summarize the role of international investment and foreign aid in economic development.
Analyze the functions of international economic institutions in the global economy.
>> Key Terms population growth
rate
malnutrition internal financing foreign investment foreign direct
investment foreign portfolio investment
debt rescheduling stabilization program nongovernmental
organizations
Growth, Resources,
and Development
A Growing Population
Illiteracy and poor nutrition are just two of the factors that hinder development. In this section, you will see what LDCs and the world community are doing to combat these conditions and encourage economic growth.
As long ago as 1798, the English economist Thomas Malthus predicted that rapid population growth would become a serious problem:
The power of population is indefinitely greater than the power in the earth to produce subsistence for man . . . . The food therefore which before supported seven millions, must now be divided among seven millions and a half or eight millions. The poor consequently must live much worse, and many of them be reduced to severe distress.
— Thomas Malthus, Essay on Population
Go ONLINE for digital resources
                    Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="527"> <text><![CDATA[Thanks to modern technology, the earth now produces more food than Malthus could have imagined. Still, rapid population growth remains one of the most pressing issues facing many less developed countries. The already poor economies of many LDCs have trouble meeting the needs of their rapidly growing populations.
Measuring Population Growth The population growth rate is a measure of how rapidly a country’s population increases in a given year. It is expressed as a percentage of the population figure at the start of the year. The population growth rate takes into account the number of babies born, the number of people who died, and the number of people who migrated to or from a country.
Compare the growth rates shown in Figure 10.9. Average population growth of less developed countries is estimated to be around 1.8 percent. This may sound low to you, but at this rate the population of LDCs will increase by nearly two thirds from 2007 to 2050. That is more than 20 times the population growth of developed nations during the same period.
Causes of Rapid Population Growth Rapid population growth has several causes. Many LDCs
are experiencing increased life expectancy. While people are living longer, birth rates in some LDCs have not decreased. When births far outpace deaths, the population grows.
Age structure also contributes to rapid population growth. In many LDCs, a high proportion of the population is of childbearing age. As these younger adults have children, the population continues to grow. The question for the future is whether these families will choose to have as many children as their parents did. Birth rates have been declining in parts of the world, which may signal a new trend. In developed nations, a larger segment of the population is older, so population increases at a much slower rate.
Population Growth Challenges As its
population grows, a country must expand employment opportunities, healthcare, education, and infrastructure just to maintain its existing standard of living. To actually improve the lives of its people, a nation has to generate a higher per capita GDP. Economic output must grow faster than the population grows.
In a less developed country with a high population growth rate, such accelerated economic
Population Growth Rates of Selected Nations, 2012
             Kuwait Chad Guatemala Afghanistan Venezuela Haiti Mexico Canada United States Sweden Austria Czech Republic Japan
             –0.5 0
0.5 1.0
1.5 2.0
2.5 3.0
3.5 4.0
              Population growth rate (percent)
              SOURCE: World Bank
>> Figure 10.9 Analyze Graphs Which of the selected countries have a population growth rate higher than the average 1.8 percent for less developed countries?
10.5 Growth, Resources, and Development 461]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="528"> <text><![CDATA[growth is a daunting task. A primary reason is that these LDCs lack various factors of production.
dETERMINE POINT Of VIEW What did English economist Thomas Malthus predict in 1798, and what influenced his prediction?
Obstacles to Development
In parts of Africa, Asia, and Latin America, physical geography is a serious obstacle to development. Natural resources are not evenly distributed throughout the world. Some nations lack mineral resources or fertile farmland. Harsh temperatures, uncertain rainfall, and vulnerability to natural disasters such as floods or earthquakes also contribute to the economic problems of some LDCs.
The problem is not always lack of resources. Rather, less developed countries often lack the means to use their resources efficiently. Technology can help LDCs develop the resources they do have. Technology, however, is costly and requires much capital. The formation of capital is another important obstacle to development.
Physical Capital The low productivity typical
of LDCs is due in part to lack of physical capital. Without capital, industry cannot grow, and farm output remains low. Also, subsistence agriculture does not give farmers the opportunity to save. As a result, they do not have the cash to purchase capital that would make their farm work more productive or to pay for goods and services that would improve their lives.
Educating and Training Growing Populations
Lack of human capital also hinders development.
To be able to move beyond mere subsistence, a nation needs an educated workforce. Education and training allow people to develop new skills and adapt to new technologies and processes. As you have read, however, many less developed countries have low literacy rates. Figure 10.10 compares figures
for education and literacy in the United States and several other countries.
Two factors combine to lower literacy rates in these countries. First, only three out of four children in LDCs who begin primary school are still in school four years later. Many children are forced to leave school because they are needed at home to work on family farms.
Second, in many LDCs, the literacy rate for women lags far behind that for men. Many women
in these countries begin raising children at an
early age. Those who do work have limited job opportunities and earn low wages. In addition, some cultures devalue women. Due to all these factors, a large part of a country’s population lacks the training needed to be highly productive.
Nutrition and Health Poor nutrition and health also impede the development of human capital. Many people in less developed countries suffer from
Education and Literacy
COUNTRY
United States Indonesia Peru Nigeria Italy Niger
PRIMARY SCHOOL ENROLLMENT (PERCENTAGE)
95.7
99
97.1
57.6
99.1
63.7
FEMALE
99
90
85
50
99
15
LITERACY RATE (PERCENTAGE) MALE
99
96
95
72
99
43
SOURCE: United Nations, World Bank
>> Figure 10.10 Analyze Charts Which country has the highest primary school enrollment?
462 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="529"> <text><![CDATA[Food Price Index
Food Price Index
      250
      200
      150
      100
50
0
2002 2003 2004 2005
2006 2007
2008 2009 2010
2011 2012
NOTE: The FAO Food Price Index is a measure of the change in international prices of a basket of food commodities. SOURCE: United Nations, Food and Agricultural Organization
>> Analyze Graphs From 2004 to 2011, the food price index doubled. How many years was that, and what effect would the steep increase have had on people in LDCs?
malnutrition, or consistently inadequate nutrition. (A worldwide increase in food prices in 2008
through 2011 aggravated the situation.) Malnutrition lowers the energy of adults and makes them more vulnerable to disease. Both results can reduce worker productivity. Malnutrition also slows the physical and mental development of children, hurting their chances of being productive workers once they become adults.
In many LDCs, poor sanitation leads to the spread of disease. In addition, many poorer countries have high rates of infection by HIV, the virus that causes AIDS. This epidemic removes large numbers of workers from the workforces of these countries. In addition, caring for these people and their families puts a strain on the resources of many LDCs. Money that could be spent on schools or infrastructure has to be devoted to healthcare or providing for orphaned children.
dRAW CONCLUSIONS Why is lack of physical capital, such as farm machinery, an obstacle to development?
Political Barriers to Growth
Political factors may also limit or even reverse
a nation’s development. Many LDCs are former colonies of European powers. Colonies had to supply the ruling powers with resources and rely on them for manufactured goods. This dependency prevented the development of industry.
In the decades after World War II, these colonies won independence. Many then turned to central planning, rather than free enterprise, as the way to modernize their economies quickly. These nations made some gains at first, but in the long run, central planning hindered their economic growth. Many are now making the transition to free enterprise systems.
Government corruption has also held back development in many LDCs. Some leaders have funneled huge sums of money into private accounts, allowing them to live luxurious lives while large numbers of their people remain poor.
Civil war and social unrest have plagued many countries, including El Salvador and, more recently, the Central African Republic, Syria, and Nigeria. Years of fighting may leave millions dead and millions more as refugees. Loss of workers, as well as damage to resources and infrastructure, can throw a nation’s economy into chaos.
 10.5 Growth, Resources, and Development 463]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="530"> <text><![CDATA[Finally, economic policies in many LDCs have favored small minorities. In some countries, policies benefit city dwellers and not the rural majority. In some, leaders favor only one ethnic group—typically their own. In extreme cases, governments practice policies of genocide—the attempted extermination of an entire ethnic or religious group.
International organizations like the World Bank work with developing countries to help them
fight corruption and develop into free enterprise systems. In Burundi, for example, the organization is helping the government protect and consolidate the country’s transition from an economy torn by conflict to a more stable economy. The Bank is working with Burundi to strengthen public finance management, promote private-sector development and economic diversification, and improve protection of vulnerable groups.
IdENTIfy CAUSE ANd EffECT How did colonialism adversely affect economic development in the colonized countries?
Finance and Development
Building an infrastructure, providing services, and creating technology and industry all require large sums of money. A developing country can acquire these funds through a variety of means. These include internal financing, foreign investment, borrowing, and foreign aid. However, many of these solutions—especially borrowing—create problems of their own.
Internal Financing In many ways, the most favorable source of development funds is internal financing. Internal financing is capital derived from the savings of a country’s own citizens. As you read earlier, when savers deposit money in banks
or other financial institutions, some of the money is used to make loans to firms. Firms invest in physical and human capital so they can expand, creating new jobs. Job growth enables workers to improve their standard of living. They buy more goods and services, which encourages businesses to expand further. As a result, the entire economy grows.
In most LDCs, though, large segments of the population do not have enough money to save. The wealthy few often keep their money in foreign banks or invest in foreign firms because these investments are safer. As a result, most poor countries have little
 MULTINATIONALS THREE EXAMPLES
 FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT
TOYOTA
LEADING AUTO MAKER
Toyota makes cars at assembly plants it owns in 28 countries.
OFFSHORING
NIKE
LEADING SUPPLIER OF ATHLETIC SHOES
Nike subcontracts production of its Nike brand shoes to foreign-owned and operated companies.
INTERNATIONAL FRANCHISING
McDONALD’S
LEADING
FOOD SERVICE RETAILER
McDonald's does not own
but franchises 80% of its restaurants in over 100 countries.
Sources: University of Chicago Booth School of Business; Toyota.com, Intel.com, Nike.com, McDonald’s.com
>> Multinationals do business overseas in different ways. Analyze Charts Which of the examples above describes a multinational that builds a plant in a foreign country to test computer parts?
464 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="531"> <text><![CDATA[U.S. Foreign Aid, 2013
 $2.1B
$8.7B
$2.7B
$5.4B
$8.4B
$2.4B
$3.4B
Peace and Security Humanitarian Assistance Health
Program Management
Democracy, Human Rights, and Governance
Education
and Social Services, Environment
Economic Development
SOURCE: ForeignAssistance.gov
>> Analyze Charts In 2013, the U.S. State Department provided more
than $33 billion in aid to foreign countries. What are the two largest Bounce to Activate Chart categories of spending?
Bounce to Activate Chart
capital available from internal financing. In order to fund development, they must turn to foreign sources.
Foreign Investment Capital that originates in other countries is called foreign investment. There are two types of foreign investment: direct investment and portfolio investment.
Foreign direct investment occurs when investors establish a business in another country. For example, multinational corporations often build factories or other facilities in an LDC. Multinationals make this investment to take advantage of natural resources available in the less developed country or to tap into the large and cheap labor force.
As you have seen, multinationals are controversial. Some economists say that the people of the LDC who work for the foreign corporation are better off than they would be doing other work. Their wages give them cash they can use to buy goods, which can help stimulate their country’s economy. Critics say that multinationals exploit workers by paying them less than they would pay workers
in developed nations. Critics also charge that multinationals can hurt a nation’s economic growth by taking profits out of the country.
Instead of building businesses, foreign investors can make purchases in another country’s financial markets. This is known as foreign portfolio investment. For example, an American investor
might buy shares in a mutual fund. The mutual fund then buys stock in a foreign company. That company can use the funds to build another plant or to pay for research and development. Still, portfolio investment does present some problems. Since the investors
live in another country, some or all of the company’s profits may be drained away from the LDC.
Borrowing and Debt In the 1970s and 1980s, many less developed countries acquired loans from foreign governments and private banks to finance development. Some of that money was misspent because of inexperience or political corruption.
Changes in the world economy also caused problems for the LDCs. As oil prices rose, they borrowed more money to buy needed fuel. Also, many of the loans were issued in—and had to
be repaid in—U.S. dollars. When the value of the dollar increased in the 1980s, many LDCs found it impossible to repay their loans. Once again, many were forced to borrow even more funds. As a result, the foreign debt in some countries grew to be greater than their annual GDP. As you will see, the world financial community has sought ways to relieve this severe debt crunch.
Foreign Aid Sometimes, rather than making loans to developing nations, foreign governments give money and other forms of aid. For instance,
10.5 Growth, Resources, and Development 465]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="532"> <text><![CDATA[many developed nations provide cash payments
for building schools, sanitation systems, roads, and other infrastructure. These foreign aid grants do not need to be repaid.
Foreign aid can be motivated by humanitarian concerns. At the same time, developed nations have military, political, economic, and cultural reasons
to extend aid to LDCs. In the years following World War II, for instance, American officials gave aid to countries in Africa, Asia, and Latin America to try to block the influence of the Soviet Union in those areas. In the early 2000s, the United States provided money to Iraq and Afghanistan. American leaders hoped to fight international terrorism by building stable democracies in those countries.
CATEgORIzE How is a foreign aid grant different from making a loan to a developing nation?
Promoting Development
Several international economic organizations promote development. The most prominent institutions are the World Bank, the United Nations Development Programme, and the International Monetary Fund. In addition, privately run aid
groups give economic help and advice in some less developed countries.
World Bank The largest provider of development assistance is the World Bank, founded in 1944. As discussed earlier, the World Bank raises money
on world financial markets and also accepts contributions from the wealthier member nations. The World Bank uses these funds to offer loans and other resources to more than 100 less developed countries. The World Bank also coordinates with other organizations to promote development throughout the world and provides advice to LDCs on how to build their economies.
United Nations Development Programme The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) is dedicated to the elimination of poverty. The UNDP
is one of the world’s largest sources of grant funding for economic and social development. It assists over 177 countries and territories, in which the majority of the world’s poorest people live. The UNDP is funded by voluntary contributions made by United Nations member states and agencies.
International Monetary Fund As you already learned, the International Monetary Fund was founded in 1946 to stabilize international exchange
The World Bank, UN Development Program, and IMF
 
WORLD BANK
UNDP
IMF
Founding
1944
1965
1944
Purpose
The World Bank gives financial and technical assistance to developing countries. Its mission is to end extreme poverty and boost shared prosperity.
The UNDP implements programs that focus on four main sectors:
• Crisis Prevention and Recovery • Democracy/Good Governance • Poverty Reduction
• Energy and Environment
The IMF promotes the stability of the international monetary system by overseeing exchange rates and international payments. Its purpose is to facilitate economic growth and reduce poverty.
  Recent Programs
• Providing microcredit in Bosnia and Herzegovina
• Supporting education of girls in Bangladesh
• Improving health care delivery in Mexico
• Helping women in Yemen acquire job skills
• Supporting mobile courts to bring justice in rural Pakistan
• Providing water to communities in Myanmar
• Committing more than $300 billion to crisis-hit countries such as Greece, Ireland, and Portugal
• Setting a goal of $750 billion in lendable resources
SOURCES: World Bank, UNDP, IMF
>> Analyze Charts The World Bank, UNDP, and IMF are international economic organizations. What goal do these three organizations share, as described in the purpose section of the chart?
Bounce to Activate Gallery
466 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="533"> <text><![CDATA[rates. Today, the IMF has expanded its role in the world economy. It promotes development by offering policy advice and technical assistance to LDCs. It also intervenes when LDCs need help in financing their international transactions.
If a country has trouble repaying a debt, the
IMF may arrange a rescheduling plan. Debt rescheduling is an agreement between a lending nation and a debtor nation.The lending nation lengthens the time of debt repayment and forgives, or dismisses, part of the loan. In return, the LDC agrees to accept a stabilization program, changing its economic policies to meet IMF goals.
A typical stabilization program involves providing incentives that will lead to higher export earnings and to fewer imports. By increasing exports, the LDC earns more foreign money to pay off its debt.
Stabilization programs are controversial because they can have a negative impact on the poor in
the short term. They often require the LDC to lift wage and price controls. As wages drop and prices rise, the poor suffer. Stabilization may also force a government to cut spending on health, food, and education. Negative experiences in East Asia and Argentina have led some critics to question whether IMF policies are the most effective way to repair a troubled economy.
Nongovernmental Organizations Some
private aid groups also work to help LDCs
build their economies. Nongovernmental organizations(NGOs) are independent groups that raise money to fund aid and development programs. Examples include the Red Cross, CARE, and the World Wildlife Fund.
Some NGOs focus on providing food or medical help when natural disasters or wars cause problems. For instance, Oxfam International provides food
to poor countries when they face extreme needs. Others try to promote development. For example, Heifer International gives animals to families in less developed countries. Families use these animals
to produce and sell products such as wool, milk, or honey.
In 1976, Muhammad Yunus of Bangladesh founded the Grameen Bank. Since then, the
bank has extended its operations to nearly every continent. The bank makes small loans—often, as little as a few dollars—to poor people. Many of the borrowers are women in rural villages. They use the
loans to start their own businesses and lift their families out of poverty.
ChECK UNdERSTANdINg What do nongovernmental organizations (NGOs) do?
ASSESSMENT
1. Identify Cause and Effect How do limited natural resources adversely affect many LDCs?
2. ClassifyWhat is the term used to describe capital derived from the savings of a country’s own citizens?
3. ContrastDistinguish between foreign direct investment and foreign portfolio investment.
4. Identify Steps in a Process What does the Grameen Bank do to promote free enterprise in a country?
5. Support a Point of View With Evidence Do you think it would be more beneficial for a country to take a loan to fund new development or to invite in foreign investors?
>> During the civil war in Syria, the Red Cross and the Syrian Arab Red Crescent helped Syrians who fled the country as well as those who faced extremely difficult wartime conditions at home.
10.5 Growth, Resources, and Development 467]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="534"> <text><![CDATA[ 10.6
Change is always challenging. Suppose that suddenly no American could attend high school without paying tuition. It is easy to imagine the hardships this might cause.
But if somebody gave you a million dollars, you might face different sorts of problems. Would you be tempted to spend the money on the wrong things? What new demands might friends and family make of you?
>> Shanghai’s skyscrapers are a symbol of China’s rapid economic growth. The country has set up a free trade zone in Shanghai to allow foreign competition.
 Bounce to Activate Flipped Video
 NGSSS
LAFS.1112.RH.4.10
>> Objectives
Identify the characteristics of economic
transition.
Summarize the political and economic changes experienced by Russia since the fall of communism.
Analyze the reasons for economic growth in China and India in recent years.
Identify the economic challenges faced by developing nations in Africa and Latin America.
>> Key Terms privatization
special economic zones
Changing
Economies
Moving Toward a Market Economy
The same is true of nations. Economic change—even change for the better—always brings new challenges.
Today, many countries are undergoing economic transition. Some are enjoying rapid growth, while others are changing their entire economic systems. In this Lesson, you will look at the changing economies of Russia, China, India, and the countries of Africa and Latin America.
For many nations, economic transition has meant moving from central planning to a market-based economy. In a command economy, the government owns and controls the factors of production. By contrast, in a market-based economy, the factors of production are owned and controlled by individuals. One of the first steps, then, in moving to a market economy is to sell
or transfer government-owned businesses to individuals. This process is called privatization.
Privatizing Business A government can privatize businesses in several ways. It could simply sell the business to one owner. It
Go ONLINE for digital resources
                    Savvas.com/FloridaSS
VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="535"> <text><![CDATA[could also sell shares to investors. A third option is to give every citizen a voucher that can be used to purchase shares in whatever businesses they wish, once those businesses are privatized.
Privatization can be a painful process. Only profitable enterprises will survive in a free market. No one will want to buy unprofitable ones, so many people will lose their jobs. Other job opportunities will eventually appear as the economy grows. However, the initial transition can be difficult for workers accustomed to jobs guaranteed by the government.
Another concern is corruption. Government leaders might make it easier for their own friends and associates to gain control of businesses. The result is an unfair distribution of ownership.
Protecting Property Rights Moving to a market economy also requires changes in the legal system. Centrally planned economies have no need to protect private property rights. A free market economy, however, cannot function without such protections. As a result, the government must create new laws that ensure a person’s right to own and transfer property. Such a basic overhaul of the legal system takes time.
Work Ethic and Attitudes In a planned economy, workers grow used to security. Many have
guaranteed jobs in which their only concern is to meet government quotas. In the free market, such guarantees do not exist. Incentives, not quotas, motivate people’s labor. As a result, workers in a transitioning economy need to learn a new work ethic.
Not surprisingly, people accustomed to central planning often worry about how change will affect them. They might resist the shift to the free market out of fear and uncertainty.
APPLy CONCEPTS Why does moving to a market economy require changes in the legal system?
Changes in Russia
Russia has faced all of the challenges described above. It was once part of the Soviet Union, the world’s most powerful communist nation. But in 1991, Soviet communism—and the Soviet Union itself— collapsed. Russia and the other former Soviet republics began the difficult transition toward a free market economy.
The End of Soviet Communism Under communism, government planners directed the Soviet economy. The nation became an industrial
 METHODSOF PRIVATIZATION
 METHOD
 EXAMPLE
 SELL BUSINESSES TO INDIVIDUALS
 Poland privatized retail shops and small industrial businesses in the early 1990s. The assets of the businesses were typically paid for with periodic payments.
 SELL SHARES TO INVESTORS
 While not a command economy, the United Kingdom had state-owned businesses. It sold shares of many of these in the 1980s, tripling the number of individual investors in the U.K.
 USE VOUCHERS
 In 1991, citizens in
Czechoslovakia
purchased privatization vouchers that were used to bid for shares in as much as 80% of the state enterprises.
Sources: The Concise Encyclopedia of Economics ; “Privatization in Russia: Some Lessons in Eastern Europe” by Jeffrey D. Sachs
>> Analyze Charts What is the difference between the privatization method Czechoslovakia used and the method Poland chose?
10.6 Changing Economies 469]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="536"> <text><![CDATA[giant and a military superpower. The Soviet Union was enormous and rich in many resources, but in the long run, its economy was unable to use those resources to provide for its people. Citizens faced frequent shortages of consumer goods, and the goods they did get were often of poor quality.
In the late 1980s, a new Soviet leader named Mikhail Gorbachev began a series of dramatic political and economic changes to revive the country’s stagnant economy. Gorbachev did not want to overturn the communist economic and political system. Rather, he hoped to incorporate the use of markets and incentives into the existing structure of communism.
The transition to free market economics created problems, however. Economic reform produced some initial hardships. People lost secure government jobs, benefits, and pensions. Many people, especially the elderly, were hurt financially. Some Russians
did begin to make the new system work for them, starting their own businesses and prospering. Still, unrest grew.
At the same time, some officials and army officers feared that the central government was becoming weak. In 1991, they tried to restore old-style communism. The attempt backfired. One by one, the 15 Soviet republics declared their independence. The largest of the new nations was the Russian Republic.
A Hard Transition Russia’s new president, Boris Yeltsin, promised rapid progress toward a market economy. Despite some improvements, hardships continued. When Yeltsin lifted price controls in 1992, prices skyrocketed. People on fixed incomes, such
as retirees living on government pensions, could not afford to buy basics like food and clothing.
In the new Russia, wealth tended to become concentrated in cities such as Moscow. The uneven distribution of income led many to call for additional change. It also led to extensive corruption and widespread organized crime.
Billions of dollars in financial aid flooded
into the country from the World Bank, the IMF,
and independent investors. However, due to mismanagement and corruption, these funds were not used efficiently. By 1998, the Russian economy was in a shambles. Debt was high, investor confidence was low, and the nation was in the midst of an economic crisis.
Russia in the 21st Century Tight controls from
the central government, combined with rising prices for Russian oil, allowed Russian leaders to stem the crisis and repay foreign debt. According to the World Bank, Russia had the world’s sixth-largest GDP in 2012, due to its oil- and export-driven economy. Economic growth has fed growing consumer demand. New laws protect investments, encouraging
Russian Oil Production, 2002–2011
(in kbpd = thousands of barrels per day)
10,500 10,000 9,500 9,000 8,500 8,000 7,500 7,000 6,500
2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011
SOURCE: U.S. Energy Information Administration
>> Analyze Graphs In what year was Russia’s peak oil production?
Which years showed the steepest rise in oil production?
Bounce to Activate Timeline
470 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="537"> <text><![CDATA[Trade Growth in China
U.S. Dollars (in trillions)
2.5 2.0 1.5 1.0 .5 0
1998 2003 2008 2013
Year
SOURCES: CIA World Factbook, Bloomberg.com, Businessweek.com
>> Analyze Graphs Which grew more rapidly between 1998 and 2013, imports or exports? How do you think that helped the Chinese economy?
Bounce to Activate Chart
foreign investors to supply capital to launch new businesses.
Still, problems persist. Russia’s economy relies too much on the export of natural resources. If the prices of these goods drop, export income will
fall, as happened in the economic crisis of 2008. Russia, however, has other goods and services it can develop. It joined the World Trade Organization in 2012, which will reduce trade barriers for Russian imports and help open foreign markets. The future holds challenges—a shrinking workforce, corruption, and lack of investment in infrastructure—but economic integration with the rest of the world is likely to keep the Russian economy within the free market.
SUPPORT IdEAS WITh ExAMPLES Name one economic problem Russia faced before the transition to a free market economy and one problem after the transition.
Growth in Asia Through Trade
Asia, the world’s largest continent, is home to more than 4 billion people—over 60 percent of the world’s total population. These people provide a huge workforce and a huge market for goods and services.
In recent decades, Asia has become one of the most dynamic players in the global economy. Nations such as Singapore, South Korea, and Taiwan have incomes comparable to highly developed nations in the rest of the world.
China is a major exporter of goods and a key trading partner of the United States. India, too,
has experienced rapid economic growth. How did these two nations, once among the world’s poorest, advance so far, so rapidly?
China In 1949, after a long civil war, communists led by Mao Zedong took power in China. They quickly put in place communist policies, giving
the government ownership of all land, resources, and enterprises. Government planners made all key decisions about the economy.
After Mao died in 1976, Deng Xiaoping became China’s new leader. Deng soon began using the tools of the free market to increase productivity. He gave farmers and factory managers more freedom to make decisions about what to produce and how much to charge for it. He also rewarded farmers, managers, and workers who increased output. With such incentives, production increased.
Deng also set up four free market centers along China’s east coast. Foreign businesses could operate, and local governments were allowed to offer tax incentives to foreign investors in these special
Bounce to Activate Chart
 10.6 Changing Economies 471]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="538"> <text><![CDATA[economic zones. Chinese businesses could operate freely as well, with managers making most of their own investment and production decisions. This approach proved so successful that China now has hundreds of these zones.
Deng’s successors have continued his policies. The economic changes, especially increased trade, have led to huge economic growth. Where the country once lagged far behind most nations of Europe and North America, China in 2013 had the world’s second most productive economy, after the United States. In 2009, China became the world’s largest exporter of goods. Since 2011, consumer spending by Chinese citizens has been a bigger driver of growth than investment. Chinese cities are now full of people who enjoy access to a wide variety of consumer goods.
Still, development has brought its share of problems. Rapid urban growth has led to increases in crime and pollution. The poor complain that the government is abandoning its promise to provide jobs and healthcare for all the nation’s people. In addition, growth has not reached all parts of the country. The government has announced that it is
planning to focus less on trade in the coming years and more on economic reform and education.
Finally, economic development has not meant political liberty. Chinese citizens still do not enjoy many political rights. The government tightly controls the press and stifles dissent.
India India is the world’s second most populous nation, after China. A former British colony, India struggled economically after winning independence. In the 1990s, though, India’s government began to invite foreign investment and promote other free market practices.
New policies encouraged Indian companies to expand. One area of significant growth was in high- technology industries. Many software companies opened new facilities in India, where educated workers could offer technical support to computer users around the world. Manufacturing grew as well.
Economic growth helped promote the emergence of a much larger middle class. One business executive noted the significance of this development:
When half the population in a society is middle class, its politics will change . . . its poor will be fewer—and society will have greater means to look after them.
—Gurcharan Das, “India’s Growing Middle Class”
India’s middle class provides a growing market for consumer goods. As the middle class seeks more (and more expensive) goods, local and foreign producers compete to meet that demand.
Still, as with China, India’s development is not complete. Over half of the labor force farms, and
only 19 percent is employed in industry. The result
is a growing gap between the richest and poorest citizens. In fact, this is true of virtually all nations with developing economies. Urban dwellers with education and skills benefit the most from growth. Uneducated people in poor rural areas struggle with poverty and continue to rely on subsistence farming.
IdENTIfy SUPPORTINg dETAILS Name two areas of growth in India’s economy.
>> Rapid industrialization without government regulation has caused damage to the environment in China. Heavy pollution is an ongoing problem, and it is common for people to wear face masks outside, as these Beijing pedestrians are doing.
472 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="539"> <text><![CDATA[Brazil’s Major Exports, 2010
Percent of Total Dollar Value
14 12 10 8 6 4 2 0
Iron
ore and concentrates
Petroleum oils Raw sugar, cane
Soybeans
Poultry
Coffee
Woodpulp
Cars
Aircraft Car parts
Major Exports
SOURCE: The Observatory of Economic Complexity
>> Analyze Graphs How much more valuable is Brazil’s export of petroleum oils than its export of cars? Do you think that ratio will change in the future? Why or why not?
Growth and Challenges in Africa and Latin America
Like Asia, Africa and Latin America are home to many poor countries. Some nations in these two regions have seen great economic growth in recent years. Others continue to struggle.
Continuing Poverty in Africa Some North
African nations have built productive economies. This success is mainly due to large reserves of oil. South of the Sahara, however, most nations face the obstacles common to all less developed countries. Economies are largely based on subsistence farming. Low literacy rates, inadequate healthcare and nutrition, high rates of HIV infection, and mounting debt hinder development efforts. Some nations are also plagued by years of civil war or ethnic conflict. Only two African nations south of the Sahara have sizable economies—South Africa and Nigeria.
Nigeria benefits from large reserves of oil. Yet over-dependence on oil has slowed growth in other areas. Nigeria also suffers from widespread political corruption and ethnic conflict. However, President Goodluck Jonathan, who became president in 2010, promised to reform the country’s electoral process, tackle corruption, and resolve Nigeria’s energy problems.
In the 1990s, South Africa shifted from longtime rule by its white minority to black majority rule. Problems in this political transition, along with high rates of HIV infection, slowed economic growth. Unemployment remains high, and poverty remains a problem. Still, South Africa has one of the 25 highest GDPs in the world. It benefits from a rich array of natural resources and a strong manufacturing base.
Different Paths in Latin America In Latin America, the two biggest success stories are
Brazil and Mexico. Both countries have abundant resources. Both have also taken steps to make their economies more diverse.
Brazil exports iron ore and timber, and its land and climate are highly suitable for growing coffee and soybeans. The discovery of large offshore oil reserves in late 2007 promises to turn Brazil into
a major oil-exporting power. Oil production grew from around 2,300 barrels a day in 2007 to 2,600 barrels a day in 2012. Brazil has become a strong manufacturing power, producing everything from vehicles to shoes. It has also adapted its sugar industry to produce ethanol. Brazil builds cars that can run on either gasoline or ethanol. More than 40 percent of the fuel that powers Brazilian cars comes from ethanol derived from sugar cane.
Mexico has reserves of oil and silver and produces rich crops of cotton and coffee. Like Brazil, Mexico
Major Exports
10.6 Changing Economies 473]]></text>
   </page>
    
    </eBook>