<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <eBook>
    <page pageNumber="410"> <text><![CDATA[ AUDIO VIDEO WRITING TEXT ASSESSMENT GAMES ACTIVITY PDF Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS [ ESSENTIAL QUESTION ] Can and should the government be fair to everyone? 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="411"> <text><![CDATA[ Next Generation Sunshine State Standards SS.912.E.2.8, HE.912.C.2.4, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9, ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1 Enduring Understandings &bull; Governments collect taxes to pay for programs, but taxes can have powerful effects on the general economy. &bull; The federal government taxes income, the manufacture or sale of some goods, imports, and other sources of wealth. &bull; The national government spends tax money on mandatory outlays, including entitlements such as Social Security, and on discretionary spending. &bull; State taxes provide money for education, public safety, transportation, and other public goods. &bull; Local governments tax residents in order to pay for police, fire protection, education, and other public goods. >> On April 15 every year is the deadline for Americans to file their individual tax returns.Learn more about how taxes relate to income and affect people across the country. Bounce to Activate My Story Video 345 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="412"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 8 Overview In this topic, you will learn about how all levels of government levy taxes and make decisions about spending. Look at the lesson outline and explore the graph. As you study this topic, you&apos;ll complete the quest team project. LESSON OUTLINE 8.1 Understanding Taxes SS.912.E.2.8, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 8.2 Federal Taxes SS.912.E.2.8 8.3 Federal Spending SS.912.E.2.9, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 8.4 State and Local Taxes and  Spending ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1, HE.912.C.2.4 Federal Receipts, 2014 (Estimated) 3% 6% 46% 11% 34% Individual income taxes Social Security, Medicare, unemployment, and other retirement receipts Corporate income taxes Excise Taxes Customs, estate, gift, and other taxes SOURCE: Office of Management and Budget 346 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="413"> <text><![CDATA[ TEAM PROJECT Civic Action Project While government has a limited role in our free enterprise system, governments at all levels levy taxes to provide a wide range of services, such as highway construction and vehicle inspections. In this quest, you&apos;ll conduct a service project on a government service or a form of taxation that interests you. STEP 1 What is an issue you care about? Research a local, state, or federal government service or tax. Is the service necessary? Is the tax fair? STEP 2 Come up with a new service or a new way to fund government. Seek out experts or reliable sources on this issue and get their input. How can you improve the situation? STEP 3 Ramp up interest! Raise awareness through opinion polls, a web site, social media, or fliers. Try to get your local newspaper, radio, and television to cover the issue. STEP 4 Make something happen! Build support for your plan with a petition, panel discussion, and letters to or meetings with public officials. NGSSS LAFS.1112.RH.3.7 RUBRIC ETEXT WRITING VIDEO ASSESSMENT PDF Go ONLINE for complete Quest materials Savvas.com/FloridaSS 347 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="414"> <text><![CDATA[ 8.1 You&apos;re looking forward to getting your first paycheck. You figure that at $7 per hour, you should be getting $140 for the 20 hours you worked. When you open the envelope, you find that the check is for much less than $140. Where did the money go? The answer is: taxes! A tax is a required payment to a local, state, or national government. The federal government and most state governments levy taxes on personal income. Is this fair? >> Taxes help fund essential services such as law enforcement. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 >> Objectives Identify the sources of the government&apos;s authority to tax in the U.S. Constitution. Describe types of tax bases and tax structures. Identify who bears the burden of a tax. Describe the key characteristics of a tax. >> Key Terms tax revenue progressive tax proportional tax regressive tax tax base individual income tax corporate income tax property tax sales tax incidence of a tax Understanding Taxes The Importance of National Taxes Fairness, or equity, is one of the main goals of a tax system. But what is fair to one person may not be fair to another. For example, some would argue that fairness requires that all people be taxed at the same rate. Others say that the person who earns more money should pay a higher percentage of income in taxes. In fact, this concept, known as progressive taxation, has been at the base of our income tax system since its beginnings. (You will read more about progressive taxation and the concept of equity shortly.) The Impact of Taxation Looking at all of the taxes taken from your paycheck can be discouraging. You worked hard for that money, and now it is being taken away. Similar feelings of frustration over taxes helped persuade American colonists to declare their independence from Britain. Unlike those colonists, however, an overwhelming majority of citizens today consent to having a portion of their earnings taken by the government. We authorize the federal government, through VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="415"> <text><![CDATA[ the Constitution and our elected representatives in Congress, to raise money in the form of taxes. In fact, taxation is the primary way that the government collects money. Taxes give the government the money it needs to operate. The income received by a government from taxes and other nontax sources is called revenue. Without revenue from taxes, the government would not be able to provide the goods and services that we not only benefit from, but also expect the government to provide. For example, we authorize the government to spend well over $3.5 trillion a year. This money helps provide national defense, highways, education, and law enforcement. We also ask the government to provide help to people in need. All of these goods and services cost money&ndash; in workers&apos; salaries, in materials, in land and labor. All members of our society share these costs through the payment of taxes. The national taxes we pay and the spending they help make possible have a large macroeconomic impact. Total government spending in the United States was over 32 percent of gross domestic product in fiscal year 2013. Federal outlays alone topped 20 percent of GDP. The way these huge sums are collected and then spent can have a number of effects on economic growth&ndash;helping to spur it in some cases and dampening it in others. The Power to Tax Taxation is a powerful tool. The founders of the United States thought long and hard before giving this tool to their new national government. The Constitution they created assigned each branch of the government certain powers and responsibilities. The powers of the legislative branch&ndash;Congress&ndash;appear in Article I, Section 8. The very first clause in this section grants Congress the power to tax. This clause is the basis for all federal tax laws. Limits on the Power to Tax The Constitution also spells out specific limits on the government&apos;s power to tax. Two of those limits are in the taxation clause. First, the purpose of a tax must be “to pay the debts and provide for the common defense and general welfare of the United States.” A tax cannot bring in money that goes to individual interests. Second, federal taxes must be the same in every state. The federal gas tax, for example, cannot be 4 cents per gallon in Maryland and 10 cents per gallon in South Dakota. Other provisions of the Constitution also limit the kinds of taxes Congress can levy, or impose. For example, Congress cannot tax religious services, because that would violate the freedom of religion promised by the First Amendment. The Twenty- Fourth Amendment prohibits “poll taxes,” or tax payments required in order to vote. Another clause of the Constitution prohibits taxing exports&ndash;goods sent out of the United States to foreign customers. The government can collect taxes only on imports&ndash;goods brought into the United States. (Congress can restrict or prohibit the export of certain goods, however, such as technology or weapons.) Yet another clause of the Constitution (Article 1, Section 9, Clause 4) prohibits Congress from levying a capitation, or “head,” tax, which is a tax to be paid by every single person. This same clause also prohibited direct taxes unless they were divided among the states according to population. A direct tax is one paid directly by a taxpayer to the government rather than indirectly&ndash;say, to a shopkeeper who later sends the money to the government. But, the Sixteenth Amendment legalized a direct tax on citizens&apos; personal income. This income-tax amendment was ratified in 1913. IDENTIFY MAIN IDEAS According to the Constitution, for what purpose can government collect taxes? Tax Structures and Tax Bases Despite the constitutional limits on its power, the government actually collects a wide variety of taxes. Economists describe these taxes in different >> On December 16, 1773, American colonists protested British tax policy by dumping chests of tea into the Boston Harbor&ndash;an event known as the Boston Tea Party. Bounce to Activate Chart 8.1 Understanding Taxes 349 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="416"> <text><![CDATA[ ways. First, they describe how the tax is structured. Economists describe three different tax structures: progressive, proportional, and regressive. Second, they describe a tax according to the object taxed&ndash; the tax base. Progressive Taxes A progressive tax is a tax for which the percentage of income paid in taxes increases as income increases. People with higher incomes pay a higher percentage of their income in taxes. People with very small incomes might pay no tax at all. In the United States, the federal income tax is structured this way. Figure 8.1 illustrates a progressive tax system. Notice that the tax rate in this example rises from 15 to 25 and then to 30 percent for that portion of income above certain levels. This is a progressive tax rate structure because as income rises, the percentage of income paid in taxes also rises. Proportional Taxes A proportional tax is a tax for which the percentage of income paid in taxes remains the same at all income levels. Selena Diaz, a corporate executive, earns $350,000 per year. Tony Owens, a nurse, earns $50,000 per year. If government levied a 6 percent proportional tax on both their incomes, Selena would pay 6 percent of $350,000, or $21,000, in taxes. Tony would pay 6 percent of $50,000, or $3,000, in taxes. With a proportional income tax, whether income goes up or down, the percentage of income paid in taxes stays the same. Regressive Taxes A regressive tax is a tax for which the percentage of income paid in taxes decreases as income increases. The sales tax levied on the sale of goods and services in many states is generally regressive&ndash;even though the sales tax rate remains constant. This is because higher-income households typically spend a lower proportion of their incomes on the goods and services that are taxable under a sales tax. As a result, although wealthier people may pay more actual dollars in sales taxes, the proportion of their incomes spent on sales taxes is lower than that of lower-income households. Selena Diaz, for example, may pay $8,000 in sales taxes while Tony Owens pays $3,500. But Tony is paying 7 percent of his income in sales taxes while Selena is paying only about 2 percent. Tax Bases A tax base is the income, property, good, or service that is subject to a tax. Different taxes have different bases. The individual income tax is based on a person&apos;s earnings. The corporate PROGRESSIVE TAXATION INCOME $25,000 $25,000 $3,750 TAX RATE 15% TOTAL TAXES $3,750 INCOME $75,000 $50,000 TAX RATE 25% $12,500 $25,000 TAX RATE 15% $3,750 TOTAL TAXES $16,250 INCOME $100,000 $25,000 TAX RATE 30% $7,500 $50,000 TAX RATE 25% $12,500 $25,000 TAX RATE 15% $3,750 TOTAL TAXES $23,750 >> Figure 8.1 The progressive structure shown here is similar&ndash;but not identical&ndash;to the federal income tax. Analyze Graphs What percentage of total income does each earner shown on this graph pay? Bounce to Activate Chart 350 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="417"> <text><![CDATA[ Who Bears the Tax Burden: Inelastic Demand New supply with $.50 tax Original supply Price $1.40 $1.00 Lower quantity Higher quantity Quantity Demand  >> Figure 8.2 This graph shows the effect of a tax when the demand for the good being taxed is inelastic. Analyze Graphs Do you think consumers or businesses will pay the larger share of the tax? Explain. income tax uses a company&apos;s profits as its base. The property tax is based on real estate and other property. The tax base for the sales tax is goods or services that are sold. When government policymakers create a new tax, they first decide what the base will be for the tax: income, profits, property, sales, or some other category. RECALL Is the federal individual income tax proportional, progressive, or regressive? The Tax Burden Government tax policies have a real impact on millions of individuals and businesses. These impacts can affect the entire economy. Thus, it is important to think about who actually bears the burden of a tax. This is not necessarily the person who sends in the money to pay the tax bill. How can we know who is actually bearing the burden of a tax? The answer lies in supply-and-demand analysis. For the purpose of this analysis, consider this example: Suppose the government imposes a gasoline tax of $.50 per gallon and collects the tax from service stations. You may think the burden of the tax falls only on the service stations, because they send the tax money to the government. But you will see that this is not always the case. Figure 8.2 shows the original supply curve (in green) and a supply curve after the $.50 tax is imposed (in blue). You see that before the tax, the market was at equilibrium, and gas cost $1.00 per gallon. The new supply curve reflects the fact that when a tax is imposed on a good, the cost of supplying the good increases. Quantity supplied will decrease at every price level. Notice the steep demand curve in Figure 8.2. This is what you would see if demand for gas were inelastic&ndash;that is, if consumers bought about the same amount no matter what the price. So, when demand is inelastic, the tax will increase the price of each gallon by a relatively large amount, and consumers will bear a large share of the tax. The $.50 tax will increase the equilibrium price by $.40 (from $1.00 to $1.40). In other words, consumers will pay about four fifths of the tax. In contrast, if demand is relatively elastic, the demand curve will be relatively flat, as in Figure 8.3. Consumers will pay a relatively small part of the tax. In this case, a $.50 tax increases the equilibrium price by only $.10 (from $1.00 to $1.10). Consumers pay only one fifth of the tax. Businesses pay the other four fifths. This example shows the incidence of a tax&ndash; that is, the final burden of a tax. When policymakers consider a new tax, they examine who will actually 8.1 Understanding Taxes 351 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="418"> <text><![CDATA[ bear the burden. As in the example above, producers can “pass on” a portion of the burden to consumers. Generally, the more inelastic the demand, the more easily the seller can shift the tax to consumers. The more elastic the demand, the more the seller bears the burden. RECALL Who bears the greater burden of a tax on a good or service when demand is inelastic? Key Characteristics of a Tax Although it is sometimes difficult to decide whether a specific tax is proportional, progressive, or regressive, economists do generally agree on the qualities a tax ought to have. A tax should have four characteristics: simplicity; efficiency; certainty; and equity, or fairness. Simplicity. Tax laws should be simple and easily understood. Taxpayers and businesses should be able to keep the necessary records and pay the taxes on a predictable schedule. Efficiency. Government administrators should be able to assess and collect taxes without spending too much time or money. Similarly, taxpayers should be able to pay taxes without giving up too much time or paying too much money in fees. Certainty. Certainty is also a characteristic of a good tax. It should be clear to the taxpayer when a tax is due, how much money is due, and how the tax should be paid. Equity. The tax system should be fair, so that no one bears too much or too little of the tax burden. Determining Equity Although everyone agrees that a tax system should be equitable and fair to taxpayers, people often disagree on what equity really means. Does it require equal distribution of wealth, or does it simply demand equal opportunity and treatment for all? Over time, this debate has led economists to propose two different ideas about how to measure the fairness of a tax. The first idea is called the benefits-received principle. According to this principle, a person should pay taxes based on the level of benefits he or she expects to receive from the government. People who drive, for example, pay gasoline taxes that are used to build and maintain highways. In this way, the people who receive the most benefit from the roads contribute the most to their upkeep. The second idea about fairness is called the ability-to-pay principle. According to this principle, people should pay taxes according to their ability Who Bears the Tax Burden: Elastic Demand New supply with $.50 tax Original supply Price $1.10 $1.00 Lower quantity Higher quantity Quantity Demand >> Figure 8.3 Here we see the impact of a tax when demand for the taxed good is elastic. Analyze Graphs Do you think consumers or businesses will pay the larger share of the tax? Explain. 352 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="419"> <text><![CDATA[ to pay. This is the principle behind a progressive income tax: People who earn more income pay more taxes. Achieving equity in a tax system for a nation the size of the U.S. is a huge challenge. Many complain about the number and complexity of taxes we are subject to. Some of this complexity is the result of efforts to achieve equity. Balancing Tax Revenues and Tax Rates How much revenue does a good tax generate? The answer is “enough, but not too much.” That is, enough so that citizens&apos; needs are met, but not so much that the tax discourages production. For example, if a company has to pay $100,000 in taxes, it will not be able to use that $100,000 to expand production. If tax rates are lower, however, the company can use more of its income to stimulate production rather than to pay taxes. Ultimately, many people argue, the economy benefits from lower tax rates. The debate over the appropriate level of taxation is a vigorous one. In this country&ndash;and around the world&ndash;people have widely different views on this subject. CHECK UNDERSTANDING What four characteristics do economists believe a tax should possess? ASSESSMENT 1. Summarize What does the United States Constitution say about government&apos;s power to tax? 2. Draw Conclusions Suppose Michelle earns $40,000 per year and Rosa earns $100,000 per year. Under a proportional tax, who would pay a greater percentage of her income in taxes? >> The government&apos;s Internal Revenue Service (IRS) has a “long form” and a simpler “short form” for filing taxes. Analyze Political Cartoons What does this cartoon suggest about the tax system? 3. Cite Evidence Cite evidence from your reading that illustrates the economic importance of national taxes in the United States. 4. Contrast How do progressive taxes differ from regressive taxes? 5. Predict Consequences Suppose the government imposed a new tax on an item for which demand is typically inelastic. Who would probably end up bearing the incidence of the tax? Why? 8.1 Understanding Taxes 353 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="420"> <text><![CDATA[ 8.2 The United States has a government “of the people, by the people, for the people.” For that government to function, it needs the economic backing of the American people. If you work and pay income taxes, you are helping to support the work the government does. Taxes are of great economic importance to the nation. >> Our tax system promotes equity, but its complexity makes it necessary for many people to get help preparing their taxes. This couple is meeting with a professional tax preparer. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS SS.912.E.2.8, SS.912.FL.6.8 >> Objectives Identify the basic characteristics and importance of individual and corporate income taxes at the national level. Explain the purpose and importance of Social Security, Medicare, and unemployment taxes. Identify other types of taxes levied at the national level. >> Key Terms direct tax withholding tax return taxable income personal exemption tax credit indirect tax estate tax gift tax tax incentive tax deduction tariffs Federal Taxes Individual and Corporate Income Taxes The income tax is one category of revenue and one of several taxes collected by the federal government. The federal government also receives revenue from corporate income taxes, social insurance taxes, excise taxes, estate and gift taxes, and taxes on imports. Individual Income Taxes The government&apos;s main source of revenues is the federal tax on individuals&apos; taxable income. This is a direct tax, or a tax collected directly from the person or entity that pays it. As Figure 8.4 shows, 46 percent of the federal government&apos;s receipts for 2014 were expected to come from the payment of individual income taxes. The graph shows the other sources of government receipts, as well. It is important to note that today, the receipts shown in Figure 8.4 rarely cover the full cost of government. In recent decades, the federal government has borrowed huge sums of money virtually every year to cover budget deficits. The amount of federal income tax a person owes is determined on an annual basis. In theory, the federal government could wait until the end of the tax year to collect individual income taxes. In VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="421"> <text><![CDATA[ reality, that would be a problem for both taxpayers and the government. Like other employers, the government has to pay regularly for rent, supplies, services, and employees&apos; salaries. A single annual payment from all the nation&apos;s taxpayers at once would make meeting these expenses difficult. Similarly, many people might have trouble paying their taxes in one large sum. For these reasons, federal income tax is collected in a “pay-as-you-earn” system. This means that individuals usually pay most of their income tax throughout the calendar year as they earn income. They have until mid-April of the following year to pay any additional income taxes they owe. Individual Tax Brackets The federal income tax is a progressive tax, which is aimed at the economic goal of equity. In other words, the tax rate rises with the amount of taxable income. You can see this progressive structure in Figure 8.5. This table gives the rates for an unmarried filer who is not the head of a household. Married couples who file their taxes jointly have a different set of tax rates. The schedule you see here shows seven rates. Each applies to a different range of income, or tax bracket. For example, a person subject to this tax table and with a taxable income of $8,925 or less would pay 10 percent income tax. If that person earned more than $400,000 in taxable income, he or she would pay the highest rate&ndash;39.6 percent&ndash; on earnings in excess of that amount. (The person would pay lower rates on the income below $400,000.) Each year, the IRS publishes new tax rate schedules that reflect any changes in the federal tax code. Supporters of our progressive system argue that it helps promote the economic goal of equity. Others, however, say progressive rates reduce the incentive to work hard and earn more. Our progressive tax system may add cost in the form of complexity. One recent study claimed Americans spend $140 and 7.6 billion hours annually on their federal taxes alone. Not all of this time and money is a result of the progressive tax code, but some of it is. Tax Withholding Employers are responsible in part for carrying out the system of collecting federal income taxes. They do so by withholding, or taking payments out of your pay before you receive it. The amount they withhold is based on an estimate of how much you will owe in federal income taxes for the entire year. After withholding the money, the employer forwards it to the federal government as an “installment payment” on your upcoming annual income tax bill. Federal Receipts, 2014 (Estimated) 3% 6% 46% 11% 34% Individual income taxes Social Security, Medicare, unemployment, and other retirement receipts Corporate income taxes Excise Taxes Customs, estate, gift, and other taxes SOURCE: Office of Management and Budget >> Figure 8.4 Analyze Graphs Based on this graph, what effect would an economic downturn, with lower corporate and individual earnings, have on government receipts? Explain. Bounce to Activate Chart 8.2 Federal Taxes 355 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="422"> <text><![CDATA[ Filing a Tax Return After the calendar year ends, employers give their employees a report stating how much income tax has already been withheld and sent to the government. The employee uses that information to complete a tax return. A tax return is a form used to file income taxes. On it, you declare your income to the government and figure out how much of that income is taxable. Taxable income is a person&apos;s gross (or total) income minus exemptions and deductions. Gross income includes earned income&ndash;salaries, wages, tips, and commissions. It also includes income from investments such as interest on savings accounts and dividends from stock. Personal exemptions are set amounts that you subtract from your gross income for yourself, your spouse, and any dependents. Tax deductions are amounts that you can subtract, or deduct, from your gross income. Commonly taken deductions include mortgage interest, large medical expenses, and state and local tax payments. Taxpayers may also deduct charitable donations. By creating a tax benefit for charitable giving, the government creates a positive incentive and lowers the cost of giving money away. The government created this incentive because, while charitable giving costs donors money they could use for other purposes, it also provides great benefits to the organizations that receive the money, the people those organizations serve, and society at large. Once you determine how much tax you owe, you can apply available tax credits. A tax credit is an amount that you can subtract from the total amount of your income tax. You can claim a credit for such things as a portion of the cost of child care and higher education. Completing a tax return allows you to determine whether the amount of income taxes you have already paid is higher or lower than the actual amount owed. If you have paid more than you owe, the government sends you a refund. If you have paid less than you owe, you must pay the balance. All federal income tax returns must be sent to the Internal Revenue Service, or IRS, by midnight on April 15 (or the next business day if April 15 falls on a weekend or holiday). Corporate Income Taxes Like individuals, corporations must pay federal income tax on their taxable income. Recall, Figure 8.4 showed that corporate taxes were expected to account for 11 percent of federal receipts in 2014. Determining corporate taxable income can be a challenge, because businesses can take many deductions. That is, they can subtract many expenses from their income before they reach the amount of income that is subject to taxation. For Federal Income Tax Rates, 2013 For Unmarried People Who Are Not Heads of Households IF TAXABLE INCOME IS OVER $0 $8,925 $36,250 $87,850 $183,250 $398,350 $400,000 BUT NOT OVER $8,925 $36,250 $87,850 $183,250 $398,350 $400,000 no limit THE TAX IS 10% $892.50 plus 15% of taxable income over $8,925 $4,991.25 plus 25% of taxable income over $36,250 $17,891.25 plus 28% of taxable income over $87,850 $44,603.25 plus 33% of taxable income over $183,250 $115,586.25 plus 35% of taxable income over $398,350 $116,163.75 plus 39.6% of taxable income over $400,000 SOURCE: Internal Revenue Service >> Figure 8.5 Analyze Charts Assuming this schedule applied to you, in what range would your taxable income fall if you were in the 28 percent tax bracket? 356 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="423"> <text><![CDATA[ Two Views on Corporate Taxes "Today, large U.S. corporations report more than $1 trillion in cash or liquid assets. They have the funds to invest in new jobs, should they choose to do so. We found no evidence that cutting the tax rate on corporate profits induces firms to create new jobs in the United States." &ndash;Center for Effective Government, “The Corporate Tax Rate Debate,” December 2013 "American manufacturers are at a distinct disadvantage to competitors headquartered in other countries. Specifically, foreign manufacturers uniformly face a lower corporate tax rate than U.S. manufacturers, and virtually all operate under territorial systems which encourage investment both abroad and at home.” &ndash;Susan Ford, Corning, Inc. executive, testimony before Congress, July 2012 Two Views on Corporate Taxes >> Views on corporate income taxes vary widely. Compare Points of View How might Susan Ford reply to the views expressed in the quote from the Center for Effective Government? example, companies deduct the cost of employees&apos; health insurance. Many other costs of doing business can also be deducted. Like individual income tax rates, corporate income tax rates are progressive. For 2013, rates begin at 15 percent on the first $50,000 of taxable income. On the highest corporate income, above $18,333,333, the tax rate is 35 percent. DEFINE What is a person&apos;s or corporation&apos;s taxable income? Social Security, Medicare, and Unemployment Taxes In addition to withholding money for income taxes, employers withhold money for taxes authorized under the Federal Insurance Contributions Act, or FICA. FICA taxes fund two large government social- insurance programs, Social Security and Medicare. Employees and employers share FICA payments. Social Security Taxes Most of the FICA taxes you pay go to the Social Security Administration to fund Old-Age, Survivors, and Disability Insurance (OASDI), or Social Security. Social Security was established in 1935 to ease the hardships of the Great Depression. From the start, Social Security provided old-age pensions and unemployment insurance to workers. Today, it also provides benefits to surviving family members of wage earners and to people whose disabilities keep them from working. Each year the government establishes an income cap for Social Security taxes. In 2013, the cap was $113,700. No Social Security taxes could be withheld from a taxpayer&apos;s wages and salaries above that amount. Medicare Taxes FICA taxes also fund Medicare. The Medicare program is a national health insurance program that helps pay for healthcare for people over age 65. It also covers people with certain disabilities. Both employees and self-employed people pay the Medicare tax on all their earnings. There is no ceiling as there is for Social Security payments. In spite of this fact, Medicare is experiencing a growing gap between receipts in tax payments and expenditures. You will learn more about this shortly. Unemployment Taxes The federal government also collects an unemployment tax, which is paid by employers. In effect, the tax pays for an insurance policy for workers. 8.2 Federal Taxes 357 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="424"> <text><![CDATA[ If workers are laid off from their jobs through no fault of their own, they can file an “unemployment compensation” claim and collect benefits for a fixed number of weeks. In order to collect unemployment benefits, an unemployed person usually must show that he or she is actively looking for another job. The unemployment program is financed by both state and federal unemployment taxes. CATEDORIZE Who benefits from Medicare taxes? Other National Taxes What are the taxes on gasoline and cable television service called? If you inherit money from your great aunt, will you have to pay a tax? Why are some imported products so expensive? To answer these questions, you need to look at excise, estate, gift, and import taxes. Excise Taxes An excise tax is a general revenue tax on the sale or manufacture of a good. Federal excise taxes apply to gasoline, cigarettes, alcoholic beverages, telephone services, cable television, and other items. An excise tax is an example of an indirect tax, or a tax that is collected by a person or business other than the one who pays it. In this case, businesses collect the tax and consumers pay it. >> Analyze Political Cartoons How would you summarize this cartoon&apos;s view of the estate tax? Bounce to Activate Gallery Estate Taxes An estate tax is a tax on the estate, or total value of the money and property, of a person who has died. It is paid out of the person&apos;s estate before the heirs receive their share. A person&apos;s estate includes not only money, but also real estate, cars, furniture, investments, jewelry, paintings, and insurance. As of 2013, if the total value of an estate was $5,250,000 or less, there was no federal estate tax. Because an estate tax is a progressive tax, the rate rises with increasing value. That is, a larger estate will be taxed by the federal government at a higher rate than a smaller one. Gift Taxes The gift tax is a tax on the money or property that one living person gives to another. The goal of the gift tax, established in 1924, was to keep people from avoiding estate taxes by giving away their money before they died. Under current law, a person can give up to $14,000 a year tax-free to each of several different people. Tariffs&ndash;Taxes on Imported Goods Taxes on imported goods (foreign goods brought into the country) are called tariffs. Tariffs were once the most important source of federal revenue, but that is no longer the case. Today they represent a tiny share of federal revenues. Today, most tariffs are intended to protect American farmers and industries from foreign competitors rather than to generate revenue. Tariffs raise the prices of foreign items, which helps keep the prices of American products competitive. Taxes That Affect Behavior The basic goal of taxation is to create revenue. However, governments sometimes use tax policy to discourage the public from buying harmful products. They also use taxes to encourage constructive behavior. The use of taxation to discourage or encourage behavior is called a tax incentive. One example you learned about earlier is the available tax deduction for charitable giving. Federal taxes on tobacco products and alcoholic beverages are examples of so-called sin taxes. Their main purpose is to discourage people from buying and using these products. Incentives also come in the form of tax credits. Congress tries to encourage energy conservation by offering a variety of credits to consumers and industry. People may receive tax credits for purchasing fuel-efficient electric or hybrid vehicles or for improvements that make buildings more energy efficient. Under the Affordable Care Act, 358 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="425"> <text><![CDATA[ the healthcare law passed in 2010, the purchase of the healthcare law passed in 2010, the purchase of health insurance may lead to a tax credit for some. Those who fail to purchase coverage may face a penalty. COMPARE AND CONTRAST How has the role of tariffs changed over history? ASSESSMENT 1. Compare and Contrast How would a single person with a taxable income of $15,000 per year and a single person with a taxable income of $300,000 per year be treated differently—and similarly—in terms of national taxes? 2. Express Ideas Clearly Why do people in the United States pay unemployment taxes? 3. Draw Conclusions What is the purpose of tax incentives? 4. Identify What are the main sources of federal government receipts? 5. Express Ideas Clearly What is an example of how the U.S. tax system attempts to promote the goal of economic equity? 8.2 Federal Taxes 359 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="426"> <text><![CDATA[ 8.3 Suppose that each year you were given a million dollars to spend on serious expenses. So much money! So many choices! Where would you begin? The federal government, with a budget that approaches $4 trillion, faces a similar “dilemma” every year. 8.3 >> Many military veterans are entitled to pensions based on their service to the country. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS SS.912.E.2.9, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 >> Objectives Analyze categories of expenditures in the U.S. federal budget. Describe major entitlement programs. Identify major types of discretionary spending in the federal budget. >> Key Terms mandatory spending discretionary spending entitlement Federal Spending Mandatory and Discretionary Spending Through the democratic process, the American public chooses between candidates who often have different ideas on how the federal government should spend its income. As you will read, government spending meets numerous needs. Our elected leaders have decided that much of the money should provide for our health and welfare. In reality, when the government considers the huge sum of money it collects to fund the budget, most of it is already accounted for. After the government fulfills all its legal obligations, only about a third of the money remains to be spent. Figure 8.6 shows the major categories of federal spending in the 2012 budget year. Some of these categories, such as Social Security and Medicare, are mandatory. Mandatory spending refers to money that Congress is mandated, or required, by existing law to spend on certain programs or to use for interest payments on the national debt. Other categories, such as defense and education, are discretionary. Discretionary spending is spending about which lawmakers are free to make choices. VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="427"> <text><![CDATA[ In general, the percentage of federal spending that is mandatory has grown in recent years. The percentage of discretionary spending has decreased. ExPRESS IdEAS CLEARLy Explain why government does not truly get to decide how to spend all the money in its budget. Government Entitlements Except for interest on the national debt, most of the mandatory spending items in the federal budget are for entitlement programs. Entitlements are social welfare programs that people are “entitled to” and benefit from if they meet certain eligibility requirements, such as being at a particular income level or age. The federal government guarantees assistance for all those who qualify. As the number of people who qualify rises, mandatory spending rises as well. As a result, managing the cost of entitlement programs has become a major concern. Some, but not all, entitlements are “meanstested.” In other words, people with higher incomes may receive lower benefits or no benefits at all. Medicaid, for instance, is means-tested. Social Security is not. A retired person who has worked and paid Social Security taxes is entitled to certain benefits. Similarly, military veterans and retired federal employees are entitled to receive pensions from the government. Entitlements are a largely unchanging part of government spending. Once Congress has set the requirements, it cannot control how many people become eligible for each kind of benefit. Congress can change the eligibility requirements or reduce the amount of the benefit in order to try to keep costs down. Such actions, however, require a change in the law. Social Security Social Security makes up a huge portion of all federal spending. About 58 million Americans receive monthly benefits from the Social Security Administration. Of those beneficiaries, some are disabled workers, but the great majority are retired workers. Many of those retirees rely solely on their Social Security checks to support themselves. The Social Security system faces an uncertain future today. To understand the uncertainty, you must understand how the Social Security system is set up. American workers pay into the system through taxes. Those taxes go toward benefits for people who are no longer working. That is, the money that you pay into Social Security today does not go into a fund for your own future retirement. It goes toward supporting people who have already retired. For the system to function properly, there must be enough workers paying in to support all the retired Federal Spending, 2012 3.5% 19.2% 13.3% 21.9% 15.3% 6.2% 9.8% 10.7% Veterans benefits and services Defense Medicare Social Security Income support Net interest on debt Medicaid and other health programs Other SOURCE: Office of Management and Budget >> Figure 8.6 Analyze Graphs What is the largest spending category in the budget represented here? Bounce to Activate Gallery 8.3 Federal Spending 361 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="428"> <text><![CDATA[ workers receiving benefits. Although the system has worked well, changes in the U.S. population threaten to undermine it. A key reason for this is the so-called baby boom&ndash;the generation born following World War II. This large demographic group has been the backbone of the workforce. But they did not have children at anywhere near the rate of their parents, and the oldest baby boomers are entering retirement. Millions more will soon follow. As this happens, the ratio of existing workers to retirees will fall. The system may not reach crisis levels for some time. But unless something is done, today&apos;s high school students might receive only limited benefits from Social Security when they retire. At the same time, making changes to the program is politically difficult. Proposals for doing so typically meet significant opposition. Medicare Medicare serves about 47 million people, most of them over 65 years old. The program pays for hospital care and for the costs of physicians and medical services. It also pays healthcare bills for people who suffer from certain disabilities and diseases. Like Social Security, Medicare is funded by taxes withheld from people&apos;s paychecks. Monthly payments paid by people who make certain levels of taxable income and receive Medicare benefits also help pay for the program. Medicare costs have been growing rapidly, partly as a result of expensive technology, but also because people are living longer. The basic problem facing Medicare is the same as the one facing Social Security: a falling ratio of workers to beneficiaries. Medicaid Medicaid benefits low-income families, some people with disabilities, and elderly people in nursing homes. It is the largest source of funds for medical and health-related services for America&apos;s poorest people. The federal government shares the costs of Medicaid with state governments. Other Mandatory Spending Programs Other means-tested entitlements benefit people and families whose incomes fall below a certain level. Requirements vary from program to program. Federal programs include the Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program and the National School Lunch Program. The federal government also pays retirement benefits and insurance for federal workers, as well as veterans&apos; pensions and unemployment insurance. Some members of Congress have pushed for additional government programs related to THE AGING U.S. POPULATION AGE GROUP 0–4 5–9 10 14 15 19 20 24 25 29 30 34 35 39 40 44 45 49 50 54 55 59 60–64 65 69 70 74 75–79 80 84 85 89 90 94 95+ 1980 2035 (PROJECTED) population pyramid looks like a pyramid 1 in 10 Americans aged 65 or older 3.2 workers per Social Security beneficiary 1946 TO 1964 IS KNOWN AS THE BABY BOOM. 10% 10% 5% 5% population pyramid more like a tower 1 in 5 Americans aged 65 or older 2.1 workers per Social Security beneficiary Source: United States Census Bureau, Social Security Administration >> As the nation gets older, the top of the population pyramid gets larger. Analyze Data Compared to 1980, how will the ratio of workers to Social Security recipients have changed by 2035? Bounce to Activate Chart 362 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="429"> <text><![CDATA[ DEFENSE SPENDING AS A PART OF DISCRETIONARY SPENDING 2012* MANDATORY SPENDING AND INTEREST 63.6% DISCRETIONARY SPENDING 36.3% DEFENSE PART OF DISCRETIONARY 19% Source: Office of Management and Budget *Does not total 100% because of rounding >> Figure 8.7 Analyze Graphs About what percentage of discretionary spending went to defense in the budget year shown? healthcare. One reason is that healthcare costs have increased at more than twice the rate of inflation over the last few decades. The average expenditure for healthcare rose from $891 per person in 1960 to $8,680 in 2011. To keep pace, health insurance costs have skyrocketed. As a result, some 48 million Americans had no health insurance in 2011. Over the years, leaders have proposed a range of solutions to these issues&ndash;from single-payer systems organized by the government, to expansion of healthcare tax credits to help make insurance more affordable. Others have insisted we rely on market forces to correct problems. In 2010, President Obama signed a new law called the Affordable Care Act. This law requires Americans who lack certain health insurance coverage to purchase it through competitive private exchanges in their state or through a federal insurance marketplace. The program also seeks to expand the Medicaid program and offers subsidies to help lower-income people afford health insurance. It remains to be seen how this program will affect healthcare costs or access for previously uninsured Americans. DESCRIBE What key demographic challenge faces the largest entitlement programs in the United States? Spending on Discretionary Programs As you have read, the majority of the federal budget is devoted to mandatory spending. The remaining funds available for discretionary spending are divided among a wide variety of programs. Defense Spending Of the categories of discretionary spending, defense spending is the largest. (See Figure 8.7.) Defense spending has dropped somewhat since the end of the Cold War in the late 1900s as a percentage of the total federal budget. As you can see from the graph, defense spending consumes about 19 percent of the federal budget. However, you can also see that defense accounts for more than half of discretionary spending. The Department of Defense spends most of the defense budget. It pays the salaries of all the men and women in the army, navy, air force, and marines, as well as the department&apos;s civilian employees. Defense spending, of course, also buys weapons, missiles, battleships, tanks, airplanes, and other equipment. Other Discretionary Spending Look again at Figure 8.7. After mandatory and defense spending, you may be surprised at how small a 8.3 Federal Spending 363 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="430"> <text><![CDATA[ >> Inspectors prepare to examine shipping containers for terrorist threats. Express Problems Clearly Why is the share of the budget that funds such discretionary activities shrinking? portion of federal spending goes into the category that could be labeled “everything else.” Some of the many programs that this category of federal spending includes are education and training, scientific research, student loans, law enforcement, environmental cleanup, and disaster aid. This part of the federal budget also pays the salaries of the millions of people who work for the civilian branches of the federal government. They include park rangers, FBI agents, file clerks, senators and members of Congress, geologists, CIA agents, Cabinet secretaries, meat inspectors, and many others. Federal Aid to State and Local Governments Some federal tax money finds its way to state and local governments&ndash;much of it from the discretionary portion of the federal budget. In 2011, about $625 billion in federal grants went to the states. This is an average of about $2,000 per person and represents nearly 40 percent of state and local expenditures. As you have read, state and federal governments share the cost of some entitlement programs, including Medicaid and unemployment compensation. They also share funding in other social programs. Additional federal money goes to the states for education, lower-income housing, highway construction, mass transit, healthcare, employment training, and dozens of other programs. Federal grants-in-aid are grants of federal money for certain closely defined purposes. States must use these federal funds only for the purpose specified and obey the federal guidelines for which aid is given. State and local governments rely on federal aid for a variety of needs. But nothing reveals that reliance as vividly as a disaster. For example, after Hurricane Katrina slammed into coastal Louisiana, Mississippi, and Alabama in 2005, those states did not have the resources to deal with the widespread destruction and human misery that the storm left behind. They looked to the federal government for help. Although critics denounced the federal relief agencies for their slow response, Congress appropriated $116 billion to help the states recover from the disaster. A similar scenario occurred in 2012, when Hurricane Sandy caused extensive damage in New York and New Jersey. Again, Congress pledged some $50 billion to aid in recovery. DESCRIBE Describe the key features of the discretionary portion of the federal budget. ASSESSMENT 1. List Name at least three examples of federal discretionary spending. 2. Describe How are the Social Security benefits of today&apos;s retirees funded? 3. Contrast How are mandatory funding and discretionary funding different? 4. Identify Supporting Details What are at least three programs in which state governments and the federal government share funding? 5. Express Problems Clearly Explain why entitlement programs challenge the federal budgeting process. 364 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="431"> <text><![CDATA[ 8.4 You and your family are thinking about colleges. Which one offers the courses you want? How much does it cost? During your research, you find that colleges within your state&apos;s university system are far less expensive than private schools. The reason is that your state government pays part of the cost of running the state colleges. In fact, funds for higher education represent a sizeable part of state expenditures. >> State tax revenues support state parks, which provide recreational and educational opportunities for people all across the country. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video State and Local Taxes and Spending Budgeting at the State Level Because they are democracies, state and local governments manage their money in accordance with priorities set by elected government officials. In this Lesson, you will examine these priorities. For example, you will see that funding education is a priority for state and local legislators. Although school-related tax increases can be painful to the taxpayer, the programs they fund help ensure that students receive a quality education. Operating Budgets Like families and individuals, governments must plan their spending ahead of time. That planning involves drawing up a budget. A budget is an estimate of future revenues and expenses. The federal government has just one budget for planned revenue and expenses. States, however, have two budgets: operating budgets and capital budgets. A state puts together an operating budget to plan for its dayto- day spending needs. Those expenses include salaries of state employees and supplies needed to run the government, such as computers and paper. They also include the maintenance of state facilities such as recreation areas and parks. NGSSS ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1, HE.912.C.2.4, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9, SS.912.FL.5.1 >> Objectives Explain how states use a budget to plan spending. Examine the major categories of state spending. Identify the types and economic importance of state taxes. Describe local government, and the types and economic importance of local taxes. >> Key Terms budget operating budget capital budget balanced budget tax exempt real property personal property tax assessor VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="432"> <text><![CDATA[ Capital Budgets A state also draws up a capital budget to pay for major capital, or investment, spending. If the state builds a new bridge, the money likely comes from this budget. Most of these expenses are met by long-term borrowing or the sale of bonds. The planning process for projects covered by the capital budget may begin years before the project itself begins. Balancing State Budgets In most states, the governor prepares the budget with the help of a budget agency. The legislature then discusses and eventually approves the budget. Unlike the federal government, 48 states require balanced budgets&ndash; budgets in which revenues are equal to spending. These laws, however, apply only to the operating budget, not the capital budget. That makes it easier to balance the overall state budget than to balance the federal budget. ChECK UNdERSTANdINg Would the construction of a new courthouse come out of a state&apos;s operating budget or capital budget? Explain. State Spending Categories Spending policies differ among the 50 states. You are probably most familiar with state spending on education, highways, police protection, and state recreation areas. There are many other categories of state spending, as you will read. Education Every state spends taxpayer money to support at least one public state university. Some, such as Texas and California, have large systems with many campuses throughout the state. In many states, tax dollars also support agricultural and technical colleges, teachers colleges, and two-year community colleges. Spending on higher education is especially important to maintaining economic growth. Public colleges and universities offer an education at much lower tuition than most private institutions. Lower tuition enables large numbers of people to get the training and skills they need to contribute to the economy. State governments also provide financial help to their local governments, which run public elementary, middle, and high schools. The total amount of money spent per student varies among the states. The national average was $10,560 per student per year in 2011. Spending on education is the most significant expenditure in state budgets. Figure 8.8 shows that it represents about 30 percent of state spending nationwide. Public Safety State police are a familiar sight along the nation&apos;s highways. The state police enforce traffic laws and help motorists in emergencies. State police Annual Percent Change in State Operating Budgets, 1980–2014 20 –10 –5 0 5 10 15 1980 1984 1988 1992 1996 2000 2004 2008 2012 Percent Change in Budget Fiscal Year SOURCE: National Association of State Budget Officers >> Changes in state budgets tend to reflect changes in the national economy. Analyze Graphs What can you infer about the national economy in the years 1981–1983 and 2007–2010? 366 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="433"> <text><![CDATA[ State Spending, 2011 29.6% 24.7% 9.4% 16% 3.3% 3% 2.4% 1.1% 2.3% 2.7% 5.5% Education Public welfare Hospitals Health Highways Corrections Natural resources Governmental administration Interest on general debt Insurance trust expenditure Other SOURCE: U.S. Census Bureau >> Figure 8.8 This graph shows combined spending by category for all the states. Analyze Graphs Based on this graph, what would you say is the states&apos; highest priority? Bounce to Activate Gallery also maintain crime labs that can assist local law- enforcement agencies. State governments build and run corrections systems. These institutions house people convicted of state crimes. Transportation Building and maintaining highway systems is another major state expense. State crews resurface roads and repair bridges. Some money for roads comes from the federal government. In turn, states contribute money to federal and interstate highway systems. States pay at least some of the costs of other kinds of transportation facilities, such as waterways and airports. Money for such projects may also comes from federal and local government budgets. Health and Welfare States look after the health and welfare of the public in various ways. Their public health policies promote health and prevent the spread of diseases. State funds support some public hospitals and clinics. State government regulations promote health and prevent disease by protecting water supplies against pollution. As you have read, states also help pay for many of the federal programs that assist individuals, such as unemployment compensation benefits. During a recession, these benefits can help boost the economy. Arts and Recreation If you&apos;ve hiked in a state forest or picnicked in a state park, you&apos;ve enjoyed another benefit of state tax dollars. Nature reserves and parks preserve scenic and historic places for people to visit and enjoy. States also run museums and help fund music and art programs. Administration Besides providing services, state governments need to spend money just to keep running. Like the federal government, state governments have an executive branch (the governor&apos;s office), a legislative branch, and a court system. State tax revenues pay the salaries of all these and other state workers, including judges, maintenance crews in state parks, the governor, and professors in state universities. IDENTIFY CENTRAL IDEAS Explain how state universities contribute to economic growth. Revenue for State Budgets For every dollar a state spends, it must take in a dollar in revenue. Otherwise, it cannot maintain a balanced budget. The 50 states took in almost $2.3 trillion from various sources in 2011. Where does this money come from? The circle graph in Figure 8.9 shows the major sources of state revenue. The largest portion is intergovernmental revenue, mostly money 8.4 State and Local Taxes and Spending 367 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="434"> <text><![CDATA[ from the federal government. Income from insurance trusts&ndash;used to pay pension and other benefits&ndash;is another key revenue source. But as you can see, taxes of various sorts make up an important share of state revenues. Just as the United States Constitution limits the federal government&apos;s power to tax, it also puts limits on the states. Because trade and commerce are considered national enterprises, states cannot tax imports or exports. They also cannot tax goods sent between states. Nonprofit organizations, including religious groups and charities, are usually tax exempt; that is, they are not subject to taxes. Sales and Excise Taxes Figure 8.9 shows that sales taxes are a main source of revenue, and the largest tax in terms of revenue, for state governments. A sales tax is a tax on goods and services. The tax&ndash;a percentage of the purchase price&ndash;is added on at the cash register and paid by the purchaser. All but a few of the 50 states collect sales taxes. Their sales tax rates range from 2.9 to 7.5 percent. Some local governments have their own, additional sales tax. In every state, some categories of products are exempt from sales tax. For example, many states do not charge sales tax on basic needs such as food and clothing. Exemption of everyday items that most people buy in similar quantities helps make sales taxes less regressive. Even states without a sales tax impose excise taxes that apply to specific products and activities. Some are sin taxes&ndash;taxes that are intended to discourage harmful behavior&ndash;on products like alcoholic beverages and tobacco. Other taxes apply to hotel and motel rooms, automobiles, rental cars, and insurance policies. Many states also tax gasoline. This state gasoline tax is in addition to the federal tax. Individual Income Tax Individual income taxes are another large contributor to many states&apos; budgets. People pay this state income tax in addition to the federal income tax. Figure 8.9 shows that state individual income taxes contribute over 11 percent of state revenue. As such, they have a substantial impact on the economy of the state. Some states tax incomes at a flat rate&ndash;that is, as a proportional tax, with the same rate applied to all income levels. Others use a progressive tax, either by creating their own progressive rate structure or by charging taxpayers a given percentage of their federal income tax. A handful of states have no state income tax. A couple tax only interest and dividends from investments, not wages and salaries. Corporate Income Tax Most states collect income taxes from corporations that do business in the state. Some states levy taxes on business profits at a fixed, flat rate. A few charge progressive rates&ndash;higher tax rates for businesses with higher profits. State Revenue, 2011 26.2% 16.3% 11.5% 8% 10.3%1.8% 25.9% Insurance trust revenue Intergovernmental revenue Sales tax Individual income tax Corporate income tax Current charges (such as user fees for parks, ports) Other SOURCE: U.S. Census Bureau >> Figure 8.9 This graph shows the ways that the states, collectively, get their revenues. Analyze Graphs What is the most significant source of tax revenue at the state level? 368 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="435"> <text><![CDATA[ State Individual Income Taxes, 2013 WA MT ID OR CA NV UT* AZ NM TX CO* WY ND SD NE KS MN IA MO OK AR LA ALMS GA FL SC NC VA KY TN WI IL* OH MI* PA* WV NY IN* ME NH VT MA* NJ RI DC MD CT DE AK HI KEY Top state income tax rate Over 10% 7–9.9% 4–6.9% 1–3.9% State income tax on dividends and interest income only No state income tax *State with a flat tax rate Source: Federation of Tax Administrators >> State individual income tax rates vary greatly. Some states have no income tax. Analyze Maps In which range does the largest number of states set their top individual income tax rate? As you have seen in Figure 8.9, corporate income taxes make up only a small portion of state revenues&ndash;about 2 percent. Nevertheless, the level of corporate income taxes can exert a strong influence on a state&apos;s economy. Low corporate taxes, along with a well-educated workforce and efficient public services, can make it easier to attract entrepreneurs and new businesses to a state. Politicians keep this fact in mind when they determine their state&apos;s taxing policies. Other State Taxes Besides the corporate income tax, businesses pay a variety of other state taxes and fees. Do you want to be a hairdresser, a carpenter, or a building contractor? If so, you will have to pay a licensing fee. A licensing fee is a kind of tax that people pay to carry on different kinds of business within a state. Some states charge a transfer tax when documents such as stock certificates are transferred and recorded. Other states tax the value of the stock shares that corporations issue. As you read earlier, the federal government taxes the estate of a person who has died. Some states, in turn, charge an inheritance tax on the value of the property that goes to each heir. Some states also tax property. That includes real estate, or real property&ndash;land and any permanent structures on the land to which a person has legal title. It also includes personal property&ndash;movable possessions or assets&ndash;such as jewelry, furniture, and boats. Some states even tax property that is intangible (meaning “not able to be touched”), such as bank accounts, stocks, and bonds. Today, however, most property taxes, especially on real estate, are levied by local governments. RECALL What kind of tax raises the price of cigarettes and no other goods or services? Local Government Spending and Revenue Your local government plays a part in many aspects of everyday life, including your town&apos;s public schools. Like state governments, local governments draw up a budget to organize their spending. The revenue they collect through taxes allows them to hire police and firefighters. Tax revenue also enables local governments to build roads; operate libraries, hospitals, and jails; and pay teachers. Even though this is the level of government closest to you, it may be the one you know the least about. Forms of Local Government You probably think of “local government” as a town or city. There are other types as well, including townships, counties, 8.4 State and Local Taxes and Spending 369 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="436"> <text><![CDATA[ and special districts such as school districts. Today, there are more than 90,000 local government units in the United States. Together they collect around $600 billion in tax revenues. The Jobs of Local Government Local governments carry major responsibilities in many areas, such as public school systems, law enforcement (local police, county sheriff&apos;s departments, park police), and fire protection. They manage public facilities (libraries, airports, public hospitals) and parks and recreational facilities (beaches, swimming pools, zoos). They monitor public health (restaurant inspection, water treatment, sewer systems), public transportation, elections (voter registration, ballot preparation, election supervision, vote counting), record keeping (birth/death certificates, wills, marriage licenses), and social services (food stamps, child care, welfare). From this listing of tasks, you can see that local governments touch our lives every day. Many of the tasks are reflected in Figure 8.10. In some towns and cities, separate commissions or private corporations carry out some of these responsibilities. Fulfilling local government&apos;s responsibilities is expensive. Some cities have found that their debts and other financial obligations are out of control. Stockton, California, filed for bankruptcy in 2012. Detroit, Michigan, did the same thing in 2013. In Detroit&apos;s case, a key cause of financial difficulties was the flight of its citizens to the suburbs. As a result, the local government lost an enormous amount of revenue, especially from property taxes. Property Tax The property tax is the most significant source of tax revenue for local governments. Figure 8.11 shows that this tax contributes about a quarter of all local government revenues. Property taxes are levied on property owners in local communities to offset the expense of services such as street construction and maintenance. An official called a tax assessor determines the value of the property. Property taxes are usually figured as a fixed dollar amount per $1,000 of the assessed value. They are a main source of funding for public schools. Other Local Taxes Local taxes are similar to the types of taxes imposed by the states. Besides property taxes, local governments levy sales, excise, and income taxes. Some of these taxes affect not only residents of a community but also visitors. In fact, many are designed specifically to raise revenue from nonresidents. In this way, tourists and others from outside the local area help boost local economies. Local Spending, 2011 3.2% 36.3% 2.5% 5.1% 2.6% 2.1% 2.7% 4.5% 4.4% 3.7% 2.5% 10.1% 11.1% 3.7% 5.3% Education Public welfare Hospitals Health Highways Police protection Fire protection Parks and recreation Housing and community development Sewerage Government administration Interest on general debt Utilities Insurance trust expenditure Other SOURCE: U.S. Census Bureau >> Figure 8.10 Local governments supply a variety of services to many different people. Analyze Graphs Based on this graph, what do you think is the largest priority of local governments? 370 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="437"> <text><![CDATA[ Local Revenue, 2011 33.2% 25.7% 5.6% 14.8% 1.8% 4.8% 4.4% 8% 1.5% Intergovernmental revenue Property tax Sales and excise tax Individual income tax Other taxes Current charges (such as parking, user fees) Miscellaneous general revenue Utility revenue Insurance trust revenue SOURCE: U.S. Census Bureau >> Figure 8.11 Like state governments, local governments get revenue from many sources. Analyze Graphs What is a key similarity between local government revenue and state government revenue shown in Fig. 8.9? Bounce to Activate Chart Suppose you&apos;ve gone on a school trip to New York City. The room rate for your hotel is $200 a night. When you see the bill in the morning, however, it&apos;s $233! Three different taxes have been added&ndash;a 4.0 percent state sales tax, a 4.5 percent city sales tax, and a 5.875 percent hotel room occupancy tax. In addition, the city charges a Metropolitan Commuter Transportation District surcharge of 0.375 percent, for a total tax of 14.75 percent. The state and city also collect room fees totaling $3.50. Many other cities have taxes aimed at tourists and business travelers. Besides hotel taxes, they include sales taxes on rental cars, airport taxes, and taxes on movie or theater tickets. A few thousand cities and other types of local governments assess a tax on individual income. It takes the form of a payroll tax. Usually the rate is low, but this tax can still produce a significant amount of revenue. Some cities have debated the idea of instituting a congestion tax on vehicles. The local government would charge drivers a fee for entering a congested, or overcrowded, area of the city between certain hours. Supporters of a congestion tax say many commuters would opt to use mass transit instead of automobiles. This would not only help clear clogged streets, but would also decrease the emission of gases that contribute to local air pollution into the atmosphere. Critics counter that the city&apos;s businesses would be hurt, as many people would decide to stay out of the downtown area&ndash;and spend their money elsewhere. RECALL What type of local tax is a main source of funding for public schools? ASSESSMENT 1. Make Predictions Which budget&ndash;capital or operating&ndash;do you think a state would draw from to fund the cleanup after a natural disaster? Why? 2. Evaluate Arguments Is it fair that nonprofit organizations are exempt from taxes? Why or why not? 3. Make Generalizations Do states generally help local governments carry out their responsibilities? 4. Generate Explanations Why might local governments design taxes to raise revenue from nonresidents? 5. Contrast In what ways do local government taxes differ from state taxes? 8.4 State and Local Taxes and Spending 371 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="438"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 8 Quick Study Guide LESSON SUMMARIES Use these lesson summaries, and the longer versions available online, to review the key ideas for each lesson in this topic. Lesson 1: Understanding Taxes LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, SS.912.E.2.8 The U.S. Constitution gives the government the power to impose taxes, which it needs to fund its activities. Taxes with rates that rise with income are progressive; taxes with the same rate for all incomes are proportional; and taxes with rates that rise as income falls are regressive. Different taxes have different bases, such as individual income taxes, corporate income taxes, or property taxes. Tax burdens can affect economic decisions. Taxes should be simple, efficient, predictable, and fair. Lesson 2: Federal Taxes SS.912.E.2.8 Individual income taxes are the federal government&apos;s main source of revenue. Income taxes are progressive and are collected through withholding from pay. Other taxes withheld from pay include Social Security taxes, Medicare taxes, and unemployment taxes. Corporations also must pay a progressive income tax. Other federal taxes include excise taxes, or taxes on the value of a good; estate taxes due when people inherit more than $5.25 million; gift taxes on gifts of more than $14,000; and tariffs on imported goods. Lesson 3: Federal Spending SS.912.E.2.9, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 Federal spending falls into two main categories. Mandatory spending is spending required by law. All other spending is discretionary, or optional, spending. The largest type of mandatory spending is for entitlements, payments that people are entitled to by law, such as Social Security, Medicare, and Medicaid. The largest area of discretionary spending is for defense. Discretionary spending also pays for education, research, law enforcement, disaster aid, and many other government programs. Federal aid to state and local governments is another type of discretionary spending. Lesson 4: State and Local Taxes and Spending ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1, HE.912.C.2.4 States prepare budgets to match their spending to their revenue. Unlike the federal government, most states require balanced budgets. State spending pays for education, public safety, highways and other transportation, health and antipoverty programs, and arts and recreation. Almost all states collect sales and excise taxes. Most states collect individual and corporate income taxes. Some states also tax property. Local governments also tax and spend. Local governments include city and county governments and school districts. Most collect property taxes. Some collect income or sales taxes. They use these to pay for school systems, police forces, and such services as parks and libraries. AUDIO READING GAMES Go ONLINE for lesson summaries Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="439"> <text><![CDATA[ VISUAL REVIEW Use these graphics to review some of the key terms and ideas from this topic. Three Types of Tax Structures TYPE OF TAX PROGRESSIVE PROPORTIONAL REGRESSIVE DESCRIPTION A larger percentage of income is taken in taxes as income increases. A constant percentage of income is taken in taxes as income increases. A smaller percentage of income is taken in taxes as income increases. EXAMPLE Income tax Some state taxes Sales tax RON’S TAXES ON A $50,000 INCOME $5,000 or 10 percent of income $7,5000, or 15 percent of income $2,000, or 5 percent of total purchases of $40,000; tax bill is 4 percent of income MARY’S TAXES ON A $150,000 INCOME $45,000, or 30 percent of income $22,500 or 15 percent of income $3,000, or 5 percent of total purchases of $60,000; tax bill is 2 percent of income Two Types of Government Spending MANDATORY • Interest on national debt • Medicare • Medicaid • Social Security DISCRETIONARY • Defense • Education • Law enforcement • Environmental cleanup State Spending Categories Education Public Safety Transportation Health and Welfare Arts and Recreation Administration Spending on education is needed for economic growth. For example, state police enforce laws. States build and maintain highways, waterways, and airports. States fund health and safety inspections and some healthcare. States fund parks, museums and art programs. State governments spend money to maintain their own operations. 373]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="440"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 8 Assessment KEY TERMS AND IDEAS SS.912.E.2.8 1. What is the main source of revenue for government? 2. Explain how progressive taxes, proportional taxes, and regressive taxes differ. 3. What are the tax bases for individual income taxes and property taxes? 4. Contrast direct taxes with indirect taxes. 5. How are tax deductions different from tax credits? 6. What is the difference between mandatory spending and discretionary spending? 7. How is a capital budget different from an operating budget? 8. What is the role of a tax assessor? CRITICAL THINKING LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10, HE.912.C.2.4, SS.912.E.2.8 9. Apply Concepts Why is it important for a tax system to be efficient? 10. Categorize If a person making $200,000 a year pays a tax bill of $10,000 and a person making $20,000 pays a tax bill of $2,000, is the tax progressive, regressive, or proportional? Explain. 11. Apply Concepts Suppose that a government decided to collect all of its revenue through a tax on tap water. Explain why this tax would or would not be fair. 12. Hypothesize Why might a government choose to levy an indirect tax rather than a direct tax? 13. Integrate Information What is another way in which governments might accomplish the same policy goals that they accomplish through tax incentives? 14. Hypothesize Why do you think that the government takes taxes out of people&apos;s paychecks instead of waiting until they are due to collect them? 15. Infer How might a mandatory spending program be changed into a discretionary spending program? 16. Synthesize The graph below shows trends in federal spending since 1955. Explain the effect of mandatory spending on the government&apos;s ability to reallocate spending. Discretionary and Mandatory Spending, 1962–2018* Percentage of Federal Budget 0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 Years 1955 1975 1995 2015 Discretionary Spending Mandatory Spending and Net Interest *Data from 2013–2018 is an estimate. SOURCE: Office of Management and Budget 17. Apply Concepts The U.S. Constitution mandates that the government provide for national defense. Why, then, is defense spending classified as discretionary? 18. Compare and Contrast How are the main sources of local revenue similar to and different from the main sources of state revenue? 19. Summarize How does state government influence health promotion and disease prevention? 20. Compare and Contrast What are the similarities and differences between state and local spending? 21. Writing Activity In this topic, you learned how governments collect and spend money. Do you believe that governments need to raise more taxes and spend more on programs? Do you believe that government taxes and spending should be cut? Or do you believe the level of taxing and spending are about right? Write a short persuasive essay arguing your opinion on these questions. Be sure to support your opinion with evidence and examples. 374 TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="441"> <text><![CDATA[ DOCUMENT-BASED QUESTIONS LAFS.1112.RH.3.7, SS.912.E.2.9 Almost two-thirds of federal expenditures are entitlements such as Social Security, Medicare, and Medicaid. As these social welfare programs continue to grow, people debate about whether to limit their benefits in order to reduce the federal budget deficit. DOCUMENT A The Executive Vice President of Government Affairs for the U.S. Chamber of Commerce outlines some of the major issues surrounding entitlement programs. Today I want to discuss a challenge that impacts every single citizen, the health of our economy, and our country&apos;s ability to maintain its leadership role in the world. That challenge is the urgent need to reform and modernize our entitlement programs&ndash; primarily Social Security, Medicare, and Medicaid. These are safety net programs that we have enacted as a compassionate society to care for the elderly in retirement, for people with disabilities, and for those who cannot afford health insurance on their own. . . . We need to fix these programs because otherwise they will consume every dollar the government collects. There will be no money left over to improve our schools, defend our country from its enemies, clean our environment, or repair our roads and bridges. . . . Why do these programs need fixing in the first place? Because Americans are thankfully living much longer than they used to, which means they are drawing more total benefits over their lifetimes than the systems were ever designed to pay for. . . . And because Americans are having fewer children, which means relatively speaking, there are fewer workers paying into the system compared with the number of beneficiaries. &ndash;R. Bruce Josten, “10 Truths About America&apos;s Entitlement Programs,” June 8, 2013 DOCUMENT B DOCUMENT C Economist Henry J. Aaron explains his view of the importance of Social Security. . . . Social Security is, and must remain, the bedrock of retirement income security. There is simply no alternative. Private income sources cannot do what social insurance does&ndash;only social insurance provides absolute inflation protection, spreads risks over generations and across the whole population, provides wage insurance, and is immune to fluctuations in asset values. Yes, changes in economic and demographic conditions can force changes in social insurance. But those changes are gradual, not abrupt. . . . The best way of saving money and maintaining replacement rates, in my view, would be measures to encourage workers able work to remain economically active until later ages than is now customary. &ndash;Henry J. Aaron, “Health Care, Entitlements, and the Federal Budget,” June 15, 2009 22. What is one reason the author of Document A wants to cut entitlement benefits? A. They do not provide the help they were meant to provide. B. They use up funds that could be used to help the elderly. C. They eat up too large a share of the federal budget. D. They are not going to the people who most need them. 23. What problem does Document B address? A. Extending insurance coverage to everyone B. Doctors&apos; tendency to rush through appointments C. The need to shorten hospital stays D. The expense of healthcare coverage 24. According to Document C, why would it be wrong to cut Social Security? A. It provides income security to beneficiaries. B. It allows people to retire early, opening up new jobs. C. It fluctuates easily when property values change. D. It is immune to changes in the economy and population. 25. Writing Task Write a paragraph describing the costs and benefits of cutting entitlements in order to balance the federal budget. In your response, integrate the arguments presented in the three sources above, as well as any relevant information in the text (including visual information such as charts and graphs.) ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE to practice Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="442"> <text><![CDATA[ VIDEO AUDIO ETEXT ACTIVITY WRITING GAMES PDF ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS [ ESSENTIAL QUESTION ] What is the proper role of government in the economy? 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="443"> <text><![CDATA[ Next Generation Sunshine State Standards SS.912.E.1.10, SS.912.E.1.11, SS.912.E.2.9, SS.912.E.3.6, ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1, LAFS.1112.RH.1.3, LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, LAFS.1112.RH.3.7, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.SL.1.2, LAFS.1112.SL.1.3, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 Enduring Understandings &bull; The government uses fiscal policy to promote full employment and maintain stable prices. &bull; Demand-side economists believe that government spending will improve the economy during times of economic weakness. Supply- side economists believe instead in using tax cuts to boost the economy. &bull; Deficits and the national debt can cause problems for a nation. &bull; The Federal Reserve uses monetary policy tools to regulate the nation&apos;s money supply. &bull; Monetary policy can lessen the frequency and amplitude of the fluctuations in the economy if it is implemented at the right time. >> The proposed federal budget is published every year and printed in book-like format. Learn more about John Maynard Keynes, an economist whose work has shaped economic policies since the Great Depression. Bounce to Activate My Story Video 377 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="444"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 9 Overview In this topic, you will learn about how the government collects and spends money and how it makes efforts to manipulate the money supply. Look at the lesson outline and explore the photographs. As you study this topic, you&apos;ll complete the quest team project. LESSON OUTLINE 9.1 The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy SS.912.E.1.10, ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1 9.2 Fiscal Policy Options SS.912.E.1.10 9.3 The National Debt and Deficits SS.912.E.2.9, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 9.4 Monetary Policy Options SS.912.E.1.11, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 9.5 The Effects of Monetary Policy SS.912.E.1.11, SS.912.E.3.6 MONETARY POLICY The Federal Reserve System carries out monetary policy. Monetary policy impacts interest rates consumers pay. Economist Milton Friedman helped shape our understanding of monetary policy. FISCAL POLICY During the Great Depression, fiscal policy called for spending on employment programs. The American people vigorously debate the nation&apos;s fiscal policy. John Maynard Keynes urged use of fiscal policy to aid the economy. 378 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="445"> <text><![CDATA[ Recessions: 1950–Present 1950 1953–1954 1955 1957–1958 This recession hit the U.S. auto industry hard. Here unemployed workers in Detroit line up to obtain financial assistance. 1960 1960–1961 1965 1970 1969–1970 1973–1975 Public protests erupted during a serious recession that was triggered by disruption of world oil supplies. 1975 1980 1980 1981–1982 1985 1990 1990–1991 1995 2000 2001 2007–2009 Falling U.S. housing prices caused huge losses for many financial firms. 2005 2010 2015 SOURCE: National Bureau of Economic Research TEAM PROJECT Document-Based Question: How well did the federal government respond to the Great Recession? What tools did the federal government use to address the Great Recession, and how effective were they? In this quest, you will assess the federal government’s actions. STEP 1 List your questions about the economic crisis of 2007–2009 and the government’s response to it. STEP 2 Examine the documents relating to the Great Recession. Note discrepancies among the sources. STEP 3 Synthesize your ideas. Then write a clear, coherent essay evaluating whether the government used the right tools to respond to the Great Recession. STEP 4 Revise your writing. Did you cite specific evidence from the documents to support your argument? Share your finished work with the class. NGSSS LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, LAFS.1112.RH.3.7, LAFS.1112.SL.1.2 Go ONLINE for complete Quest materials VIDEO ETEXT WRITING RUBRIC PDF ASSESSMENT Savvas.com/FloridaSS]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="446"> <text><![CDATA[ 9.1 Does your family have a household budget? Have you ever tried to budget your own money? Either way, you know that you have to take a close look at how much money you have coming in and how much you have to spend. Your goal is to get those two figures in line. But it&apos;s not easy. Sometimes it requires giving something up. Sometimes&ndash;although you try to avoid it&ndash;it may even require borrowing money. No matter what, making a budget takes time. Somebody has to sit down with a calculator, a stack of bills, a checkbook, and a calendar to figure it all out. >> Congressional staff members receive massive copies of the proposed 2012 budget. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS SS.912.E.1.10, ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1 >> Objectives Describe how the federal budget is created. Analyze the impact of expansionary and contractionary fiscal policy on the economy. Identify the limits of fiscal policy. >> Key Terms fiscal policy federal budget fiscal year appropriations bill expansionary policy contractionary policy The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy Now, imagine how much more effort it would take if your expenses were $3.5 trillion per year. Suppose everyone in the house had to agree on every single item in the budget, and you had to send it to somebody else for final approval. Now you have an idea what the U.S. federal government must do before it can spend your tax money. Unlike a family, the federal government is not just interested in making income meet expenses. As you will see, the government may also use its taxing and spending policies to speed up economic growth&ndash;or even to slow it down. Fiscal Policy The federal government takes in and spends huge amounts of money. In fact, it spends an average of about $10 billion every day. This tremendous flow of cash into and out of the economy has a large impact on aggregate supply and aggregate demand. The government&apos;s taxing and spending decisions are shaped both by budgetary needs and by fiscal policy. Fiscal policy is the VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="447"> <text><![CDATA[ use of government spending and revenue collection to influence the economy. Fiscal policy is a tool used to expand or to slow economic growth, to achieve full employment, and to maintain price stability. The federal government makes key fiscal policy decisions&ndash;how much to spend and how much to tax&ndash;each year when it creates the federal budget. Federal Budget Basics The federal budget is a written document estimating the federal government&apos;s revenue and authorizing its spending for the coming year. Like any organization&apos;s budget, it lists expected income and shows exactly how the money will be spent. In effect, the budget reflects the nation&apos;s priorities&ndash;the tasks and goals it finds most pressing and worthy of financial support. Figure 9.1 helps illustrate this point by showing how the federal budget in one year was distributed among broad spending categories. It also shows how spending has changed over time. The federal government prepares a new budget for each fiscal year. A fiscal year is a 12-month period used for budgeting purposes. It is not necessarily the same as the January-to-December calendar year. The federal government uses a fiscal year that runs from October 1 through September 30. Step 1: Agencies Submit Spending Proposals The federal budget takes about 18 months to prepare. During this time, citizens, Congress, and the President debate the government&apos;s spending priorities. In fact, the budget reflects the nation&apos;s commitment to different priorities. There are several basic steps in the federal budget process. These steps are outlined in Figure 9.2. The federal budget must fund many offices and agencies in the federal government, and Congress cannot know all of their needs. So, before the budget is put together, each federal agency writes a detailed estimate of how much it expects to spend in the coming fiscal year. These spending proposals are sent to a special unit of the executive branch, the Office of Management and Budget (OMB). Created in 1970, the OMB is part of the Executive Office of the President. As its name suggests, the OMB is responsible for managing the federal government&apos;s budget. Its most important job is to prepare that budget. Step 2: Executive Branch Draws Up a Budget The OMB reviews the federal agencies&apos; spending proposals. Representatives from the agencies may explain their spending proposals to the OMB and try to persuade the OMB to give them as much money as they have requested. Usually, the OMB suggests giving each agency less than it requests. $ FEDERAL SPENDING IN THE UNITED STATES $ SPENDING I N T H E UNITED STATES Federal Outlays (in billions) 0 $500 $1,000 $1,500 $2,000 $2,500 $3,000 $3,500 $4,000 Fiscal Year 1970 1975 1980 1985 1990 1995 2000 2005 2010 2012 FEDERAL SPENDING IN BILLIONS HUMAN RESOURCES $2,346.6 Example: Social Security, Medicare DEFENSE $677.9 Example: weapons, paying soldiers NET INTEREST $220.4 Annual cost of borrowing PHYSICAL RESOURCES $215.5 Example: energy, environmental protection OTHER $178.4 Example: diplomacy, space program >> Figure 9.1 Federal spending has risen sharply in recent decades. Analyze Graphs Based on this data, which category is most likely responsible for the steep growth in spending? Explain your answer. 9.1 The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy 381 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="448"> <text><![CDATA[ The OMB then works with the President&apos;s staff to combine all of the individual agency budgets into a single budget document. This document reveals the President&apos;s overall spending plan for the coming fiscal year. The President presents the budget to Congress in January or February. Step 3: Congress Debates The President&apos;s budget is only a starting point. The number of changes Congress makes to the President&apos;s budget depends on the relationship between the President and Congress. Congress carefully considers, debates, and modifies the President&apos;s proposed budget. For help, members of Congress rely on the assistance of the Congressional Budget Office (CBO). Created in 1974, the CBO gives Congress independent economic data to help with its decisions. Much of the work done by Congress is done in small committees. Working at the same time, committees in the House of Representatives and the Senate analyze the budget and hold hearings at which agency officials and others can speak out about the budget. The House Budget Committee and Senate Budget Committee combine their work to propose one initial budget resolution, which must be adopted by May 15, before the beginning of the fiscal year. This resolution is not intended to be final. It gives initial estimates for revenue and spending to guide the legislators as they continue working on the budget. Then, in early September, the budget committees propose a second budget resolution that sets binding spending limits. Congress must pass this resolution by September 15, after which Congress cannot pass any new bills that would spend more money than the budget resolution allows. Finally, the Appropriations Committee of each house submits bills to authorize specific spending, based on the decisions Congress has made. By this time, the new fiscal year is about to start, and Congress faces pressure to get these appropriations bills adopted and submitted to the President before the previous year&apos;s funding ends on September 30. If Congress cannot finish in time, it must pass short-term emergency spending legislation known as “stopgap funding” to keep the government running. If Congress and the President cannot even agree on temporary funding, the government “shuts down,” and all but the most essential federal offices close. Step 4: Back to the White House Once Congress approves the appropriations bills, they are sent to the President, who can sign the bills into law. If the President vetoes any of the bills, Congress has two options. It can vote to override the President&apos;s veto&ndash;a difficult task, because an override requires the votes of two thirds of each chamber. More often, Congress works with the President to write an CREATING FEDERAL BUDGET Federal agencies send requests for funding to Office of Management and Budget (OMB). The OMB works with the President to create a budget, which the President then sends to Congress. Congress debates and makes changes to the budget and returns it to the President. President signs budget into law. OR President vetoes the budget. Congress overrides the President’s veto by a 2/3 majority. OR Congress and the President compromise and agree on a new budget. >> Figure 9.2 The basic steps in the establishment of a federal budget are shown here. Analyze Information Why do you think compromise is such an important part of the budget process? Bounce to Activate Chart 382 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="449"> <text><![CDATA[ TOOLBOX OF FISCAL POLICY INCREASE GOVERNMENT SPENDING CUT TAXES + INCREASE/DEMAND, PRICES, AND OUTPUT FEDERAL GOVERNMENT - DECREASE/DEMAND, PRICES, AND OUTPUT INCREASE TAXES DECREASE GOVERNMENT SPENDING>> Figure 9.3 When implementing fiscal policy, government has several tools at its disposal. Analyze Information If government leaders wanted to spur economic activity, which tools would they select? Explain. appropriations bill on which both sides can agree. Once that is completed, the President signs the new budget into law. LIST What two offices provide information that helps the President and Congress make budget decisions? How Fiscal Policy Decisions Impact the Economy Government officials who take part in the budget process debate how much should be spent on specific programs such as defense or education. They also consider how much should be spent in all. These decisions do not affect only the specific programs in the budget&ndash;they affect the entire economy. Government spending increases or decreases can affect the nation&apos;s total economic output. Similarly, the raising or lowering of taxes may help reduce or boost output. (See Figure 9.3.) Fiscal policy that tries to increase output is known as expansionary policy. Fiscal policy intended to decrease output is called contractionary policy. By carefully choosing to follow expansionary or contractionary fiscal policy&ndash; and considering the costs of each&ndash;the federal government tries to make the economy grow as smoothly and sustainably as possible. Expansionary Fiscal Policy Governments use an expansionary fiscal policy to raise the level of output in the economy. That is, they use expansionary policy to encourage growth, either to try to prevent a recession or to move the economy out of a recession. Recall that a recession is the part of the business cycle that occurs when output declines for at least two quarters, or three-month periods, in a row. Expansionary fiscal policy involves increasing government spending, cutting taxes, or both. If the federal government increases its spending, or buys more goods and services, it triggers a chain of events that raises output and creates jobs. Government spending increases aggregate demand, which causes prices to rise, as shown in Figure 9.4. According to the law of supply, higher prices encourage suppliers of goods and services to produce more. To do this, firms will hire more workers. In short, an increase in demand should lead to lower unemployment and to an increase in output. The economy will expand. Tax cuts can work in a similar way to encourage economic expansion. If the federal government cuts taxes, individuals keep more of their income, and 9.1 The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy 383 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="450"> <text><![CDATA[ businesses keep more of their profits. Consumers have more money to spend on goods and services, and firms have more money to spend on land, labor, and capital. If consumers and businesses spend the money they gain through tax cuts, this spending will increase demand, prices, and output. The U.S. government&apos;s response to the recession that began after the 2008 financial crisis illustrates expansionary fiscal policy. The American Recovery and Reinvestment Act both increased government spending and cut taxes. The act provided funding for road construction and repair, for scientific research, and for many other projects. It also cut payroll taxes, provided a tax credit for new home buyers, and offered other tax breaks. The goal was to increase demand, lower unemployment, and spur economic output. Contractionary Fiscal Policy Under some circumstances, the government may employ a contractionary fiscal policy. Contractionary fiscal policy tries to decrease aggregate demand and, by decreasing demand, to reduce the growth of economic output. If contractionary fiscal policy is strong enough, it may slow the growth of output to zero or even lead to a fall in gross domestic product (GDP). (See Figure 9.5.) Why would the government try to decrease economic output? The government sometimes tries to slow down the economy to fight inflation, a rapid increase in prices. When demand exceeds supply, producers respond by raising output and raising prices. If producers cannot expand production enough, they will raise their prices, which can lead to high inflation. Left unchecked, inflation cuts into consumers&apos; purchasing power and discourages economic growth and stability. Contractionary fiscal policy aimed at slowing the growth of total output generally involves two alternatives. The Federal government can decrease spending or raise taxes&ndash;or both. If the federal government spends less, or buys fewer goods and services, it triggers a chain of events that may lead to slower GDP growth. As Figure 9.6 indicates, government spending represents a significant share of GDP. A decrease in government spending leads to a decrease in aggregate demand, because the government is buying less than before. Decreased demand tends to lower prices. According to the law of supply, lower prices encourage suppliers to cut their production and possibly lay off workers. Lower production lowers the growth rate of the economy and may even reduce GDP. This chain of events is the exact opposite of what happens when the government increases spending. The government uses the same tools to try to influence the economy in both cases, but in different ways and with very different goals. When the federal government raises taxes, individuals have less money to spend on goods and Effects of Expansionary Fiscal Policy Price level Low prices High prices Higher output, higher prices Aggregate supply Lower output, lower prices Aggregate demand with higher government spending Original aggregate demand Total output in the economy Low output High output >> Figure 9.4 The goal of expansionary fiscal policy is to achieve higher aggregate demand&ndash;and higher output and prices. Analyze Graphs In this graph, what causes the effect of increased demand, output, and prices? Bounce to Activate Chart 384 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="451"> <text><![CDATA[ EFFECTS OF A CONTRACTIONARY FISCAL POLICY To contract the economy, government buys fewer goods and services. Companies that sell goods and services to the government have lower profits and less money available to pay workers.Workers and investors have less money to spend on goods and services. Decreased demand tends to lead to lower prices, forcing suppliers to cut production and lay off workers. The growth rate of the economy slows. >> Figure 9.5 Infer What can you infer about the amount of goods and services purchased by government from outside companies? services or to save for the future. Firms keep less of their profits and have less money to invest in land, labor, and capital. As a result of these decreases in demand, prices tend to fall. Producers of goods and suppliers of services tend to cut production. This slows the growth of GDP. IdENTIfy CENTRAL IdEAS What are the two main tools that government uses to implement fiscal policy? The Limits and Costs of Fiscal Policy Fiscal policy can be a powerful tool that can keep the economy in balance, but it can also be clumsy and difficult to put into practice. In addition, fiscal policy decisions come at a cost. The Reality of Entitlements Increasing or decreasing federal spending is not an easy task. Many spending categories in the federal budget are entitlements that are fixed by law. Over half the federal budget is set aside for programs such as Medicaid, Social Security, and veterans&apos; benefits before Congress even begins the budget process. Government cannot change spending for entitlements under current law. Also, it must continue to pay interest on the large debt the nation has incurred. As a result, significant change in federal spending generally must come from the smaller discretionary spending part of the federal budget. This gives government little fiscal leeway. Knowing the Future Governments use fiscal policy to prevent big changes in the level of GDP. Despite the statistics, however, it is difficult to know the current state of the economy. No one can know for sure how quickly the business cycle will move from one stage to the next, nor can anyone identify exactly where in the cycle the economy is at any particular time. Predicting future economic performance is even more difficult. If economists forecast well, then the lag would not matter. They could tell Congress in advance what the appropriate fiscal policy is. But economists do not forecast well. Most economists, for example, badly under predicted both the rise in unemployment in 1981 and the strength of the recovery that began in late 1982. Absent accurate forecasts, attempts to use discretionary fiscal 9.1 The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy 385 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="452"> <text><![CDATA[ policy to counteract business cycle fluctuations are as likely to do harm as good. &ndash;David N. Weil, Professor of Economics at Brown University Delayed Results Although changes in fiscal policy affect the economy, changes take time. Once officials decide to change fiscal policy, they have to put the changes into effect within the federal budget, which takes more than a year to develop. Finally, they have to wait for the changes to affect the economy. As Figure 9.7 shows, by the time a new policy takes effect, the economy might be moving in the opposite direction. Government could propose massive public spending on highways and other infrastructure in the middle of a recession, only to have the economy recover before construction begins. In cases like this, fiscal policy would only strengthen the new trend, instead of correcting the original problem. If government continued to spend freely on highways in the middle of a recovery, it could lead to high inflation and a labor shortage. Political Pressures The President and the members of Congress, who develop the federal budget and the federal government&apos;s fiscal policy, are elected officials. If they wish to be reelected, they must make decisions that please the people who elect them&ndash;not necessarily decisions that are good for the overall economy. For example, government officials have an incentive to boost spending or lower taxes. Expansionary fiscal policies are often popular with voters. Government spending benefits firms that receive government contracts and individuals who receive direct government payments. Lower taxes leave more disposable income in people&apos;s pockets. On the other hand, contractionary fiscal policy, which decreases government spending or raises taxes, is often unpopular. Firms and individuals who expect income from the government are not happy when the income is reduced. No one likes to pay higher taxes, even when the revenue is spent on a highly valued good or service. Coordinating Fiscal Policy For fiscal policy to be effective, various branches and levels of government must work together. For example, if the federal government is pursuing contractionary policy, state and local governments should, ideally, pursue a similar fiscal policy. However, this does not always happen. For example, after the federal government cut income taxes in 2001 and 2003, many state and local governments raised income and property taxes in order to fund their budgets and avoid deep spending cuts. The federal government was willing 2010 GDP (in billions of dollars) 10,349 1,214 1,786 1,826 Personal Consumption Federal Government Spending State and Local Government Spending Gross Private Domestic Investment SOURCE: www.census.gov >> Figure 9.6 Analyze Graphs What percentage of GDP did spending by federal and state and local governments amount to in the year shown? 386 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="453"> <text><![CDATA[ Delayed Results and Fiscal Policy January 1 January 3 Experts say the economy is entering a recession. March 15 The President calls for increased spending on infrastructure to spur the economy. July 1 July 1 Congress debates and eventuallly agrees to fund proposed projects. October 1 New infrastructure projects officially begin. October 30 Experts announce that the recession has ended. January 1 January 1 Infrastructure project spending is just beginning to impact the economy. >> Figure 9.7 Using fictional events, this timeline illustrates the challenge of mounting a fiscal response to an economic downturn. Summarize Summarize the difficulty with fiscal policy that is represented by the events on this timeline. to cut taxes and run a deficit in poor economic times, but most state and local governments were legally forbidden to do so. Businesspeople, politicians, and economists often disagree about how well the economy is performing and what the goals of fiscal policy should be. Also, different regions of the country can experience different economic conditions. Some states may have high unemployment while others face a labor shortage. In addition, in order for the federal government&apos;s fiscal policy to be effective, it must also be coordinated with the monetary policy of the Federal Reserve. You will learn more about monetary policy elsewhere. Governments must recognize that short-term effects of fiscal policy will differ from long-term effects. These differing effects must be considered in evaluating the overall cost of any fiscal policy. For example, a tax cut or increased spending may give a quick boost to production and to employment. However, as the economy returns to full employment, continued high levels of government spending or increased market spending may lead to high inflation and interest rates. Similarly, an increase in taxes or fees or a decrease in government spending may “cool” the economy and avoid inflation. In the short run, reduced government spending and higher taxes may even contribute to a recession. But at the same time, such fiscal policies may create opportunities for private investment spending that could lead to higher economic growth in the long run. In this way, slow growth or even recession in the short term can lead to prosperity and more jobs in the future. EXPRESS PROBLEMS CLEARLY What challenge do policy-makers face when contemplating large changes in spending levels for the federal budget? ASSESSMENT 1. Define What is fiscal policy? 2. Express Ideas Clearly How does the government use the federal budget to implement its fiscal policy? 3. Apply Concepts Describe a hypothetical government budget that employs an expansionary policy. 4. Summarize Explain how fiscal policy decisions impact the economy. 5. Identify Identify at least one cost and one benefit of using fiscal policy as a tool to pursue the goal of economic growth. 9.1 The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy 387 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="454"> <text><![CDATA[ 9.2 Picture the scene: It&apos;s the Great Depression. Families everywhere are poor and hungry. Factories, shops, and even banks are closed, and millions are unemployed. People are not just anxious&ndash;they are desperate. >> During the Great Depression, government spending helped people like the family shown here. Generate Explanations Why do you think some people turn to the government for aid when times are difficult? Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS SS.912.E.1.10 >> Objectives Compare and contrast classical economics and demand-side economics. Analyze the importance of John Maynard Keynes and his economic theories. Explain the basic principles of supply-side economics and the importance of Milton Friedman. Analyze the impact of fiscal policy decisions on the economy of the United States. >> Key Terms classical economics Arthur Laffer productive capacity Milton Friedman demand-side John Kenneth economics Galbraith Keynesian economics multiplier effect automatic stabilizer supply-side economics deficit spending John Maynard Keynes Fiscal Policy Options Classical Economics During the Great Depression, it was clear that millions of people needed help. Less clear was the answer to this question: Who should provide it? A factory owner? The local supermarket? A religious institution or maybe the neighbors? What about the government? Would you expect the government to spend large amounts of money to give your father or mother&ndash;as well as thousands of other people&ndash;a job? Nowadays, many of us are used to the idea that the government might use its spending power to stimulate the economy. But at the time of the Depression, this was a radical new idea. And today, there are plenty of people who think that there are better ways the government can stimulate the economy than by spending. In this text, you will look at two very different fiscal policy options the government can pursue. In a free market, people act in their own self-interest, causing prices to rise or fall so that supply and demand will always return to equilibrium. This idea that free markets regulate themselves is central to the school of thought known as classical economics. Adam Smith, David Ricardo, and Thomas Malthus all contributed VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="455"> <text><![CDATA[ basic ideas to this school. For well over a century, classical economics dominated economic theory and government policies. Some aspects of classical economic thought are still widely followed today. The Great Depression, which began in 1929, challenged the classical theory. Prices fell over several years, so demand should have increased enough to stimulate production as consumers took advantage of low prices. Instead, demand also fell as people lost their jobs and bank failures wiped out their savings. Figure 9.9 highlights the widespread economic devastation. According to classical economics, the market should have reached equilibrium, with full employment. But it didn&apos;t, and millions suffered from unemployment and other hardships. Farmers lost their farms because corn was selling for seven cents a bushel and beef for two and a half cents a pound. Yet even with these low prices, many people were too poor to buy food. The Great Depression highlighted a problem with classical economics: It did not address how long it would take for the market to return to equilibrium. Classical economists recognized that it could take some time and looked for equilibrium to reestablish itself “in the long run”&ndash;over time. One economist, who was not satisfied with the idea of simply waiting for the economy to recover on its own, commented, “In the long run we are all dead.” That economist was John Maynard Keynes (pronounced CANES). IDENTIFY What event challenged the dominance of the classical economics school of thought? Keynesian Economics British economist John Maynard Keynes developed a new theory of economics to explain the Great Depression. Keynes presented his ideas in 1936 in a book called The General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money. He wanted to develop a comprehensive explanation of macroeconomic forces. Such an explanation, he argued, should tell economists and politicians how to get out of economic crises like the Great Depression. In sharp contrast to classical economics, Keynes wanted to give government a tool it could use immediately to boost the economy in the short run. His theories have had a huge impact on the changing role of government in the U.S. free enterprise system. Keynes Versus Classical Economics Classical economists had always looked at how the equilibrium of supply and demand applied to HOW BAD WAS THE GREAT DEPRESSION? 46.8% decline in industrial production 40% drop in real GDP At least 20% maximum unemployment 33% decline in stock value 20% bank failure rate 31% decline in money supply 2.5 million people displaced from the states of the Great Plains SOURCE: www.britannica.com >> Figure 9.9 Classical economics taught that a struggling economy would recover on its own. But the Great Depression lasted for many years. Analyze Data Why do you think the economy took so long to recover during the Great Depression? 9.2 Fiscal Policy Options 389 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="456"> <text><![CDATA[ individual products. In contrast, Keynes focused on the workings of the economy as a whole. Keynes looked at the productive capacity of the entire economy. Productive capacity, often called full-employment output, is the maximum output that an economy can sustain over a period of time without increasing inflation. Keynes attempted to answer the difficult question posed by the Great Depression: Why does actual production in an economy sometimes fall far short of its productive capacity? Keynes argued that the Depression continued because neither consumers nor businesses had an incentive to spend enough to cause an increase in production. After all, why would a company spend money to increase production when demand for its products was falling? How could consumers significantly increase demand when they had barely enough money to survive? The only way to end the Depression, Keynes thought, was to find a way to boost aggregate demand. Economists who agreed with the idea that demand drives the economy developed a school of thought known as demand-side economics. They asked themselves this question: Who could spend enough to spur demand and revitalize production? Keynesian Economics Output High output Low output Productivity capacity Consumer spending Business spending Government Consumer spending Business spending >> Figure 9.10 Keynes sought to achieve the full productive capacity of the economy. Analyze Graphs According to Keynes, what could fill the gap between low output and full productive capacity? Changing Government&apos;s Role in the Economy Keynes thought that the answer to that question was: the federal government. (See Figure 9.10.) He reasoned that in the early 1930s, only the federal government still had the resources to spend enough to affect the whole economy. The government could, in effect, make up for the drop in private spending by buying goods and services on its own. This, Keynes argued, would encourage production and increase employment. Then, as people went back to work, they would spend their wages on more goods and services, leading to even higher levels of production. This ever-expanding cycle would carry the economy out of the Great Depression. Once the crisis was over, Keynes believed, the government could step back and reduce its spending. These ideas form the core of Keynes&apos;s approach to resolving problems with the economy. Keynesian economics uses demand-side theory as the basis for encouraging government action to help the economy. In other words, Keynesian economics proposes that government can and should use fiscal policy to help the economy. Keynes argued that fiscal policy can combat the two fundamental macroeconomic problems: periods of recession and periods of inflation. Avoiding Recession The federal government, Keynes argued, should keep track of the total level of spending by consumers, businesses, and government. If total spending begins to fall far below the level required to keep the economy running at full capacity, the government should watch out for the possibility of recession. The government can respond by increasing its own spending until spending by the private sector returns to a higher level. Or it can cut taxes so that spending and investment by consumers and businesses increase. Raising government spending and cutting taxes are expansionary fiscal policies. After he was elected President in 1932, Franklin D. Roosevelt carried out expansionary fiscal policies. His New Deal put people to work&ndash;whether planting forests, building dams and schools, or painting murals. The federal government paid for all these programs. Classical economists criticized these programs. Even today, many people argue that instead of creating new jobs, such public works projects only shift employment from the private to the public sector. The dispute over Keynes&apos;s ideas is generally reflected today in the philosophies of the two political parties. Republicans generally have been 390 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="457"> <text><![CDATA[ THE MULTIPLIER EFFECT $10B + $8B + $6.4B + $5.1B Government spends an additional $10 billion. GDP INCREASES $10 BILLION. Recipients of the $10 billion spend $8 billion of it. GDP INCREASES $8 BILLION. Recipients of the $8 billion spend $6.4 billion of it. GDP INCREASES $6.4 BILLION. Recipients of the $6.4 billion spend $5.1 billion of it. GDP INCREASES $5.1 BILLION. GDP And so on…until the original $10 billion spending has INCREASED GDP BY $50 BILLION.>> Figure 9.11 The multiplier effect helps explain how government spending boosts the economy. Synthesize Explain how the multiplier effect supports Keynesian theory. associated with using tax cuts to stimulate the economy. Democrats generally have favored more expansive government programs to stimulate the economy. Keynes and Inflation Keynes also argued that the government could use a contractionary fiscal policy to prevent inflation or reduce its severity. The government can reduce inflation either by increasing taxes or by reducing its own spending. Both of these actions decrease overall demand. The Multiplier Effect Fiscal policy, although difficult to control, is a powerful tool. The key to its power is the multiplier effect. The multiplier effect in fiscal policy is the idea that each dollar spent or not taxed by government creates a change much greater than one dollar in the national income. In other words, the effects of changes in fiscal policy are multiplied. Suppose the federal government finds that business investment is dropping. To prevent a recession, in the next budget the government decides to spend an extra $10 billion to stimulate the economy. How will this affect the economy? With this government spending, demand, income, and GDP will increase by $10 billion. After all, if the government buys an extra $10 billion of goods and services, then an extra $10 billion of goods and services have been produced. However, the GDP could increase by more than $10 billion. Here&apos;s why: The businesses that sold the $10 billion in goods and services to the government have earned an additional $10 billion. These businesses will spend their additional earnings on wages, raw materials, and investment, sending money to workers, other suppliers, and stockholders. What will the recipients do with this money? They will spend part of it. Suppose they spend 80 percent of it, or $8 billion. The businesses that benefit from this second round of spending will then pass it back to households and other businesses, who will again spend 80 percent of it, or $6.4 billion. The next round will add an additional $5.1 billion to the economy, and so on. This phenomenon is illustrated in Figure 9.11. In this example, when all of the rounds of spending are added up, the initial spending of $10 billion adds about $50 billion to GDP. So, fiscal policy initiatives can have a bigger kick than the initial amount spent. Note, though, that not all spending multiplies at the same rate. For example, the multiplier effect on borrowed money may be greatly reduced. 9.2 Fiscal Policy Options 391 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="458"> <text><![CDATA[ The Role of Automatic Stabilizers Fiscal policy is used to achieve many economic goals. One of the most important things that fiscal policy can achieve is a more stable economy. A stable economy is one in which there are no rapid changes in economic indicators, which include stock prices, interest rates, and manufacturers&apos; new orders of capital goods. What&apos;s more, set up properly, fiscal policy can come close to stabilizing the economy automatically. Figure 9.12 shows how real GDP in the United States changed in the years following 1930. Prior to World War II, there were often large changes in GDP from year to year. Although GDP still fluctuates, these fluctuations have been smaller than they were before the war. Economic growth has been much more stable in the United States in the last 70 or so years. Why did this happen? After the war, federal taxes and spending on transfer payments&ndash;two key tools of fiscal policy&ndash;increased sharply. National taxes and transfer payments, or transfers of cash from the government to consumers, stabilize economic growth. When national income is high, the government collects more in taxes and pays out less in transfer payments. Both of these actions take money away from consumers, and therefore reduce spending. This decrease in spending balances out the increase in spending that results from rising income in a healthy economy. The opposite is also true. When income in the country is low, the government collects less in taxes and pays out more in transfer payments. Both actions increase the amount of money held by consumers, and thus increase spending. This increase in spending balances out the decrease in spending resulting from decreased income. Figure 9.13 shows the recent fluctuations in one type of transfer payment&ndash;food stamps. Taxes and transfer payments do not eliminate changes in the rate of growth of GDP, but they do make these changes smaller. Because they help make economic growth more stable, they are known as stabilizers. Policymakers do not have to make changes in taxes and transfer payments for them to have their stabilizing effect. Taxes and most transfer payments are tied to the GDP and to personal income, so they change automatically. Thus, they are called automatic stabilizers&ndash;tools of fiscal policy that increase or decrease automatically depending on changes in GDP and personal income. Some stabilizers are no longer automatic. The former Aid to Families with Dependent Children (AFDC), often called welfare, lost its entitlement status in 1996 and was renamed Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF). Now the federal government gives the states a set amount of money each year to spend as they wish. However, the stabilizer effect was not completely lost. When Annual Change in GDP, 1930–2012 Percentage change in GDP Year 20 15 10 5 0 –5 –10 –15 Year 1930 1940 1950 1960 1970 1980 1990 2000 2010 SOURCE: Bureau of Economic Analysis, Historical Statistics of the United States >> Figure 9.12 The U.S. economy has experienced regular ups and downs since 1930. Analyze Graphs How do the years after World War II show the effect of automatic stabilizers? 392 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="459"> <text><![CDATA[ Food Stamp Recipients, 1990–2012 Number of Recipients (in million) 50 30 40 20 10 1990 1992 1994 1996 1998 2000 2002 2004 2008 2006 2010 2012 SOURCE: www.fns.usda.gov >> Figure 9.13 The number of food-stamp recipients fell during the economic growth of the mid-1990s and rose during a recession that began in 2007. Analyze Graphs How do macroeconomic developments affect the number of people requiring food- stamp assistance? the economy boomed in the late 1990s, state spending on TANF fell. IDENTIFY MAIN IDEAS How did Keynes propose to end the Great Depression? Supply-Side Economics Another school of economic thought promotes a different direction for fiscal policy. Supply-side economics is based on the idea that the supply of goods drives the economy. Whereas Keynesian economics tries to encourage economic growth by increasing aggregate demand, supply-side economics relies on increasing aggregate supply. It does this by focusing on taxes. In recent years, supply-side economics has had a significant impact on the U.S. economy and free enterprise system. Analyzing the Laffer Curve Supply-side economists believe that taxes have a strong negative impact on economic output. They often use the Laffer curve, named after the economist Arthur Laffer, to illustrate the effects of taxes. The Laffer curve (Figure 9.14) presents a supply-side view of the relationship between the tax rate and the total tax revenue that the government collects. The total revenue depends on both the tax rate and the health of the economy. The Laffer curve suggests that high tax rates may not bring in much revenue if they cause economic activity to decrease. Suppose the government imposes a tax on the wages of workers. If the tax rate is zero, as at point a on the graph, the government will collect no revenue, although the economy will benefit from the lack of taxes. As the government raises the tax rate, it starts to collect some revenue. You can see this change in Figure 9.14. From a 0 percent tax rate (point a) to a 50 percent tax rate on the curve (point b), rising tax rates begin to discourage some people from working as many hours as they might, and hinder companies from investing and increasing production. The net effect of a higher tax rate and a slightly lower tax base is still an increase in revenue. At tax rates higher than 50 percent, the decrease in workers&apos; effort is so large that the higher tax rate actually decreases total tax revenue. In other words, high rates of taxation will eventually discourage so many people from working that tax revenues will fall. In the extreme case of a 100 percent tax rate, no one would want to work! In this case, shown at point c on the curve, the government would collect no revenue. 9.2 Fiscal Policy Options 393 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="460"> <text><![CDATA[ The Relationship Between Taxes and Output The heart of the supply-side argument is that a tax cut increases total employment so much that the government actually collects more in taxes at the new, lower tax rate. Suppose the initial tax on labor is $3 an hour, and the typical worker works 30 hours per week, paying a total of $90 in taxes each week. If the government cuts the tax on labor to $2 an hour, and the worker responds by working 50 hours per week, the worker will pay $100 in taxes a week, an increase of $10. Figure 9.15 shows the increase in government revenues during a time when government was at least partly following supply-side policies. The economic growth of the 1980s was impressive, but it is hard to pin down the role that U.S. supply-side economic policies played in this outcome. Some economists argue that although a tax cut encourages some workers to work more hours, the end result is a relatively small increase in the number of hours worked. Take the example of the worker above. These economists would say that if the tax cut increased the hours worked from 30 hours to 35 hours, the worker would pay only $70 in taxes ($2 per hour times 35 hours), down from $90 ($3 per hour times 30 hours). In general, these economists argue, taxpayers do not react strongly enough to tax cuts to increase tax revenue. As you can see, there is much debate over the relationship between tax rates and output. In addition to being an economic question, this debate plays a major role in American politics today. CHECK UNDERSTANDING How does the supply-side economics theory link taxation to employment levels? The Recent History of U.S. Fiscal Policy As you recall, Keynes presented his ideas at a time when the world economy was engulfed in a severe economic downturn. President Herbert Hoover, a strong believer in classical economics, thought that the economy was basically sound and would return to equilibrium on its own, without government interference. His successor, President Franklin D. Roosevelt, was more willing to increase government spending to help boost the economy. World War II Keynes&apos;s theory was fully tested in the United States during World War II. As the country geared up for war, government spending increased dramatically. The government spent large sums of money to feed soldiers and equip them Laffer Curve High revenues Tax revenues Low revenues Tax rate Low taxes a b c 0% 50% 100%  High taxes >> Figure 9.14 The Laffer curve shows the theoretical effect increasingly higher tax rates have on tax revenues. Analyze Graphs According to the Laffer curve, what do both a very high and a very low tax rate produce? Bounce to Activate Chart 394 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="461"> <text><![CDATA[ Federal Revenue, 1975–1992 YEAR 1975 1976 1977 1978 1979 1980 1981 1982 1983 REVENUE (IN BILLIONS OF DOLLARS) 279.09 298.06 355.56 399.56 463.30 517.11 599.27 617.77 600.56 YEAR 1984 1985 1986 1987 1988 1989 1990 1991 1992 REVENUE (IN BILLIONS OF DOLLARS) 666.44 734.04 769.16 854.29 909.24 991.11 1,031.96 1,054.99 1,091.21 SOURCE: Office of Management and Budget >> Figure 9.15 Federal revenue clearly rose throughout the period shown, even though the 1980s was a decade of tax cuts. Analyze Data Do the data here support the idea of supply-side economics? Explain. Bounce to Activate Chart with everything from warplanes to rifles to medical supplies. This money was given to the private sector in exchange for goods. Just as Keynesian economics predicted, the additional demand for goods and services moved the country sharply out of the Great Depression and toward full productive capacity. The enormous government spending during the war boosted output and greatly reduced unemployment. But the benefits of this U.S. economic policy also had costs. Until the presidency of Franklin Roosevelt, the federal government had sought to balance its budget, spending no more than it received in revenue. During the New Deal and World War II, expenditures exceeded revenues, a situation known as deficit spending. To finance deficit spending, the government has to borrow money, for which it pays interest. This represents a financial cost as well as an opportunity cost&ndash;the money used to pay interest cannot be used for other purposes. Postwar Keynesian Policy After World War II ended, Congress created the Council of Economic Advisers (CEA). Made up of three respected economists, the CEA advised the President on economic policy. Between 1945 and 1960, the U.S. economy was generally healthy and growing, despite a few minor recessions. The last recession continued into the term of President John F. Kennedy, with unemployment reaching a level of 6.7 percent. Kennedy&apos;s chief financial policy adviser, chairperson of the CEA Walter Heller, thought that the economy was below its productive capacity. He convinced Kennedy that tax cuts would stimulate demand and bring the economy closer to full productive capacity. As Figure 9.16 shows, the highest marginal tax rate on individual income was about 90 percent in the early 1960s&ndash;compared with a top rate of 39.6 in 2013. Kennedy proposed tax cuts, both because he agreed with Heller and because tax cuts are popular. A version of Kennedy&apos;s tax cuts was enacted in 1964, under President Lyndon Johnson. At the same time, the Vietnam War raised government spending. Over two years, consumption and GDP increased by more than 4 percent a year. There is no way to prove that the tax cut caused this growth, but the result was generally what Keynesian economics predicted. Keynesian economics was used often in the 1960s and 1970s. One Keynesian economist, John Kenneth Galbraith, greatly influenced national policies. Galbraith, a strong supporter of public spending, helped develop the far-reaching&ndash;and enormously costly&ndash;social welfare programs that lay at the heart of President Johnson&apos;s vision of a Great Society. (See Figure 9.17.) 9.2 Fiscal Policy Options 395 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="462"> <text><![CDATA[ Supply-Side Policy in the 1980s During the late 1970s, with Keynesian fiscal policy in place, unemployment and inflation rates soared. When Ronald Reagan became President in 1981, he vowed to cut taxes and spending. An “anti-Keynesian,” Reagan did not believe that government should spend its way out of a recession: Government spending has become so extensive that it contributes to the economic problems it was designed to cure. More government intervention in the economy cannot possibly be a solution to our economic problems. &ndash;Ronald Reagan, White House Report on the Program for Economic Recovery, 1981 Reagan instituted policies based on supply-side economics, a theory promoted by economists such as George Gilder. Among Reagan&apos;s advisers was Milton Friedman, a former professor of economics. Friedman strongly supported individual freedom and pushed for more laissez-faire policies&ndash;hallmarks of classical and supply-side economics. He also supported a constitutional amendment to balance the federal budget. In 1981, Reagan proposed a tax cut that reduced taxes by 25 percent over three years. In a short time, the economy recovered and flourished. Still, tax cuts plus an expanded defense budget led to further deficit spending, just as following Keynesian policy would have done. Under the next few Presidents, the federal government spent much more money than it took in. As you will read in the next lesson, this gap caused increasing concern among economists and policymakers. A Return to Keynes In late 2008, the United States was hit with what many economists believed was the worst financial crisis since the Great Depression. A number of major financial institutions failed. Credit became harder to get, consumer spending dropped, and unemployment rose. The crisis occurred in the midst of what news commentators named the Great Recession, an economic downturn that had begun in December 2007. In November 2008, voters elected a new President, Barack Obama. He promised to take firm action to stimulate the economy. Obama signed a stimulus bill in February 2009 that aimed to boost demand and create jobs. The $840 billion package included contracts, grants, and loans for education, transportation, and infrastructure projects. It also included a set of tax cuts and additional entitlement payments. To many observers, such proposals seemed to signal a shift back to a Keynesian fiscal policy, as in the New Deal. Top Marginal Tax Rate, 1925–Present Top Marginal Tax Rate(percent of income) 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 Year 1925 1935 1945 1955 1965 1975 1985 1995 2005 2015 SOURCE: Tax Policy Center: Urban Institute and Brookings Institute >> Figure 9.16 The top marginal tax rates&ndash;rates affecting the highest incomes&ndash;have varied widely over the last century. Analyze Graphs What has been the general trend in the top marginal tax rate since 1945? 396 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="463"> <text><![CDATA[ Great Society Programs Community Action Program Head Start Job Corps Medicare Medicaid Focused on helping the urban poor become self-sufficient Gave underprivileged preschoolers the early learning necessary to be prepared for kindergarten Provided vocational training to the underprivileged Ensured health care services to people age 65 and older and others with certain disabilities Provided medical insurance for low-income people Model Cities Program National Endowment for the Arts and Humanities Neighborhood Youth Corps Upward Bound Volunteers in Service to America Funded urban redevelopment Funded artists and galleries for the cultural betterment of society Gave poor urban youths work experience and encouraged continued education Helped poor high school students get a college education A domestic Peace Corps aimed at helping communities in the U.S. SOURCE: www.ushistory.org >> Figure 9.17 Publicly funded Great Society programs served all age groups but focused mainly on the poor and underprivileged. Predict Consequences How do you think the Great Society affected the federal budget? Obama’s economic stimulus program received mixed reviews. The economy emerged from the recession in June 2009, but growth remained unsteady into 2013. By the middle of that year, the unemployment rate had fallen to 7.4 percent from a high of 10 percent, but that left about 12 million Americans looking for work. Some of Obama’s advisers, following Keynesian principles, insisted that the government should have injected much more money into the economy to encourage sustained growth. However, concerns in Congress about the escalating deficit undercut arguments for pursuing further expansionary fiscal policies. Identify What Keynesian fiscal policy tool did President Kennedy use? ASSESSMENT 1. Interpret When John Maynard Keynes said, “In the long run we are all dead,” what problem of classical economics was he pointing out? 2. Analyze Information What might be one cost and one benefit of Keynesian economic policies? 3. Identify Cause and Effect Why might cutting taxes increase economic output and total employment? 4. Support Ideas With Evidence What ideas of Milton Friedman are reflected in the policies of Ronald Reagan? 5. Draw Conclusions Did Keynesian fiscal policy help end the Great Recession of 2007–2009? Explain your answer. 9.2 Fiscal Policy Options 397 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="464"> <text><![CDATA[ Primary Sources LAFS.1112.RH.1.3, LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, SS.912.E.3.6 The Economic Role of the government: Two Views During the Great Depression, unemployment was widespread, and shaky banks could not lend to businesses or consumers. John Maynard Keynes argued that governments had to create money and inject it into the economy to help create jobs. Keynes&apos;s General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money was published in 1936. President Roosevelt&apos;s New Deal program followed Keynes&apos;s advice. Some economists, including Friedrich Hayek, disagreed, arguing that too much government spending could lead to inflation and other economic problems. In a 1950 speech, Hayek stated his views. >> Economists disagree about the economic role of government agencies and the Federal Reserve System, whose headquarters is shown here. General Theory of Employment, Interest, and Money: John Maynard Keynes . . . The State will have to exercise a guiding influence on the propensity to consume. . . . Furthermore, it seems unlikely that the influence of banking policy on the rate of interest will be sufficient by itself to determine an optimum rate of investment. I conceive, therefore, that a somewhat comprehensive socialisation [shift to the government] of investment will prove the only means of securing an approximation to full employment . . . But beyond this no obvious case is made out for a system of State Socialism which would embrace most of the economic life of the community. It is not the ownership of the instruments of production which it is important for the State to assume. If the State is able to determine the aggregate amount of resources devoted to augmenting the instruments and the basic rate of reward to those who own them, it will have accomplished all that is necessary. ExPLAIN AN ARgUMENT What does Keynes argue that government needs to do? What does he argue that it need not do? . . . The central controls necessary to ensure full employment will, of course, involve a large extension of the traditional functions of government. . . . But there will still remain a wide field for the exercise of private initiative and responsibility. . . . Whilst, therefore, the enlargement of the functions of government, involved in the task of adjusting to one another the propensity to consume and the inducement to invest, would seem . . . to a contemporary American financier to be a terrific encroachment on individualism, I defend it, on the contrary, both as the only practicable means of avoiding the destruction of existing economic forms in their entirety and as the condition of the successful functioning of individual initiative. EXPLAIN AN ARGUMENT Why is “an enlargement of the functions of government” necessary, according to Keynes? . . . The authoritarian state systems of to-day seem to solve the problem of unemployment at the expense of efficiency and of freedom. It is certain that the world will not much longer tolerate the unemployment which . . . is associated&ndash;and, in my opinion, inevitably associated&ndash;with present-day 398 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="465"> <text><![CDATA[ capitalistic individualism. But it may be possible by a right analysis of the problem to cure the disease whilst preserving efficiency and freedom. . . . DRAW INFERENCES What does Keynes imply will result if the problem of unemployment is not solved? full Employment, Planning and Inflation: friedrich hayek In the five years that have elapsed since the war, central planning, “full employment,” and inflationary pressure have been the three features which have dominated economic policy in the greater part of the world. Of these only full employment can be regarded as desirable in itself. . . . Inflation, even “repressed inflation,” is undoubtedly an evil, though some would say a necessary evil if other desirable aims are to be achieved. It is part of the price we pay for having committed ourselves to a policy of full employment and central planning. IDENTIFY CAUSE ANd EFFECT What evil does Hayek claim is caused by a policy of full employment? Full employment has come to mean, that Maximum of employment that can be brought about in the short run by monetary pressure. . . . That in most situations employment can be temporarily increased by monetary expansion [that is, inflation] has long been known. . . .What is new about present beliefs is that it is now widely held that so long as monetary expansion creates additional employment, it is innocuous or at least will cause more benefit than harm. Yet while in practice full employment policies merely mean that in the short run employment is kept somewhat higher than it would otherwise be, it is at least doubtful whether over longer periods they will not in fact lower the level of employment which can be permanently maintained without progressive monetary expansion. These policies are however constantly represented as if the practical problem were not this but as if the choice were between full employment thus defined and the lasting mass unemployment of the nineteen-thirties. The habit of thinking in terms of an alternative between “full employment” and a state of affairs in which there are unemployed factors of all kinds available is perhaps the most dangerous legacy which we owe to the great influence of the late Lord Keynes. . . . dETERMINE AUThOR&apos;S POINT Of VIEw Why does Hayek feel that Keynes&apos;s influence has been “dangerous”? ASSESSMENT 1. Assess an Argument Evaluate Keynes&apos;s and Hayek&apos;s different points of view on the economic role of government by assessing their claims, reasoning, and evidence. Which do you think makes the more convincing argument? Explain. 2. Compare and Contrast Reread the text under the heading “Business Cycles in the United States” in Topic 7 Lesson 2 and under “The Recent History of U.S. Fiscal Policy” in Topic 9 Lesson 2. Compare Keynes&apos;s explanation of the effects of government action with the facts in the texts, then compare Hayek&apos;s explanation with those facts. Which explanation best matches the textual evidence? Where does the text leave matters uncertain? 3. Draw Inferences What are areas of agreement between Keynes and Hayek? ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINEfor primary sources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="466"> <text><![CDATA[ 9.3 If you have used a credit card, you might have some idea how easy it is to spend money you don&apos;t have. If you fail to pay the credit card bill in full each month, the high interest rate may mean that the amount you owe just keeps increasing. Soon you may face a mountain of debt. >> When this picture was taken in early 2013, the national debt was $16.5 trillion on its way to topping $17 trillion by the end of the year. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS SS.912.E.2.9, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 >> Objectives Explain the importance of balancing the budget. Analyze the impact of fiscal policy decisions on the nation&apos;s economy. Summarize the way budget deficits add to the national debt. Identify how political leaders have tried to control the deficit. >> Key Terms budget surplus budget deficit Treasury bill Treasury note Treasury bond national debt crowding-out effect The National Debt and Deficits Budget Surpluses and Deficits The federal government is no stranger to spending more than it has. The government uses spending as a fiscal policy tool to improve the economy. The basic tool of fiscal policy is the federal budget. It is made up of two fundamental parts: revenue (taxes) and expenditures (spending programs). When the federal government&apos;s revenues equal its expenditures in any particular fiscal year, the federal government has a balanced budget. In reality, the federal budget is almost never balanced. Usually, it is either running a surplus or a deficit. A budget surplus occurs in any year when revenues exceed expenditures. In other words, there is more money going into the Treasury than coming outofit. A budget deficit occurs in any year when expenditures exceed revenues. In other words, there is more money coming out of the Treasury than going into it. Deficits have become a common characteristic of the economy in recent decades. Figure 9.18 illustrates this development clearly. Assume the federal government starts with a balanced budget. If the government decreases expenditures without changing VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="467"> <text><![CDATA[ anything else, it will run a budget surplus. Similarly, if it increases taxes&ndash;revenues&ndash;without changing anything else, it will run a surplus. This analysis also explains budget deficits. If the government increases expenditures without changing anything else, it will run a deficit. Similarly, if it decreases taxes without changing anything else, it will run a deficit. The deficit can grow or shrink because of forces beyond the government&apos;s control. Surpluses and deficits can be very large figures. The largest deficit, in 2009, was over $1.4 trillion. Dealing With Deficits When the government runs a deficit, it is because it did not take in enough revenue to cover its expenses for the year. When this happens, the government must find a way to pay for the extra expenditures. There are two basic actions the government can take to do so. Creating Money The government can create new money to pay salaries for its workers and benefits for citizens. Traditionally, governments simply printed the bills they needed. Today, the government can create money electronically by actions that effectively deposit money in people&apos;s bank accounts. The effect is the same. This approach works for relatively small deficits but can cause severe problems when there are large deficits. What are these problems? When the government creates more money, it increases the amount of money in circulation. This increases the demand for goods and services and can increase output. But once the economy reaches full employment, output cannot increase. The increase in money will mean that there are more dollars but the same amount of goods and services. Prices will rise so that a greater amount of money will be needed to purchase the same amount of goods and services. In other words, prices go up, and the result is inflation. Covering very large deficits by printing more money can cause hyperinflation. This happened in Germany and Russia after World War I, in Brazil and Argentina in the 1980s, and in Ukraine in the 1990s. If the United States experienced hyperinflation, a shirt that cost $30 in June might cost $50 in July, $80 in August, and $400 in December! Borrowing Money The U.S. federal government usually does not resort to creating money to cover a budget deficit. Instead, it borrows money. The government commonly borrows money by selling bonds. A bond is a type of loan: a promise to repay money in the future, with interest. Consumers and businesses buy bonds from the government. The Budget Surpluses and Deficits, 1950–2012 Surplus or deficit (in billions of dollars) Year 2000 1500 –1500 –1000 –500 0 500 1000 1950 1960 1970 1980 SOURCE: Office of Management and Budget 1990 2000 2010 >> Figure 9.18 Budgets that followed the gray horizontal line on this graph would be balanced. Analyze Graphs Write a brief summary of this graph and the story it tells about surpluses and deficits from 1950 to 2012. 9.3 The National Debt and Deficits 401 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="468"> <text><![CDATA[ government thus has the money to cover its budget deficit. In return, the purchasers of the bonds earn interest on their investment over time. United States Savings Bonds (“EE Bonds”) allow millions of Americans to lend small amounts of money to the federal government. In return, they earn interest on the bonds for up to 30 years. Other common forms of government borrowing are Treasury bills, notes, and bonds. Treasury bills are short-term bonds that have maturity dates of 26 weeks or less. Treasury notes have terms of 2 to 10 years. Treasury bonds mature 30 years after issue. Federal borrowing lets the government undertake more projects than it could otherwise afford. Wise borrowing allows the government to create more public goods and services. Federal borrowing, however, also has serious disadvantages. RECALL What is the most common method the federal government uses to pay for expenditures that exceed revenues? Deficits and the National Debt Like people, when the government borrows money, it goes into debt. The national debt is the total amount of money the federal government owes to bondholders. Every year that there is a budget deficit and the federal government borrows money to cover it, the national debt will grow. The national debt is owed to investors who hold Treasury bonds, bills, and notes. These bonds are considered to be among the safest investments in the world. As such, they offer a secure investment for individuals and businesses. Because the United States is widely viewed as stable and trustworthy, the federal government can borrow money at a lower rate of interest than private citizens or corporations can. Lower interest rates benefit taxpayers by reducing the cost of government borrowing. The Difference Between Deficit and Debt Many people are confused about the difference between the deficit and the debt. The deficit is the amount of money the government borrows for one budget, representing one fiscal year. The debt, on the other hand, is the sum of all the government borrowing before that time, minus the borrowings that have been repaid. Each deficit adds to the debt. Each surplus subtracts from it. Measuring the National Debt In dollar terms, the size of the national debt is extremely large. By the end of 2013, it exceeded $17 trillion! Such a large number can best be analyzed in relation to the size of the economy as a whole. Therefore, let&apos;s look at the size of the debt as a percentage of gross domestic product National Debt as a Percentage of GDP Percentage of GDP 120 80 100 60 40 20 0 Year 1940 1946 1952 1958  1964 1970 1976 1982 1988 1994 2000 2006 2012 2018 World War II 1980 NOTE: Figures for 2013–2018 are projected. SOURCE: The Office of Management and Budget. www.whitehouse.gov/omb/budget/historicals, Table 7.1  >> Figure 9.19 Measuring the national debt as a percentage of GDP is a way to compare debt at different times in history. Analyze Graphs How would you describe today&apos;s debt in the context of the last 80 years? Bounce to Activate Gallery 402 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="469"> <text><![CDATA[ THE CROWDING-OUT EFFECT THE GOVERNMENT FEDERAL SPENDS MORE THAN IT TAKES IN. THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT BORROWS MONEY TO COVER THE DEFICIT. INVESTORS AND BANKS LOAN MONEY TO GOVERNMENT BY BUYING U.S. BONDS –AN ATTRACTIVE INVESTMENT.AS A RESULT, INVESTORS AND BANKS HAVE LESS TO LEND PRIVATE BUSINESSES. PRIVATE BUSINESSES MUST PAY HIGHER INTEREST RATES TO BORROW SCARCE MONEY. %>> Figure 9.20 This diagram shows one way excess spending can hurt the economy. Analyze Charts According to this diagram, what causes private businesses to be crowded out in the quest for investment? (GDP) over time. This can be seen in Figure 9.19. Historically, debt as a percentage of GDP rises during wartime, when government spending increases faster than taxation, and it falls during peacetime. Notice how this characteristic of the U.S. economy has changed in recent times. In the 1980s, the United States began to run a large debt, even though the country wasn&apos;t at war. The debt was in part a result of increases in spending during President Ronald Reagan&apos;s terms. In addition, the Reagan administration also cut taxes. The combined effect of higher spending and lower tax rates was several years of increased budget deficits. The impact of these fiscal policy decisions on the economy was significant. The government borrowed billions of dollars to cover the deficits, adding to the national debt. As a result, the ratio of debt to GDP grew very large for peacetime. ChECK UNdERSTANdINg To whom does the government owe the national debt? The Impact of Debt The growth of the national debt during the Reagan administration led many to focus on the problems caused by a national debt. In general, three problems can arise from a national debt. Problems of a National Debt The first problem with a national debt is that it reduces the funds available for businesses to invest. This is because in order to sell its bonds, the government must offer a higher interest rate. Individuals and businesses, attracted by the higher interest rates and the security of investing in the government, use their savings or profits to purchase government bonds. Take a look at Figure 9.20. It explains how every dollar spent on a government bond is one fewer dollar that can be invested in private business. Less money is available for companies to expand their factories, conduct research, and develop new products, and so interest rates rise. This loss of funds for private investment caused by government borrowing is called the crowding-out effect. Federal borrowing “crowds out” private borrowing by making it harder for private businesses to borrow. A national debt, then, can hurt investment and slow economic growth over the long run. In this way, fiscal policy decisions can have a significant impact on how the economy and the free enterprise system function. The second problem with a high national debt is that the government must pay interest to bondholders. The more the government borrows, the more interest it has to pay. Paying the interest on the debt is sometimes called servicing the debt. 9.3 The National Debt and Deficits 403 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="470"> <text><![CDATA[ Over time, the interest payments have become very large. About the year 2000, the federal government spent about $250 billion a year servicing the debt. Moreover, there is an opportunity cost&ndash;dollars spent servicing the debt cannot be spent on something else, such as defense, healthcare, or infrastructure. A possible third problem involves foreign ownership of the national debt. The biggest holder of that debt is the United States government itself. The government uses bonds as a secure savings account for holding Social Security, Medicare, and other funds. But about a quarter of the debt is owned by foreign governments, including Japan, China, and the United Kingdom. Some critics of the debt fear that a country like China could use its large bond holdings as a tool to extract favors from the United States. Others disagree, arguing that foreign states own too little of the debt to cause any concern. Other Views on the National Debt Some people insist that the national debt is not a big problem. (You can see an example of such a view in Figure 9.21.) Traditional Keynesian economists believe that fiscal policy is an important tool that can be used to help achieve full productive capacity. To these analysts, the benefits of a productive economy outweigh the costs of interest on national debt. In the short term, deficit spending may help create jobs and encourage economic growth. However, a budget deficit can be an effective tool only if it is temporary. Most people agree that if the government runs large budget deficits year after year, the costs of the growing debt will eventually outweigh the benefits. IdENTIfy What are the problems of having a large national debt? Measures to Control the Deficit During the 1980s and the early 1990s, annual budget deficits added substantially to the national debt. Several factors frustrated lawmakers in their attempts to control the deficit. As we have seen, much of the budget consists of entitlement spending that is politically difficult to change. Another large part of the budget consists of interest that must be paid to bondholders. Finally, specific budget cuts are often opposed by interest groups. Reducing Deficits Concerns about the budget deficits of the mid-1980s caused Congress to OPPOSING VIEWS ON THE DANGER OF DEBT “Recent and projected growth in U.S. government debt poses a serious hazard to the nation. At a minimum, high levels of government debt mean substantial government resources must go toward servicing debt&ndash;to pay interest.” J.D. Foster, Ph.D, The Heritage Foundation, June 18, 2013 “With so many economic, political, and social problems facing us today, there is little point in focusing attention on something that is not one. The false fear of which I speak is the chance of US debt default.” John T. Harvey, Forbes, September 10, 2012 >> Figure 9.21 On the subject of the national debt, observers differ over the nature and extent of the threat. Compare Points of View Explain how these two viewpoints differ on the subject of the national debt. 404 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="471"> <text><![CDATA[ pass the Gramm-Rudman-Hollings Act. This law created automatic across-the-board cuts in federal expenditures if the deficit exceeded a certain amount. The automatic nature of the cuts saved lawmakers from having to make difficult decisions about individual funding cuts. However, the act exempted significant portions of the budget (including interest payments and many entitlement programs such as Social Security) from the cuts. The Supreme Court found that some parts of the Gramm-Rudman-Hollings Act were unconstitutional. Congress attempted to correct the flaws. In 1990, however, lawmakers realized that the deficit was going to be much larger than expected. Because Congress had exempted so many programs from automatic cuts, funding for nonexempt programs would be dramatically slashed. To resolve the crisis, President George H. W. Bush and congressional leaders negotiated a new budget system that replaced Gramm-Rudman-Hollings. The 1990 Budget Enforcement Act created a “pay-as-yougo” system (also known as PAYGO). PAYGO required Congress to raise enough revenue to cover increases in direct spending that would otherwise contribute to the budget deficit. This law expired in 2002, but in 2007 the House and Senate restored PAYGO in the form of special budget rules. At various times, citizens and politicians have suggested amending the Constitution to require a balanced budget. In 1995, a balanced budget amendment gained the two-thirds majority it needed to pass the House, but the next year it failed by a single vote in the Senate. Supporters argued that the amendment would force the federal government to be more disciplined about its spending. Opponents said that a constitutional amendment requiring a balanced budget would not give the government the flexibility it needed to deal with rapid changes in the economy. The Surpluses of the Late 1990s The late 1990s brought a welcome reversal of fortune. For the first time in thirty years, the President and the Office of Management and Budget were able to announce that the federal government was running a surplus. How did this happen? First, the new budget procedures begun under President Bush and extended under President Clinton helped Congress control the growth of government spending. Second, tax increases by President Clinton in 1993 resulted in more federal revenue. Finally, the strong economy and low unemployment meant that more individuals and corporations were earning more money&ndash;and thus paying more to the government in taxes. >> This 1993 magazine reflected a booming market for personal computers&ndash;a boom that played a key role in the fast-growing economy of the 1990s. A Return to Deficit Spending The changeover from deficits to surplus brought with it a different set of political concerns. Investors who had come to rely heavily upon Treasury bonds as the basic “safe” investment worried that the federal government would remove all bonds from the market as it repaid its debt. Americans debated how to make best use of the budget surplus. As a presidential candidate in 2000, George W. Bush pledged to use the surplus to guarantee Social Security into the new century, provide additional medical benefits to older people, and reduce income taxes. However, the surplus was short-lived. The end of the stock market boom, an economic slowdown, and a new federal income tax cut reduced federal revenues. The Islamist terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, dealt a double blow to the federal budget by disrupting the economy and imposing a new set of defense costs. You can see how these costs affected government spending in Figure 9.22. In response, the federal government returned to deficit spending. The federal budget continued to show a large deficit for the next several years, due in part to counterterrorism efforts and the very costly wars in Afghanistan and Iraq. In fiscal year 2008 9.3 The National Debt and Deficits 405 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="472"> <text><![CDATA[ Federal Spending, 2000 and 2007 20% 9% 27% 23% 21% 16% 2000 2007 12% 30% 19% 23% Defense Social Security Medicare/ Other Health Care Interest Other SOURCE: Office of Management and Budget >> Figure 9.22 Federal spending priorities changed significantly between 2000 and 2007. Analyze Graphs Which categories saw the greatest increase over this time period? Bounce to Activate Chart alone, the President&apos;s funding requests for the war on terrorism approached $200 billion. The long-term outlook for the federal budget is uncertain. Funding for stimulus projects and new healthcare initiatives may cause long-term spending to increase. Social Security and Medicare are projected to rise sharply in the next 30 years as large numbers of baby boomers leave the job market and retire. Balancing the budget is expected to become even more difficult. IDENTIFY What factors contributed to the deficit spending of the 2000s? ASSESSMENT 1. Identify Cause and Effect What is the impact of a budget deficit on the national debt? 2. Check Understanding Explain the crowding- out effect that results from national debt. 3. Evaluate Arguments Is creating money to cover a budget deficit a good or bad idea? Explain your answer. 4. Draw Conclusions Of the three possible problems that can arise from having a large national debt, which is the most serious? Explain. 5. Predict Consequences How could lowering income taxes during an economic downturn lead to increased national debt? 406 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="473"> <text><![CDATA[ 9.4 Suppose you have a checkbook that allows you to write as many checks as you wish for any amount you desire. You don&apos;t need to worry about the balance in your account, and the checks will always be cashed, no matter how much you spend. Of course, no person has an account like that. However, the Federal Reserve comes close. By using its monetary policy tools, the Federal Reserve System affects the nation&apos;s money supply. The Fed has the power to increase or decrease the amount of money in the United States. The Fed manipulates the money supply in order to stabilize the American economy. >> Coins and paper bills are manufactured in facilities like this. But it is the Federal Reserve that puts money in circulation through the process of money creation.Bounce to Activate Flipped Video Monetary Policy Options Creating Money Money Manufacture vs. Money Creation The U.S. Department of the Treasury is responsible for manufacturing money in the form of currency. The Federal Reserve is responsible for putting money into circulation. How does this money get into the economy? The process is called money creation, and it is carried out by the Fed and by banks all around the country. This process is similar to the multiplier effect of government spending. The multiplier effect in fiscal policy holds that every one-dollar change in fiscal policy creates a change greater than one dollar in the economy. The process of money creation works in much the same way. How Banks Create Money Money creation does not mean the printing of new bills. Banks create money not by printing it, but by simply going about their business. For example, suppose you take out a loan of $1,000. You decide to deposit the money in a checking account. Once you have  NGSSS SS.912.E.1.11, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, SS.912.FL.3.6, SS.912.FL.5.8 >> Objectives Describe the process of money creation. Analyze how the Federal Reserve uses reserve requirements to implement U.S. monetary policy. Analyze the three primary tools the Federal Reserve uses to implement monetary policy, including open market operations. Explain why the Federal Reserve prefers open market operations as a means to implementing monetary policy. >> Key Terms money creation required reserve ratio money multiplier formula excess reserves discount rate federal funds rate prime rate open market operations security VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="474"> <text><![CDATA[ deposited the money, you now have a balance of $1,000. This money is a demand deposit that must be paid by the bank to you whenever you ask for it. It is counted as part of what economists call M1&ndash;the total amount of money people can gain access to and spend readily. So, as a result of this loan and deposit, the money supply has increased by $1,000. The process of money creation begins here. Banks make money by charging interest on loans. Your bank will lend part of the $1,000 that you deposited. The maximum amount that a bank can lend is determined by the required reserve ratio (RRR)&ndash;the fraction of deposits that banks are required to keep in reserve. This is calculated as the ratio of reserves to deposits. The RRR, which is established by the Federal Reserve, ensures that banks will have enough funds to supply customers&apos; withdrawal needs. Suppose in our example that the RRR is 0.1, or 10 percent. This means that the bank is required to keep 10 percent of your $1,000 demand deposit balance, or $100, in reserve. It is allowed to lend $900. Follow along in Figure 9.23 to see what happens to this money next. Let&apos;s say the bank lends that $900 to Kai, and he deposits it in his checking account. Kai now has $900 he didn&apos;t have before. Kai&apos;s $900 is now included in M1. You still have your $1,000 in your account, on which you can write a check at any time. Thus, your initial deposit to the bank and the subsequent loan have caused the money supply to increase by $1,000 + $900 for a total of $1,900. Now suppose that Kai uses the $900 to buy Lena&apos;s old car. Lena deposits the $900 from Kai into her checking account. Her bank keeps 10 percent of the deposit, or $90, as required reserves. It will lend the other $810 to its customers. So, Lena has a demand deposit balance of $900, which is included in the money supply, and the new borrowers get $810, which is also added to the money supply. This means that the money supply has now increased by $1,000 + $900 + $810 = $2,710&ndash;all because of your initial $1,000 deposit. The Money Multiplier This money creation process will continue until the loan amount, and hence the amount of new money that can be created, becomes very small. To determine the total amount of new money that can be created and added to the money supply, economists use the money multiplier formula, which is calculated as 1 ÷ RRR. To apply the formula, they multiply the initial deposit by the money multiplier: Increase in money supply = initial cash deposit × 1/RRR. In our example the RRR is 0.1, so the $ MONEY CREATION $ $1,000 + $900 + $810 = $2,710 You deposit $1,000 into your checking account. $100 HELD IN RESERVE Your $1,000 deposit minus $100 in reserves is loaned to Kai, who gives it to Lena. $900 AVAILABLE FOR LOANS Lena’s $900 deposit minus $90 in reserves is loaned to another customer. $90 HELD IN RESERVE At this point, the money supply has increased by $2,710. $810 AVAILABLE FOR LOANS >> Figure 9.23 Money is created as banks loan out money not kept in reserve. Analyze Charts How would an increase in the reserve requirement affect money creation in this example? 408 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="475"> <text><![CDATA[ MONEY MULTIPLIER FORMULA INITIAL CASH DEPOSIT 1 REQUIRED RESERVE RATIO (RRR) INCREASE IN MONEY SUPPLY EXAMPLE $1,000 1 0.1 $10,000 INCREASE IN MONEY SUPPLY >> Figure 9.24 The required reserve ratio is the key to the money multiplier formula. Analyze Charts What would the increase in money supply be if the RRR in this example were 0.2? money multiplier is 1 ÷ 0.1 = 10. (See Figure 9.24.) This means that the deposit of $1,000 can lead to a $10,000 increase in the money supply. As of 2012, banks in the United States had no reserve requirements on the first $12.4 million of demand deposit assets. They were required to hold 3 percent reserves on demand deposit assets between $12.4 and $79.5 million, and 10 percent on all demand deposit assets exceeding $79.5 million. In the real world, however, people hold some cash outside of the banking system, meaning that some funds leak out of the money multiplier process. Also, banks sometimes hold excess reserves, which are reserves greater than the required amounts. These excess reserves ensure that banks will always be able to meet their customers&apos; demands and the Fed&apos;s reserve requirements. The actual money multiplier effect in the United States is estimated to be between 2 and 3. The Federal Reserve has three basic tools to implement U.S. monetary policy and adjust the amount of money in the economy. These tools for creating money (or destroying it, if need be) are reserve requirements, the discount rate, and open market operations. dESCRIbE How do banks create money by going about their ordinary business? Monetary Tool #1: Reserve Requirements The simplest way for the Fed to adjust the amount of reserves in the banking system is to change the required reserve ratio. (See Figure 9.25.) The Fed&apos;s Board of Governors has sole responsibility over changes in reserve requirements. However, changing the reserve requirement is not the Fed&apos;s preferred tool. A reduction of the RRR frees up reserved money in banks, allowing them to make more loans. It also increases the money multiplier. Both effects will lead to a substantial expansion of the money supply. The process also works in reverse. Even a slight increase in the RRR forces banks to hold more money in reserves. This causes a contraction in the money supply. Although changing reserve requirements can be an effective means of changing the money supply, the Fed does not use this tool often because it is disruptive to the banking system. Even a small increase in the RRR would force banks to “call in” significant numbers of loans&ndash;that is, to require some borrowers to pay the entire outstanding balance of their loans sooner than planned. This can be difficult for the borrower. For this reason, the Fed rarely changes reserve requirements. 9.4 Monetary Policy Options 409 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="476"> <text><![CDATA[ CHECK UNDERSTANDING What effect would a reduction in the required reserve rate (RRR) have on banks? Monetary Tool #2: The Discount Rate In the past, the Fed lowered or raised the discount rate to increase or decrease the money supply. The discount rate is the interest rate the Federal Reserve charges on loans to financial institutions. Today, the discount rate is primarily used to ensure that sufficient funds are available in the economy. For example, during a financial crisis, there may not be enough funds in the banking system to provide the necessary loans to businesses and individuals. In that case, the ability of banks to borrow from the Federal Reserve at the discount rate provides a key safety net. Today, to implement monetary policy, the Federal Reserve primarily adjusts the federal funds rate, which is the interest rate that banks charge one another for loans. It does not actually set a new federal funds rate, however. Instead, it decides on a “target” level for the rate and takes steps to reach that target. These steps are part of the Fed&apos;s open market operations, which you will read about shortly. The Fed does set the discount rate, and it keeps this rate above the federal funds rate. Banks usually choose to borrow from one another at the funds rate. Only if they need additional reserves will they turn to the Federal Reserve and borrow at the higher discount rate. Changes in the federal funds and discount rates affect the cost of borrowing for banks or other financial institutions. In turn, these changes affect the prime rate. The prime rate is the rate banks charge on short-term loans to their best customers&ndash; usually large companies with good credit ratings. Ultimately, other interest rates follow, including the rates banks pay on savings accounts and the rates they charge for personal loans. The discount rate, federal funds rate, and prime rate are short-term rates. They determine the cost of borrowing for a few hours, days, or months, These rates have a limited impact on long-term economic growth. To influence long-term rates, the Fed must use other tools. IDENTIFY MAIN IDEAS What is the main tool that the Federal Reserve uses to adjust the money supply? RESERVE REQUIREMENTS AN INCREASE IN RESERVE REQUIREMENTS FORCES BANKS TO INCREASE RESERVES. $ BANKS REDUCE LENDING, CAUSING THE MONEY SUPPLY TO CONTRACT. REDUCED RESERVE REQUIREMENTS CAUSE BANKS TO DECREASE RESERVES. BANKS INCREASE LENDING, CAUSING THE MONEY SUPPLY TO EXPAND. $ >> Figure 9.25 The Fed uses reserve requirements to influence the money supply. Express Ideas Clearly Who or what is directly affected by a change in reserve requirements? Bounce to Activate Chart 410 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="477"> <text><![CDATA[ OPEN MARKET OPERATIONS WHEN THE FED SELLS REMOVE RESERVES BOND BUYERS FROM BANKS. $ BANKS CAUSING THE LENDING, REDUCE MONEY SUPPLY TO CONTRACT. WHEN THE FED PURCHASES ADD RESERVES BOND SELLERS TO BANKS. BANKS CAUSING THE LENDING, INCREASE MONEY SUPPLY TO EXPAND. $>> Figure 9.26 Open market operations involve the buying and selling of government securities. Identify Steps in a Process What steps would lead to a reduction in the money supply through open market operations? Bounce to Activate Chart Monetary Tool #3: Open Market Operations Open market operations are the buying and selling of government securities in order to alter the supply of money. (See Figure 9.26.) A security is a financial document, such as a stock certificate or bond, that represents ownership of corporate shares or the promise of repayment by a company or government. Today open market operations are by far the most important&ndash;and most often used&ndash;tool employed by the Fed to implement U.S. monetary policy. Purchasing Government Securities When the Federal Open Market Committee (FOMC) chooses to increase the money supply, it orders the trading desk at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York to purchase a certain quantity of government securities on the open market. The Federal Reserve Bank buys these securities with checks drawn on Federal Reserve funds. The bond sellers then deposit the money from the bond sales into their banks. As the Federal Reserve Board explains: [T]he bank now has more reserves than it wants. So the bank can lend these unwanted reserves to another bank in the federal funds market. Thus, the Fed&apos;s open market purchase increases the supply of reserves to the banking system, and the federal funds rate falls. &ndash;“What Are Open Market Operations?” Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco In this way, funds enter the banking system, setting in motion the money creation process described earlier. Selling Government Securities If the FOMC chooses to decrease the money supply, it must make an open market bond sale. In this case, the Fed sells government securities back to bond dealers, receiving from them checks drawn on their own banks. After the Fed processes these checks, the money is out of circulation. This operation reduces reserves in the banking system. In order to keep their reserves at the required levels, banks reduce their outstanding loans. The money multiplier process then works in reverse, resulting in a decline in the money supply that is greater than the value of the initial securities purchase. 9.4 Monetary Policy Options 411 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="478"> <text><![CDATA[ >> The economic crisis that occurred from 2007 to 2009 shook financial markets and prompted the Fed to take action. Targets To judge whether its open market operations are having the desired effect on the economy, the Fed periodically evaluates one or more economic targets. You have read about how the federal funds rate serves as the main target for interest rates. The Fed also keeps an eye on various measures of the money supply. Close analysis of these targets helps the Fed meet its goal of promoting a stable and prosperous economy. RECALL What action does the Federal Open Market Committee take if it wants to decrease the money supply? Using Monetary Policy Tools Open market operations are the most often used of the Federal Reserve&apos;s monetary policy tools. They can be conducted smoothly and on an ongoing basis to meet the Fed&apos;s goals. The Fed changes the discount rate less frequently. It usually follows a policy of keeping the discount rate in line with other interest rates in the economy in order to prevent excess borrowing by member banks from the Fed, which might threaten economic stability. Today, the Fed does not change reserve requirements to conduct monetary policy. Changing reserve requirements would force banks to make drastic changes in their plans. Open market operations or changes in the discount rate do not disrupt financial institutions. During the recent financial crisis of 2007–2009, the Fed took aggressive action to stabilize the financial system and promote economic growth. It used open market operations to lower the federal funds rate to nearly zero. The goal was to stimulate more lending and help boost economic activity, but it was still not enough to stem the crisis. So the Fed took an additional, unconventional step: It purchased longer-term securities from banks in the hope of bringing down long-term interest rates. This action pumped billions of dollars into the financial system and helped ease the crisis. But this action did come at a potential cost, as some economists worried that it would lead to inflation. In setting its monetary policy goals, the Federal Reserve keeps a close eye on market forces, studying inflation and business cycles to determine its policy. As you just read, changes in the money supply affect interest rates. You will find out more about how this process works shortly. IdENTIfy MAIN IdEAS Why are open market operations the Fed&apos;s preferred monetary policy tool? ASSESSMENT 1. Check Understanding What is money creation? 2. Summarize What are the three basic tools the Federal Reserve can use to affect the nation&apos;s money supply and implement monetary policy? 3. Hypothesize What would likely happen if the Fed changed reserve requirements? 4. Analyze Information Why do the discount rate, federal funds rate, and prime rate have a limited impact on the long-term growth of the economy? 5. Synthesize What was one benefit and one cost of the Fed&apos;s unusual step of buying long-term securities following the financial crisis of 2008– 2009? 412 TOPIC 9 Fiscal and Monetary Policy ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="479"> <text><![CDATA[ 9.5 Have you ever asked a parent for money&ndash;a raise in your allowance, perhaps, or cash to buy concert tickets? If so, you know that timing is everything. If, for example, your parent has just paid a huge bill for home or car repairs, you know that&apos;s the wrong time to ask for spending money. Timing is also critical to the Fed. Proper timing can support the Fed&apos;s effort to achieve economic growth and stability. Bad timing can impede it.>> A building project such as this takes months or years to plan and carry out. So, the monetary policy that influenced the decision to build may take even longer to have its full impact. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video The Effects of Monetary Policy The Basics of Monetary Policy How, then, does monetary policy influence macroeconomic performance&ndash;that is, the functioning of the entire economy? Monetary policy alters the supply of money. The supply of money, in turn, affects interest rates. Interest rates affect the level of investment and spending in the economy. (See Figure 9.27.) How Money Supply Impacts Interest Rates It is easy to see the cost of money if you are borrowing it. The cost&ndash;the price that you, as a borrower, pay&ndash;is the interest rate. Even if you spend your own money, the interest rate still affects you because you are giving up interest by not saving or investing. The market for money is like any other market. If the supply is higher, the price&ndash;the interest rate&ndash;is lower. If the supply is lower, the price is higher. In other words, when the money supply is high, interest rates are low. When the money supply is low, interest rates are high. How Interest Rates Affect Spending Recall that interest rates are important factors of spending in the economy. Lower interest NGSSS 9.5 SS.912.E.1.11, SS.912.E.3.6, SS.912.FL.3.6, SS.912.FL.5.8 >> Objectives Explain how monetary policy works. Describe how the timing of monetary policy can impact business cycles and key economic indicators. Analyze the costs and benefits of monetary policy in terms of economic growth. Contrast two general approaches to monetary policy. >> Key Terms easy money policy tight money policy inside lag outside lag monetarism Friedrich Hayek VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    </eBook>