<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <eBook>
  <page pageNumber="1"> <text><![CDATA[ Arthur O&apos;Sullivan, Ph.D. Steven M. Sheffrin, Ph.D. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="2"> <text><![CDATA[ Social Studies Reimagined [ To start, download the free Savvas BouncePages app on your smartphone or tablet. Simply search for the Savvas BouncePages app in your mobile app store. The app is available for Android and IOS (iPhone&reg;/iPad&reg;). ] Make your book come alive! Activate your digital course interactivities directly from the page. To launch the myStory video look for this icon. To activate more interactivities look for this icon. Bounce to Activate Illustr 1. AIM the camera over the image so it is easily viewable on your screen. 2. TAP the screen to scan the page. 3. BOUNCE the page to life by clicking the icon. Cover Image: Money in pocket. Oxford/Getty Images Acknowledgments appear at the end of the book, which constitute an extension of this copyright page. Copyright &copy; 2018 Savvas Learning Company LLC. All Rights Reserved. Printed in the United States of America. This publication is protected by copyright, and permission should be obtained from the publisher prior to any prohibited reproduction, storage in a retrieval system, or transmission in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical, photocopying, recording, or likewise. For information regarding permissions, request forms and the appropriate contacts within Savvas Learning Company Rights & Permissions Department., please visit www.savvas.com/permissions. SAVVAS is an exclusive trademark in the U.S. and/or other countries owned by Savvas Learning Company LLC. ISBN-13: 978-0-32-891456-2 ISBN-10: 0-32-891456-8 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 VOUD 19 18 17 16 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="3"> <text><![CDATA[ Authors, Consultants, Partners [ Authors ] Arthur O&apos;Sullivan, Ph.D. Arthur O&apos;Sullivan is a Professor of Economics at Lewis and Clark College in Portland, Oregon, where he teaches microeconomics and urban economics. After receiving his B.S. degree in economics at the University of Oregon, he spent two years in the Peace Corps, working with city planners in the Philippines. He received his Ph.D. degree in economics from Princeton University in 1981 and has taught at the University of California, Davis, and Oregon State University. Professor O&apos;Sullivan&apos;s research explores economic issues concerning urban land use, environmental protection, and public policy. His articles appear in many economics journals, including the Journal of Urban Economics, the Journal of Environmental Economics and Management, the National Tax Journal, the Journal of Public Economics, and the Journal of Law and Economics. Steven M. Sheffrin, Ph.D. Steven M. Sheffrin is Professor of Economics and Director of the Murphy Institute at Tulane University in New Orleans. Previously, he was Dean of the Division of Social Sciences and Professor of Economics at the University of California, Davis. He has been a visiting professor at Nuffield College, University of Oxford; the London School of Economics and Political Science; Princeton University; and Nanyang Technological University, Singapore. He holds a BA from the College of Social Sciences, Wesleyan University, and a Ph.D. in economics from Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Professor Sheffrin is the author of numerous books and articles in the fields of macroeconomics, public finance, and international economics. [ Program Consultant ] Dr. Kathy Swan is an Associate Professor of Curriculum and Instruction at the University of Kentucky. Her research focuses on standards-based technology integration, authentic intellectual work, and documentary-making in the social studies classroom. Swan has been a four-time recipient of the National Technology Leadership Award in Social Studies Education. She is also the advisor for the Social Studies Assessment, Curriculum, and Instruction Collaborative (SSACI) at CCSSO. [ Program Partners ] NBC Learn, the educational arm of NBC News, develops original stories for use in the classroom and makes archival NBC News stories, images, and primary source documents available on demand to teachers, students, and parents. NBC Learn partnered with Savvas to produce the myStory videos that support this program.Constitutional Rights Foundation is a nonprofit, nonpartisan organization focused on educating students about the importance of civic participation in a democratic society. Constitutional Rights Foundation is the lead contributor to the development of the Civic Discussion Topic Inquiries for this program. Constitutional Rights Foundation is also the provider of the Civic Action Project (CAP) for the Economics and Magruder’s American Government programs. CAP is a project-based learning model for civics, government, and economics courses. iii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="4"> <text><![CDATA[ Reviewers & Academic Consultants Savvas Economics was developed especially for you and your students. The story of its creation began with a three- day Innovation Lab in which teachers, historians, students, and authors came together to imagine our ideal Social Studies teaching and learning experiences. We refined the plan with a series of teacher roundtables that shaped this new approach to ensure your students&apos; mastery of content and skills. A dedicated team, made up of Savvas authors, content experts, and social studies teachers, worked to bring our collective vision into reality. Kathy Swan, Professor of Education and architect of the new College, Career, and Civic Life (C3) Framework, served as our expert advisor on curriculum and instruction. Savvas would like to extend a special thank you to all of the teachers who helped guide the development of this program. We gratefully acknowledge your efforts to realize Next Generation Social Studies teaching and learning that will prepare American students for college, careers, and active citizenship. [ Program Advisors ] Campaign for the Civic Mission of Schools is a coalition of over 70 national civic learning, education, civic engagement, and business groups committed to improving the quality and quantity of civic learning in American schools. The Campaign served as an advisor on this program. Buck Institute for Education is a nonprofit organization dedicated to helping teachers implement the effective use of Project-Based Learning in their classrooms. Buck Institute staff consulted on the Project-Based Learning Topic Inquiries for this program. [ Florida Academic Reviewers ] Gina Carlisle Robert McLaren Former Teacher at William R. Boone High School Orlando, Bethany Crawford Forest High School Ocala, Florida John Crawford Forest High School Ocala, Florida Robert McLaren Brevard Public Schools (Retired) Viera, Florida John M Pellegrino Faculty Emeritus Fort Lauderdale High School Fort Lauderdale, Florida Therese Schultz Nourse, Ed.D. Marion Virtual School Ocala, Florida Sally Weaver Marion County Public Schools Ocala, Florida [ Program Academic Consultants ] Barbara Brown Director of Outreach College of Arts and Sciences African Studies Center Boston University Boston, Massachusetts William Childs Professor of History Emeritus The Ohio State University Columbus, Ohio Jennifer Giglielmo Associate Professor of History Smith College Northhampton, Massachusetts Joanne Connor Green Professor, Department Chair Political Science Texas Christian University Fort Worth, Texas Ramdas Lamb, Ph.D. Associate Professor of Religion University of Hawaii at Manoa Honolulu, Hawaii Huping Ling Changjiang Scholar Chair Professor Professor of History Truman State University Kirksville, Missouri Jeffery Long, Ph.D. Professor of Religion and Asian Studies Elizabethtown College Elizabethtown, Pennsylvania Gordon Newby Professor of Islamic, Jewish and Comparative Studies Department of Middle Eastern and South Asian Studies Emory University Atlanta, Georgia Mark Peterson Associate Professor Department of Asian and Near Eastern Languages Brigham Young University Provo, Utah William Pitts Professor, Department of Religion Baylor University Waco, Texas Benjamin Ravid Professor Emeritus of Jewish History Department of Near Eastern and Judaic Studies Brandeis University Waltham, Massachusetts Harpreet Singh College Fellow Department of South Asian Studies Harvard University Cambridge, Massachusetts Christopher E. Smith, J.D., Ph.D. Professor Michigan State University MSU School of Criminal Justice East Lansing, Michigan John Voll Professor of Islamic History Georgetown University Washington, D.C. Michael R. Wolf Associate Professor Department of Political Science Indiana University-Purdue University Fort Wayne Fort Wayne, Indiana]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="5"> <text><![CDATA[ Social Studies Reimagined Social studies is more than dots on a map or dates on a timeline. It’s where we’ve been and where we’re going. It’s stories from the past and our stories today. And in today’s fast-paced, interconnected world, it’s essential. Welcome to the next generation of Florida social studies! Savvas&apos;s new Florida social studies program was created in collaboration with Florida educators, social studies experts, and students. The program is based on Savvas&apos;s FL NGSSS Mastery. The System uses tested best practices, FL NGSSS expectations, technology, and a four-part framework&ndash;Connect, Investigate, Synthesize, and Demonstrate&ndash;to prepare students to be college- and career-ready while mastering FL NGSSS. The System includes: &bull;100% coverage of the Florida Next Generation Sunshine State Standards. &bull;FL NGSSS-focused table of contents that will save teachers time and improve pacing. Higher-level content that gives support to access complex text, acquire core content knowledge, and tackle rigorous questions. &bull;Inquiry-focused Projects, Civic Discussions, and Document Analysis activities that develop content and skills mastery in preparation for real-world challenges. &bull;Digital content on Savvas Realize that is dynamic, flexible, and uses the power of technology to bring social studies to life. Connect Make meaning personal Investigate Acquire knowledge and skills Demonstrate Show understanding Synthesize Practice knowledge and skills » Go online to learn more and see the program overview video. The digital course on Realize! The program&apos;s digital course on Realize puts rich and engaging content, embedded assessments with instant data, and flexible tools at your fingertips. v ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="6"> <text><![CDATA[ Connect: Make Meaning Personal CONNECT! Florida students will begin the Savvas Florida NGSSS Mastery System by engaging in the topic story and connecting it to your own lives. FL NGSSS Preview&ndash;Each Topic opens with FL NGSSS, allowing students to preview expected learning outcomes. Students will also find FL NGSSS at the beginning, throughout, and at the end of every lesson. FL NGSSS process skills are closely integrated within the content. >> Instruction begins with an Essential Question. These thought-provoking questions engage students and introduce the Topic. [ ESSENTIAL QUESTION ] Who benefits from the free market economy? 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems 2 Next Generation Sunshine State Standards AUDIOVIDEO WRITINGETEXT ASSESSMENTGAMESACTIVITY PDF Go ONLINEfor digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS >> Two young men stand and smile at their bicycle shop. [ ESSENTIAL QUESTION ] Who benefits from the free market economy? SS.912.E.1.3, SS.912.E.1.8, SS.912.E.2.1, SS.912.E.2.11, SS.912.E.2.12, LAFS.1112.RH.1.1, LAFS.1112.RH.1.2, LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, LAFS.1112.RH.3.8, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.SL.1.1, LAFS.1112.WHST.2.4 Bounce to Activate My Story VideoLeslie Bradshaw and the importance of innovation. Enduring Understandings &bull; Becausesocietiesanswerthekeyeconomicquestionsdifferently,multipleeconomicsystemshavedeveloped. &bull; Competitionhelpsregulatemarketsandgivesproducersincentivestomakewhatconsumerswant. &bull; Becausepuremarketandpurecentrallyplannedeconomieshavedrawbacks,nationstendtohavemixedeconomies. &bull; UndertheAmericanfreeenterprisesystem,thegovernmentpreserveseconomicfreedomswhileprotectingthepublicinterestthroughlimitedregulationoftheeconomy. Bounce to Activate My Story VideoLeslie Bradshaw and the importance of innovation. >> Developed in partnership with NBCLearn, the My Story videos help students connect to the Topic content by hearing the personal story of an individual whose life is related to the content students are about to learn. vi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="7"> <text><![CDATA[ Investigate: Acquire Knowledge and Skills INVESTIGATE! Step two of the FL NGSSS Mastery System allows Florida students to investigate the topic story through a number of engaging features as they learn the content. >> Active Classroom Strategies integrated in the daily lesson plans help to increase in-class participation, raise energy levels and attentiveness, all while engaging in the story. These 5-15 minute activities have you use what you have learned to draw, write, speak, and decide. >> Interactive Primary Source Galleries: Use primary source image galleries throughout the lesson to see, analyze, and interact with images that tie to the topic story content. vii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="8"> <text><![CDATA[ Investigate >> Feel like you are a part of the story with interactive 3-D models. caring for the sick. An aircraft plant manufactures only airplanes&ndash;not airplanes, refrigerators, and bicycles. Specialization leads to efficiency in the use of capital, land, and labor. It is better for people to learn one task or a few tasks very well than to learn a little about many tasks. Because they concentrate on one or a few tasks, they can do their work more efficiently, saving resources by avoiding waste. For this reason, the top performers in most fields are specialists who have worked hard to sharpen their particular skills. Specialization also benefits businesses. Focusing on a limited number of related products or services allows them to use their limited capital and labor more efficiently. Buying and Selling People in primitive cultures had to make everything they needed from materials they gathered from nature. Even in more recent times, some people strive for self-sufficiency. However, because most of us in the modern world specialize in producing just a few goods or services, we need a mechanism that allows us to sell what we have produced and to buy what we want. Figure 2.3 illustrates this concept. In a modern market-based economy, people typically earn income by specializing in particular jobs. They then use this income to buy the products that they want to consume. IdentIfy MaIn Ideas Why do markets exist? Elements of a Free Market Economy In a free market economy, answers to the three basic economic questions are made by voluntary exchange in markets. The choices made by individuals determine what gets made, how it is made, and how much people can consume of the goods and services produced. Individuals and businesses make their own decisions about what to buy or sell. Market economies are also called capitalist economies because the capital that entrepreneurs invest in businesses is a vital part of the system. In a free market system, individuals and privately owned businesses own the factors of production, make what they want, and buy what they want. In other words, individuals answer the three basic >> Figure 2.3 This farmer specializes in raising one crop, using income from its sale to purchase equipment and other goods. Test Conclusions What evidence can you see that the farmer earns income from the specialized production of one crop? questions of what to produce, how to produce it, and who consumes what is produced. The United States has a free market economic system. This system is commonly referred to as the United States free enterprise system. In general, free enterprise, free market, and capitalism are all synonyms for the economic system of the United States. Households and Firms The participants in a free market economy are households and firms. A household is a person or group of people living in a single residence. Households own the factors of production&ndash;land, labor, and capital. They are also consumers of goods and services. A business, or firm, is an organization that uses resources to produce a product or service, which it then sells. Firms transform inputs, or factors of production, into outputs, or goods and services. We can represent the exchanges that take place in a free market economy in a diagram called a circular flow model. Look at Figure 2.4. The diagram shows how households and firms exchange money, resources, and products in the marketplace. The inner ring of the diagram represents the flow of resources and products. Note that both households and firms are resource owners in this model. The outer ring represents the flow of money. Factor and Product Markets As you can see from the lower half of the model, firms purchase factors of production from households. This arena of exchange is called the factor market. An example of this is when firms purchase or rent land. They hire workers, paying them wages or salaries for their labor. They also borrow money from households to purchase capital, paying households interest or profits in return. Now look at the top half of the circular flow model. The arena in which households buy the goods and services that firms produce is the product market. So, when you buy food at a supermarket, you are taking part in the product market physical flow. If you follow the rings of the diagram, you will see that in the product market, households purchase the products made by firms with the money they receive from firms in the factor market. The monetary and physical flows through the factor and product markets are truly circular. express Ideas Clearly What is the role of firms in the free market economy? >> Figure 2.4 The circular flow model shows the interaction between households and fi rms in a free market. Analyze Charts What is the primary item that changes hands in the monetary flow? Bounce to Activate IllustrationBounce to Activate 3D Model32 tOpIC 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems 2.2 Free Markets 33 >> Continue to investigate the topic story through dynamic interactive maps. Build map skills while covering the essential standards. >> Learn content by reading narrative text online or in a printed Student Edition. Synthesize: Practice Knowledge and Skills  SYNTHESIZE! In step three of the Mastery System, pause to reflect on what you learn and revisit an essential question. viii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="9"> <text><![CDATA[ Demonstrate: Show Understanding DEMONSTRATE! The final step of the FL NGSSS Mastery System is to demonstrate understanding of the NGSSS. >> The digital course on Realize! The program&apos;s digital course on Realize puts engaging content, embedded assessments, instant data, and flexible tools at your fingertips. >> FL NGSSS Assessment. At the end of each lesson and topic, demonstrate understanding through Lesson Quizzes, Topic Tests, and Topic Inquiry performance assessments. The System provides remediation and enrichment recommendations based on your individual performance towards mastery. >> Class and Data features on Realize make it easy to use students&apos; FL NGSSS mastery data to show if time is needed to re-teach or move ahead. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="10"> <text><![CDATA[ Table of Contents TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics 1 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.1 SS.912.E.1.2 SS.912.E.1.7 SS.912.E.2.3 LAFS.1112.RH.2.6 LAFS.1112.RH.3.7 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10 myStory Video: Fundamentals of Economics 1.1 Scarcity ...............................................................................................................4 Interactive Flipped Video: Needs Versus Wants Interactive Map: Scarcity Around the World Interactive Chart: What Kind of Business Would You Create? 1.2 Opportunity Cost and Trade-Offs ...............................................................9 Interactive Flipped Video: Opportunity Costs Interactive Gallery: Trade-Offs Interactive Chart: What Would You Choose? 1.3 Production Possibilities Curves............................................................... 13 Interactive Flipped Video: Trade-Offs Interactive Chart: Production Possibilities Interactive 3-D Model: The Law of Increasing Costs Review and Assessment............................................................................. 18 [ To activate your digital course interactivities download the free Savvas BouncePages app on your smartphone or tablet. Simply search for the Savvas BouncePages app in your mobile app store. The app is available for Android and IOS (iPhone&reg;/iPad&reg;). ] x ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="11"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Access your Digital Lesson TOPIC 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems 22 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.3 SS.912.E.1.8 SS.912.E.1.11 SS.912.E.2.1 SS.912.E.2.11 SS.912.E.2.12 LAFS.1112.RH.1.1 LAFS.1112.RH.1.2 LAFS.1112.RH.2.6 LAFS.1112.RH.3.8 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.SL.1.1 LAFS.1112.WHST.2.4 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 myStory Video: Leslie Bradshaw, Guiding Innovation 2.1 The Three Key Economic Questions....................................................... 26 Interactive Flipped Video: Answering Key Economic Questions Interactive Chart: Answering the Three Basic Economic Questions 2.2 Free Markets .................................................................................................. 31 Interactive Flipped Video: Competition Interactive Illustration: Specialization and Productivity Interactive 3-D Model: The Circular Flow Model of a Market Economy Interactive Gallery: The Self-Regulating Nature of the Marketplace 2.3 Centrally Planned Economies .................................................................. 39 Interactive Flipped Video: Case Study, China Interactive Chart: Comparing Economic Systems Interactive Gallery: Central Planning in Two Communists Systems 2.4 Mixed Economies.......................................................................................... 44 Interactive Flipped Video: Mixed Economies Interactive Chart: Circular Flow Model of a Mixed Economy Interactive Gallery: Examining Different Economic Systems 2.5 Benefits of Free Enterprise ....................................................................... 50 Interactive Flipped Video: What is Free Enterprise? Interactive Chart: Basic Characteristics of Free Enterprise Interactive Timeline: Major Federal Regulatory Agencies 2.6 Supporting Economic Growth .................................................................. 57 Interactive Flipped Video: Supporting Economic Growth Interactive Graph: Tracking Business Cycles Interactive Gallery: Analyzing Technology and Productivity 2.7 Public Goods and Externalities................................................................ 62 Interactive Flipped Video: How the Economy Works Interactive Gallery: Public Goods Interactive Before and After: Externalities Review and Assessment............................................................................. 70 xi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="12"> <text><![CDATA[ Table of Contents TOPIC 3 Demand, Supply, and Prices 74 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.4 SS.912.E.1.7 SS.912.E.2.4 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.WHST.2.4 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10 MAFS.K12.MP.5.1 myStory Video: Principles of Supply and Demand 3.1 Fundamentals of Demand ......................................................................... 78 Interactive Flipped Video: What is Demand? Interactive Chart: Demand in Action Interactive Chart: Interpreting a Demand Schedule and Graph 3.2 Shifts in Demand .......................................................................................... 83 Interactive Flipped Video: Shifts in Demand Interactive Graph: Graphing Changes in Demand Interactive Gallery: Non-Price Determinants That Influence Demand 3.3 Elasticity of Demand ................................................................................... 88 Interactive Flipped Video: Elasticity of Demand Interactive Graph: Understanding Elastic and Inelastic Demand Interactive Gallery: Factors That Affect Elasticity of Demand 3.4 Fundamentals of Supply ............................................................................ 95 Interactive Flipped Video: The Law of Supply Interactive Chart: Interpreting a Supply Schedule and Graph Interactive Chart: Understanding Elasticity and Inelasticity of Supply 3.5 Costs of Production .................................................................................... 101 Interactive Flipped Video: Marginal Changes Interactive Graph: Changes in Marginal Returns Interactive Illustration: Fixed, Variable, and Total Costs Interactive Chart: Understanding Production Costs 3.6 Changes in Supply ..................................................................................... 108 Interactive Flipped Video: Changes in Supply Interactive Gallery: Non-Price Determinants That Influence Supply 3.7 Equilibrium and Price Controls ............................................................. 114 Interactive Flipped Video: Equilibrium and Disequilibrium Interactive Chart: Interpreting a Supply and Demand Schedule and Graph Interactive Graph: Understanding Price, Shortage, and Surplus xii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="13"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Access your Digital Lesson 3.8 Changes in Market Equilibrium ............................................................ 121 Interactive Flipped Video: Market Equilibrium Interactive Graph: Analyzing Change in Demand Interactive Gallery: From Shortage to Equilibrium 3.9 Prices at Work.............................................................................................. 127 Interactive Flipped Video: Prices at Work Interactive Gallery: Rationing and Black Markets Interactive Chart: Describing Advantages of the Price System Review and Assessment........................................................................... 134 TOPIC 4 Competition and Market Structures 138 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.6 SS.912.E.1.8 SS.912.E.2.1 SS.912.E.2.4 SS.912.E.2.6 LAFS.1112.RH.1.3 LAFS.1112.RH.2.6 LAFS.1112.RH.3.7 LAFS.1112.RH.3.9 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.WHST.2.4 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10 myStory Video: Andrew Carnegie, The Law of Competition 4.1 Pure Competition........................................................................................ 142 Interactive Flipped Video: What is Perfect Competition? Interactive Chart: Characteristics of Competition Interactive Chart: Starting a Business 4.2 Monopolies.................................................................................................... 147 Interactive Flipped Video: How Monopolies Form Interactive Gallery: Analyzing Monopolies in America Interactive Graph: How Monopolies Set Output and Price 4.3 Monopolistic Competition and Oligopoly ........................................... 155 Interactive Flipped Video: Monopolistic Competition Interactive Gallery: Non-price Competition Interactive Illustration: Comparing Types of Competition 4.4 Government Regulation and Competition ......................................... 162 Interactive Flipped Video: Government Regulation Interactive Cartoon: Analyzing a Monopoly Cartoon Interactive Timeline: The History of AT&T Review and Assessment........................................................................... 168 xiii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="14"> <text><![CDATA[ Table of Contents TOPIC 5 Business and Labor 172 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.5 SS.912.E.1.9 SS.912.E.2.3 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 myStory Video: Melissa Grows a Business 5.1 Sole Proprietorships................................................................................... 176 Interactive Flipped Video: What are Sole Proprietorships? Interactive Gallery: Looking at Sole Proprietorships Interactive Chart: Analyzing Sole Proprietorships 5.2 Partnerships and Franchises .................................................................. 181 Interactive Flipped Video: Partnerships Interactive Chart: Analyzing Partnerships Interactive Illustration: Understanding Business Franchises 5.3 Corporations................................................................................................. 187 Interactive Flipped Video: The Corporation Interactive Chart: Analyzing the Corporate Form of Ownership Interactive Illustration: Understanding Vertical Integration 5.4 Nonprofit Organizations .......................................................................... 193 Interactive Flipped Video: Nonprofit Organizations Interactive Chart: Describing Types of Cooperatives Interactive Gallery: Understanding Nonprofit Organizations 5.5 The Labor Force........................................................................................... 198 Interactive Flipped Video: Labor Interactive Gallery: Comparing Jobs in a Changing Economy Interactive Graph: Analyzing Data About Women at Work 5.6 Labor and Wages......................................................................................... 206 Interactive Flipped Video: Supply and Demand for Labor Interactive Graph: Determining the Equilibrium Wage Interactive Gallery: Exploring Factors Affecting Wages 5.7 Labor Unions ................................................................................................ 213 Interactive Flipped Video: Unions Interactive Chart: Analyzing the Decline of Labor Unions Interactive Illustration: Collective Bargaining in Action Review and Assessment........................................................................... 220 xiv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="15"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Access your Digital Lesson TOPIC 6 Money, Banking, and Financial Markets 224 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.10 SS.912.E.1.11 SS.912.E.1.13 SS.912.E.1.14 SS.912.E.1.15 SS.912.E.1.16 SS.912.E.2.3 SS.912.E.2.10 LAFS.1112.RH.1.2 LAFS.1112.RH.2.4 LAFS.1112.RH.2.5 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.SL.1.1 LAFS.1112.SL.2.4 LAFS.1112.WHST.1.1 LAFS.1112.WHST.1.2 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 myStory Video: Warren Buffet, Investing for Value 6.1 The Role of Money...................................................................................... 228 Interactive Flipped Video: Money Interactive Before and After: Comparing Barter and Money Interactive Gallery: Investigating the Six Characteristics of Money 6.2 Changes in American Banking .............................................................. 234 Interactive Flipped Video: Banking Interactive Timeline: Important Events in Banking History Interactive Gallery: Analyzing the Financial Crisis of 2008 6.3 The Federal Reserve System .................................................................. 245 Interactive Flipped Video: The Federal Reserve Interactive Illustration: Examining the Structure of the Fed Interactive Illustration: The Check Clearing Process 6.4 The Functions of Modern Banks............................................................ 255 Interactive Flipped Video: Financial Institutions Interactive Chart: Calculate Compound Interest Interactive Chart: Comparing Types of Loans 6.5 Investing ....................................................................................................... 263 Interactive Flipped Video: Investing Interactive Illustration: Linking Savers and Investors Interactive Chart: Identifying Types of Risk 6.6 Bonds and Other Financial Assets........................................................ 270 Interactive Flipped Video: Bonds Interactive Chart: Identifying Types of Bonds 6.7 Stocks ............................................................................................................. 277 Interactive Flipped Video: Stocks Interactive Timeline: Investigating the History of the Dow Interactive Illustration: How to Read an Online Stock Report Review and Assessment........................................................................... 286 xv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="16"> <text><![CDATA[ Table of Contents TOPIC 7 Economic Performance and Challenges 344 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.10 SS.912.E.1.12 SS.912.E.2.1 SS.912.E.2.5 SS.912.E.2.7 SS.912.E.3.1 SS.912.E.3.2 MAFS.K12.MP.5.1 LAFS.1112.RH.1.1 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.SL.1.3 LAFS.1112.WHST.1.1 LAFS.1112.WHST.1.2 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 myStory Video: Unemployment, Measuring the Health of the Economy 7.1 Gross Domestic Product ........................................................................... 294 Interactive Flipped Video: What is GDP? Interactive Chart: What is Gross Domestic Product? Interactive Graph: Interpreting the Impact of Events on U.S. GDP 7.2 Business Cycles........................................................................................... 301 Interactive Flipped Video: Business Cycles Interactive Graph: Analyzing a Business Cycle Interactive Chart: Analyzing a Recession 7.3 Economic Growth ....................................................................................... 310 Interactive Flipped Video: Technology&apos;s Role in Driving Growth Interactive Graph: Explain Capital Deepening Interactive Gallery: Analyzing Causes of Economic Growth 7.4 Unemployment............................................................................................ 317 Interactive Flipped Video: What is Unemployment? Interactive Chart: Determining Types of Unemployment Interactive Graph: Interpreting Unemployment Data 7.5 Inflation and Deflation ............................................................................. 323 Interactive Flipped Video: What is Inflation? Interactive Chart: Analyzing the Wage-Price Spiral Interactive Gallery: Interpreting Causes and Effects of Inflation 7.6 Poverty and Income Distribution.......................................................... 329 Interactive Flipped Video: Finding Solutions to Poverty Interactive Graph: Analyzing Poverty Rates Interactive Timeline: Changes in Anti-Poverty Policies Review and Assessment........................................................................... 340 xvi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="17"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Access your Digital Lesson TOPIC 8 Taxes and Spending 344 NGSSS SS.912.E.2.8 HE.912.C.2.4 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1 TOPIC 9 myStory Video: Income, Taxes and Spending 8.1 Understanding Taxes ................................................................................ 348 Interactive Flipped Video: National Tax Rates in the U.S. and Elsewhere Interactive Chart: Exploring the Constitution and Taxation Interactive Chart: Progressive, Regressive, and Proportional Taxation 8.2 Federal Taxes............................................................................................... 354 Interactive Flipped Video: The Structure of National Revenues Interactive Graph: Analyzing Historical Changes in Federal Receipts Interactive Gallery: Examining Tax Deductions and Incentives 8.3 Federal Spending ....................................................................................... 360 Interactive Flipped Video: Entitlements and the National Budget Interactive Gallery: Analyzing Categories of the Federal Budget Interactive Chart: Exploring Major Entitlement Programs 8.4 State and Local Taxes and Spending.................................................... 365 Interactive Flipped Video: State Taxes and Spending in Different States Interactive Gallery: Analyzing State Spending Interactive Graph: Examining State and Local Revenues Review and Assessment........................................................................... 372 Fiscal and Monetary Policy 376 NGSSS SS.912.E.1.10 SS.912.E.1.11 SS.912.E.2.9 SS.912.E.3.6 ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1 LAFS.1112.RH.1.3 LAFS.1112.RH.2.6 LAFS.1112.RH.3.7 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.SL.1.2 LAFS.1112.SL.1.3 LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 myStory Video: John Maynard Keynes, Influencing the Economy 9.1 The Federal Budget and Fiscal Policy.................................................. 380 Interactive Flipped Video: Fiscal Policy Basics Interactive Chart: The Budget Process Interactive Graph: The Effects of Fiscal Policy 9.2 Fiscal Policy Options................................................................................. 388 Interactive Flipped Video: Fiscal Policy Options Interactive Graph: Analyzing the Laffer Curve Interactive Timeline: Exploring Fiscal Policy in a Changing Economy xvii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="18"> <text><![CDATA[ Table of Contents 9.3 The National Debt and Deficits.............................................................. 400 Interactive Flipped Video: What is the National Debt? Interactive Gallery: Budget Deficits and Federal Debt Interactive Graph: Analyzing Federal Spending Priorities 9.4 Monetary Policy Options.......................................................................... 407 Interactive Flipped Video: Monetary Policy Tools Interactive Chart: Analyzing Interest Rate Effect Interactive Chart: Affecting the Money Supply 9.5 The Effects of Monetary Policy.............................................................. 413 Interactive Flipped Video: Timing Monetary Policy Interactive Chart: Analyzing Easy Money and Tight Money Interactive Gallery: How Monetary Policy Affects the Economy Review and Assessment........................................................................... 422 TOPIC 10 Trade, Development, and Globalization 426 NGSSS SS.912.E.2.12 SS.912.E.3.2 SS.912.E.3.3 SS.912.E.3.4 SS.912.E.3.5 SS.912.G.2.2 SS.912.G.3.3 SS.912.G.4.4 LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 LAFS.1112.SL.1.3 LAFS.1112.SL.1.3 myStory Video: North and South Korea, Comparative Paths to Development 10.1 Why Nations Trade ................................................................................... 430 Interactive Flipped Video: Absolute and Comparative Advantage Interactive Gallery: Identifying Resources and Specialization Interactive Map: Comparing U.S. Trading Partners 10.2 Trade Barriers and Agreements ........................................................... 438 Interactive Flipped Video: Costs and Benefits of Free Trade Interactive Map: Analyzing U.S. Trade with Canada and Mexico Interactive Illustration: Examining Globalization – the Auto Industry 10.3 Exchange Rates and Trade..................................................................... 447 Interactive Flipped Video: Foreign Trade in the American Economy Interactive Chart: Contrasting the Effects of Exchange Rates Interactive Graph: Analyzing the Impact of U.S. Exports and Imports xviii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="19"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Access your Digital Lesson 10.4 Development .............................................................................................. 455 Interactive Flipped Video: Success Stories in National Development Interactive Gallery: Interpreting Indicators of Development Interactive Chart: Identifying Patterns of Development 10.5 Growth, Resources, and Development ............................................... 460 Interactive Flipped Video: Economic Development Interactive Graph: Categorizing U.S. Foreign Aid Interactive Gallery: Identifying the Functions of World Organizations 10.6 Changing Economies ............................................................................... 468 Interactive Flipped Video: Building Economies Interactive Timeline: Summarizing Russia&apos;s Transition to a Market Economy Interactive Graph: Analyzing Economic Growth in China 10.7 Globalization .............................................................................................. 475 Interactive Flipped Video: Agriculture Around the World Interactive Chart: Defining the Elements of Globalization Interactive Gallery: Investigating World Migration Review and Assessment........................................................................... 486 United States Constitution......................................................... 490 Declaration of Independence..................................................... 514 Personal Finance .......................................................................... 516 21st Century Skills ....................................................................... 562 Atlas................................................................................................ 594 Glossary.......................................................................................... 611 Spanish Glossary .......................................................................... 621 Index ............................................................................................... 632 Acknowledgments....................................................................... 655 xix ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="20"> <text><![CDATA[ Digital Resources Many types of digital resources help you investigate the topics in this course. You&apos;ll find biographies, primary sources, maps, and more. These resources will help bring the topics to life. Core Concepts Culture &bull; What Is Culture? &bull; Families and Societies &bull; Language &bull; Religion &bull; The Arts &bull; Cultural Diffusion and Change &bull; Science and Technology Economics &bull; Economics Basics &bull; Economic Process &bull; Economic Systems &bull; Economic Development &bull; Trade &bull; Money Management Geography &bull; The Study of Earth &bull; Geography&apos;s Five Themes &bull; Ways to Show Earth&apos;s Surface &bull; Understanding Maps &bull; Earth in Space &bull; Time and Earth&apos;s Rotation &bull; Forces on Earth&apos;s Surface &bull; Forces Inside Earth &bull; Climate and Weather &bull; Temperature &bull; Water and Climate &bull; Air Circulation and Precipitation &bull; Types of Climate &bull; Ecosystems &bull; Environment and Resources &bull; Land Use &bull; People&apos;s Impact on the Environment &bull; Population &bull; Migration &bull; Urbanization Government and Civics &bull; Foundations of Government &bull; Political Systems &bull; Political Structures &bull; Conflict and Cooperation &bull; Citizenship History &bull; How Do Historians Study History? &bull; Measuring Time &bull; Historical Sources &bull; Archaeology and Other Sources &bull; Historical Maps Personal Finance &bull; Your Fiscal Fitness: An Introduction &bull; Budgeting &bull; Checking &bull; Investments &bull; Savings and Retirement &bull; Credit and Debt &bull; Risk Management &bull; Consumer Smarts &bull; After High School &bull; Taxes and Income Landmark Supreme Court Cases &bull; Korematsu v. United States &bull; Marbury v. Madison &bull; McCulloch v. Maryland &bull; Gibbons v. Ogden &bull; Worcester v. Georgia &bull; Dred Scott v. Sandford &bull; Plessy v. Ferguson &bull; Schenck v. United States &bull; Brown v. Board of Education &bull; Engel v. Vitale &bull; Sweatt v. Painter &bull; Mapp v. Ohio &bull; Hernandez v. Texas &bull; Gideon v. Wainwright &bull; Wisconsin v. Yoder &bull; Miranda v. Arizona &bull; White v. Regester &bull; Tinker v. Des Moines School District &bull; Roe v. Wade &bull; Baker v. Carr &bull; Grutter v. Bollinger &bull; Edgewood v. Kirby &bull; Texas v. Johnson &bull; National Federation of Independent Businesses et al. v. Sebelius et al. &bull; Mendez v. Westminster and Delgado v. Bastrop ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="21"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Access your Digital Lesson Interactive Primary Sources &bull; Code of Hammurabi &bull; Psalm 23 &bull; The Republic, Plato &bull; Politics, Aristotle &bull; Edicts, Asoka &bull; Analects, Confucius &bull; First Letter to the Corinthians, Paul &bull; The Quran &bull; The Magna Carta &bull; Travels, Ibn Battuta &bull; The Destruction of the Indies, Bartolomé de Las Casas &bull; Mayflower Compact &bull; English Petition of Right &bull; English Bill of Rights &bull; Two Treatises of Government, John Locke &bull; The Spirit of Laws, Baron de Montesquieu &bull; The Social Contract, Jean-Jacques Rousseau &bull; The Interesting Narrative of the Life of Olaudah Equiano &bull; “Give Me Liberty or Give Me Death,” Patrick Henry &bull; “Remember the Ladies,” Abigail Adams &bull; Common Sense, Thomas Paine &bull; Declaration of Independence &bull; Virginia Declaration of Rights &bull; Virginia Statute for Religious Freedom, Thomas Jefferson &bull; “To His Excellency, General Washington,” Phillis Wheatley &bull; Articles of Confederation &bull; Anti-Federalist Papers &bull; The Federalist No. 10, James Madison &bull; The Federalist No. 39, James Madison &bull; The Federalist No. 51 &bull; The Federalist No. 78, Alexander Hamilton &bull; Northwest Ordinance &bull; Iroquois Constitution &bull; Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen &bull; Farewell Address, George Washington &bull; Mexican Federal Constitution of 1824 &bull; State Colonization Law of 1825 &bull; Law of April 6, 1830 &bull; Debate Over Nullification, Webster and Calhoun &bull; Turtle Bayou Resolutions &bull; Democracy in America, Alexis de Tocqueville &bull; 1836 Victory or Death Letter from the Alamo, Travis &bull; Texas Declaration of Independence &bull; Declaration of Sentiments and Resolutions &bull; “Ain&apos;t I a Woman?,” Sojourner Truth &bull; Uncle Tom&apos;s Cabin, Harriet Beecher Stowe &bull; “A House Divided,” Abraham Lincoln &bull; First Inaugural Address, Abraham Lincoln &bull; Declaration of Causes: February 2, 1861 &bull; Emancipation Proclamation, Abraham Lincoln &bull; Gettysburg Address, Abraham Lincoln &bull; Second Inaugural Address, Abraham Lincoln &bull; “I Will Fight No More Forever,” Chief Joseph &bull; How the Other Half Lives, Jacob Riis &bull; The Pledge of Allegiance &bull; Preamble to the Platform of the Populist Party &bull; Atlanta Exposition Address, Booker T. Washington &bull; The Jungle, Upton Sinclair &bull; Hind Swaraj, Mohandas Gandhi &bull; The Fourteen Points, Woodrow Wilson &bull; Two Poems, Langston Hughes &bull; Four Freedoms, Franklin D. Roosevelt &bull; Anne Frank: The Diary of a Young Girl, Anne Frank &bull; Charter of the United Nations &bull; Universal Declaration of Human Rights &bull; Autobiography, Kwame Nkrumah &bull; Inaugural Address, John F. Kennedy &bull; Silent Spring, Rachel Carson &bull; “I Have a Dream,” Martin Luther King, Jr. &bull; “Letter From Birmingham Jail,” Martin Luther King, Jr. &bull; “Tear Down This Wall,” Ronald Reagan &bull; “Freedom From Fear,” Aung San Suu Kyi &bull; “Glory and Hope,” Nelson Mandela xxi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="22"> <text><![CDATA[ Digital Resources Biographies &bull; Abigail Adams &bull; John Adams &bull; John Quincy Adams &bull; Samuel Adams &bull; James Armistead &bull; Crispus Attucks &bull; Moses Austin &bull; Stephen F. Austin &bull; James A. Baker III &bull; William Blackstone &bull; Simón Bolívar &bull; Napoleon Bonaparte &bull; Chief Bowles &bull; Omar Bradley &bull; John C. Calhoun &bull; César Chávez &bull; Wentworth Cheswell &bull; George Childress &bull; Winston Churchill &bull; Henry Clay &bull; Bill Clinton &bull; Jefferson Davis &bull; Martin De León &bull; Green DeWitt &bull; Dwight Eisenhower &bull; James Fannin &bull; James L. Farmer, Jr. &bull; Benjamin Franklin &bull; Milton Friedman &bull; Betty Friedan &bull; Bernardo de Gálvez &bull; Hector P. Garcia &bull; John Nance Garner &bull; King George III &bull; Henry B. González &bull; Raul A. Gonzalez, Jr. &bull; Mikhail Gorbachev &bull; William Goyens &bull; Ulysses S. Grant &bull; José Gutiérrez de Lara &bull; Alexander Hamilton &bull; Hammurabi &bull; Warren Harding &bull; Friedrich Hayek &bull; Jack Coffee Hays &bull; Patrick Henry &bull; Adolf Hitler &bull; Oveta Culp Hobby &bull; James Hogg &bull; Sam Houston &bull; Kay Bailey Hutchison &bull; Andrew Jackson &bull; John Jay &bull; Thomas Jefferson &bull; Lyndon B. Johnson &bull; Anson Jones &bull; Barbara Jordan &bull; Justinian &bull; John F. Kennedy &bull; John Maynard Keynes &bull; Martin Luther King, Jr. &bull; Marquis de Lafayette &bull; Mirabeau B. Lamar &bull; Robert E. Lee &bull; Abraham Lincoln &bull; John Locke &bull; James Madison &bull; John Marshall &bull; George Marshall &bull; Karl Marx &bull; George Mason &bull; Mary Maverick &bull; Jane McCallum &bull; Joseph McCarthy &bull; James Monroe &bull; Charles de Montesquieu &bull; Edwin W. Moore &bull; Moses &bull; Benito Mussolini &bull; José Antonio Navarro &bull; Chester A. Nimitz &bull; Richard M. Nixon &bull; Barack Obama &bull; Sandra Day O&apos;Connor &bull; Thomas Paine &bull; Quanah Parker &bull; Rosa Parks &bull; George Patton &bull; John J. Pershing &bull; John Paul II &bull; Sam Rayburn &bull; Ronald Reagan &bull; Hiram Rhodes Revels &bull; Franklin D. Roosevelt &bull; Theodore Roosevelt &bull; Lawrence Sullivan Ross &bull; Haym Soloman &bull; Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna &bull; Phyllis Schlafly &bull; Erasmo Seguín &bull; Juan N. Seguín &bull; Roger Sherman &bull; Adam Smith &bull; Joseph Stalin &bull; Raymond L. Telles &bull; Alexis de Tocqueville &bull; Hideki Tojo &bull; William B. Travis &bull; Harry Truman &bull; Lech Walesa &bull; Mercy Otis Warren &bull; George Washington &bull; Daniel Webster &bull; Lulu Belle Madison White &bull; William Wilberforce &bull; James Wilson &bull; Woodrow Wilson &bull; Lorenzo de Zavala &bull; Mao Zedong ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="23"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Access your Digital Lesson 21st Century Skills &bull; Identify Main Ideas and Details &bull; Set a Purpose for Reading &bull; Use Context Clues &bull; Analyze Cause and Effect &bull; Categorize &bull; Compare and Contrast &bull; Draw Conclusions &bull; Draw Inferences &bull; Generalize &bull; Make Decisions &bull; Make Predictions &bull; Sequence &bull; Solve Problems &bull; Summarize &bull; Analyze Media Content &bull; Analyze Primary and Secondary Sources &bull; Compare Viewpoints &bull; Distinguish Between Fact and Opinion &bull; Identify Bias &bull; Analyze Data and Models Atlas &bull; Analyze Images &bull; Analyze Political Cartoons &bull; Create Charts and Maps &bull; Create Databases &bull; Read Charts, Graphs, and Tables &bull; Read Physical Maps &bull; Read Political Maps &bull; Read Special-Purpose Maps &bull; Use Parts of a Map &bull; Ask Questions &bull; Avoid Plagiarism &bull; Create a Research Hypothesis &bull; Evaluate Web Sites &bull; Identify Evidence &bull; Identify Trends &bull; Interpret Sources &bull; Search for Information on the Internet &bull; Synthesize &bull; Take Effective Notes &bull; Develop a Clear Thesis &bull; Organize Your Ideas &bull; Support Ideas With Evidence &bull; Evaluate Existing Arguments &bull; Consider & Counter Opposing Arguments &bull; Give an Effective Presentation &bull; Participate in a Discussion or Debate &bull; Publish Your Work &bull; Write a Journal Entry &bull; Write an Essay &bull; Share Responsibility &bull; Compromise &bull; Develop Cultural Awareness &bull; Generate New Ideas &bull; Innovate &bull; Make a Difference &bull; Work in Teams &bull; Being an Informed Citizen &bull; Paying Taxes &bull; Political Participation &bull; Serving on a Jury &bull; Voting &bull; United States: Political &bull; United States: Physical &bull; Florida: Political &bull; Florida: Physical &bull; World Political &bull; World Physical &bull; World Climate &bull; World Ecosystems &bull; World Population Density &bull; World Land Use &bull; North Africa and Southwest Asia: Political &bull; North Africa and Southwest Asia: Physical &bull; Sub-Saharan Africa: Political &bull; Sub-Saharan Africa: Physical &bull; South Asia: Political &bull; South Asia: Physical &bull; East Asia: Political &bull; East Asia: Physical &bull; Southeast Asia: Political &bull; Southeast Asia: Physical &bull; Europe: Political &bull; Europe: Physical &bull; Russia, Central Asia, and the Caucasus: Political &bull; Russia, Central Asia, and the Caucasus: Physical &bull; North America: Political &bull; North America: Physical &bull; Central America and the Caribbean: Political &bull; Central America and the Caribbean: Physical &bull; South America: Political &bull; South America: Physical &bull; Australia and the Pacific: Political &bull; Australia and the Pacific: Physical xxiii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="24"> <text><![CDATA[ Economics Next Generation Sunshine State Standards ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1 English language learners communicate for social and instructional purposes within the school setting. ELD.K12.ELL.SS.1 English language learners communicate information, ideas and concepts necessary for academic success in the content area of Social Studies. HE.912.C.2.4 Evaluate how public health policies and government regulations can influence health promotion and disease prevention. LAFS.1112.RH.1.1 Cite specific textual evidence to support analysis of primary and secondary sources, connecting insights gained from specific details to an understanding of the text as a whole. LAFS.1112.RH.1.2 Determine the central ideas or information of a primary or secondary source; provide an accurate summary that makes clear the relationships among the key details and ideas. LAFS.1112.RH.1.3 Evaluate various explanations for actions or events and determine which explanation best accords with textual evidence, acknowledging where the text leaves matters uncertain. LAFS.1112.RH.2.4 Determine the meaning of words and phrases as they are used in a text, including analyzing how an author uses and refines the meaning of a key term over the course of a text (e.g., how Madison defines faction in Federalist No. 10). LAFS.1112.RH.2.5 Analyze in detail how a complex primary source is structured, including how key sentences, paragraphs, and larger portions of the text contribute to the whole. LAFS.1112.RH.2.6 Evaluate authors differing points of view on the same historical event or issue by assessing the authors claims, reasoning, and evidence. LAFS.1112.RH.3.7 Integrate and evaluate multiple sources of information presented in diverse formats and media (e.g., visually, quantitatively, as well as in words) in order to address a question or solve a problem. LAFS.1112.RH.3.8 Evaluate an authors premises, claims, and evidence by corroborating or challenging them with other information. LAFS.1112.RH.3.9 Integrate information from diverse sources, both primary and secondary, into a coherent understanding of an idea or event, noting discrepancies among sources. LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 By the end of grade 12, read and comprehend history/social studies texts in the grades 11CCR text complexity band independently and proficiently. LAFS.1112.SL.1.1 Initiate and participate effectively in a range of collaborative discussions (one-on-one, in groups, and teacher-led) with diverse partners on grades 1112 topics, texts, and issues, building on others ideas and expressing their own clearly and persuasively. Come to discussions prepared, having read and researched material under study; explicitly draw on that preparation by referring to evidence from texts and other research on the topic or issue to stimulate a thoughtful, well-reasoned exchange of ideas. Work with peers to promote civil, democratic discussions and decision-making, set clear goals and deadlines, and establish individual roles as needed. Propel conversations by posing and responding to questions that probe reasoning and evidence; ensure a hearing for a full range of positions on a topic or issue; clarify, verify, or challenge ideas and conclusions; and promote divergent and creative perspectives. Respond thoughtfully to diverse perspectives; synthesize comments, claims, and evidence made on all sides of an issue; resolve contradictions when possible; and determine what additional information or research is required to deepen the investigation or complete the task. LAFS.1112.SL.1.2 Integrate multiple sources of information presented in diverse formats and media (e.g., visually, quantitatively, orally) in order to make informed decisions and solve problems, evaluating the credibility and accuracy of each source and noting any discrepancies among the data. LAFS.1112.SL.1.3 Evaluate a speakers point of view, reasoning, and use of evidence and rhetoric, assessing the stance, premises, links among ideas, word choice, points of emphasis, and tone used. LAFS.1112.SL.2.4 Present information, findings, and supporting evidence, conveying a clear and distinct perspective, such that listeners can follow the line of reasoning, alternative or opposing perspectives are addressed, and the organization, development, substance, and style are appropriate to purpose, audience, and a range of formal and informal tasks. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="25"> <text><![CDATA[ LAFS.1112.WHST.1.1 Write arguments focused on discipline-specific content. Introduce precise, knowledgeable claim(s), establish the significance of the claim(s), distinguish the claim(s) from alternate or opposing claims, and create an organization that logically sequences the claim(s), counterclaims, reasons, and evidence. Develop claim(s) and counterclaims fairly and thoroughly, supplying the most relevant data and evidence for each while pointing out the strengths and limitations of both claim(s) and counterclaims in a discipline-appropriate form that anticipates the audiences knowledge level, concerns, values, and possible biases. Use words, phrases, and clauses as well as varied syntax to link the major sections of the text, create cohesion, and clarify the relationships between claim(s) and reasons, between reasons and evidence, and between claim(s) and counterclaims. Establish and maintain a formal style and objective tone while attending to the norms and conventions of the discipline in which they are writing. Provide a concluding statement or section that follows from or supports the argument presented. LAFS.1112.WHST.1.2 Write informative/explanatory texts, including the narration of historical events, scientific procedures/ experiments, or technical processes. Introduce a topic and organize complex ideas, concepts, and information so that each new element builds on that which precedes it to create a unified whole; include formatting (e.g., headings), graphics (e.g., figures, tables), and multimedia when useful to aiding comprehension. Develop the topic thoroughly by selecting the most significant and relevant facts, extended definitions, concrete details, quotations, or other information and examples appropriate to the audiences knowledge of the topic. Use varied transitions and sentence structures to link the major sections of the text, create cohesion, and clarify the relationships among complex ideas and concepts. Use precise language, domain-specific vocabulary and techniques such as metaphor, simile, and analogy to manage the complexity of the topic; convey a knowledgeable stance in a style that responds to the discipline and context as well as to the expertise of likely readers. Provide a concluding statement or section that follows from and supports the information or explanation provided (e.g., articulating implications or the significance of the topic). LAFS.1112.WHST.2.4 Produce clear and coherent writing in which the development, organization, and style are appropriate to task, purpose, and audience. LAFS.1112.WHST.2.5 Develop and strengthen writing as needed by planning, revising, editing, rewriting, or trying a new approach, focusing on addressing what is most significant for a specific purpose and audience. LAFS.1112.WHST.2.6 Use technology, including the Internet, to produce, publish, and update individual or shared writing products in response to ongoing feedback, including new arguments or information. LAFS.1112.WHST.3.7 Conduct short as well as more sustained research projects to answer a question (including a self-generated question) or solve a problem; narrow or broaden the inquiry when appropriate; synthesize multiple sources on the subject, demonstrating understanding of the subject under investigation. LAFS.1112.WHST.3.8 Gather relevant information from multiple authoritative print and digital sources, using advanced searches effectively; assess the strengths and limitations of each source in terms of the specific task, purpose, and audience; integrate information into the text selectively to maintain the flow of ideas, avoiding plagiarism and overreliance on any one source and following a standard format for citation. LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 Draw evidence from informational texts to support analysis, reflection, and research. LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10 Write routinely over extended time frames (time for reflection and revision) and shorter time frames (a single sitting or a day or two) for a range of discipline-specific tasks, purposes, and audiences. MAFS.K12.MP.1.1 Make sense of problems and persevere in solving them. Mathematically proficient students start by explaining to themselves the meaning of a problem and looking for entry points to its solution. They analyze givens, constraints, relationships, and goals. They make conjectures about the form and meaning of the solution and plan a solution pathway rather than simply jumping into a solution attempt. They consider analogous problems, and try special cases and simpler forms of the original problem in order to gain insight into its solution. They monitor and evaluate their progress and change course if necessary. Older students might, depending on the context of the problem, transform algebraic expressions or change the viewing window on their graphing calculator to get the information they need. Mathematically proficient students can explain correspondences between equations, verbal descriptions, tables, and graphs or draw diagrams of important features and relationships, graph data, and search for regularity or trends. Younger students might rely on using concrete ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="26"> <text><![CDATA[ Economics Next Generation Sunshine State Standards objects or pictures to help conceptualize and solve a problem. Mathematically proficient students check their answers to problems using a different method, and they continually ask themselves, Does this make sense? They can understand the approaches of others to solving complex problems and identify correspondences between different approaches. MAFS.K12.MP.3.1 Construct viable arguments and critique the reasoning of others. Mathematically proficient students understand and use stated assumptions, definitions, and previously established results in constructing arguments. They make conjectures and build a logical progression of statements to explore the truth of their conjectures. They are able to analyze situations by breaking them into cases, and can recognize and use counterexamples. They justify their conclusions, communicate them to others, and respond to the arguments of others. They reason inductively about data, making plausible arguments that take into account the context from which the data arose. Mathematically proficient students are also able to compare the effectiveness of two plausible arguments, distinguish correct logic or reasoning from that which is flawed, and if there is a flaw in an argument explain what it is. Elementary students can construct arguments using concrete referents such as objects, drawings, diagrams, and actions. Such arguments can make sense and be correct, even though they are not generalized or made formal until later grades. Later, students learn to determine domains to which an argument applies. Students at all grades can listen or read the arguments of others, decide whether they make sense, and ask useful questions to clarify or improve the arguments. MAFS.K12.MP.5.1 Use appropriate tools strategically. Mathematically proficient students consider the available tools when solving a mathematical problem. These tools might include pencil and paper, concrete models, a ruler, a protractor, a calculator, a spreadsheet, a computer algebra system, a statistical package, or dynamic geometry software. Proficient students are sufficiently familiar with tools appropriate for their grade or course to make sound decisions about when each of these tools might be helpful, recognizing both the insight to be gained and their limitations. For example, mathematically proficient high school students analyze graphs of functions and solutions generated using a graphing calculator. They detect possible errors by strategically using estimation and other mathematical knowledge. When making mathematical models, they know that technology can enable them to visualize the results of varying assumptions, explore consequences, and compare predictions with data. Mathematically proficient students at various grade levels are able to identify relevant external mathematical resources, such as digital content located on a website, and use them to pose or solve problems. They are able to use technological tools to explore and deepen their understanding of concepts. MAFS.K12.MP.6.1 Attend to precision. Mathematically proficient students try to communicate precisely to others. They try to use clear definitions in discussion with others and in their own reasoning. They state the meaning of the symbols they choose, including using the equal sign consistently and appropriately. They are careful about specifying units of measure, and labeling axes to clarify the correspondence with quantities in a problem. They calculate accurately and efficiently, express numerical answers with a degree of precision appropriate for the problem context. In the elementary grades, students give carefully formulated explanations to each other. By the time they reach high school they have learned to examine claims and make explicit use of definitions. SS.912.E.1.1 Identify the factors of production and why they are necessary for the production of goods and services. SS.912.E.1.2 Analyze production possibilities curves to explain choice, scarcity, and opportunity costs. SS.912.E.1.3 Compare how the various economic systems (traditional, market, command, mixed) answer the questions: (1) What to produce?; (2) How to produce?; and (3) For whom to produce? SS.912.E.1.4 Define supply, demand, quantity supplied,and quantity demanded; graphically illustrate situations that would cause changes in each, and demonstrate how the equilibrium price of a product is determined by the interaction of supply and demand in the market place. SS.912.E.1.5 Compare different forms of business organizations. SS.912.E.1.6 Compare the basic characteristics of the four market structures (monopoly, oligopoly, monopolistic competition, pure competition). SS.912.E.1.7 Graph and explain how firms determine price and output through marginal cost analysis. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="27"> <text><![CDATA[ SS.912.E.1.8 Explain ways firms engage in price and nonprice competition. SS.912.E.1.9 Describe how the earnings of workers are determined. SS.912.E.1.10 Explain the use of fiscal policy (taxation, spending) to promote price stability, full employment, and economic growth. SS.912.E.1.11 Explain how the Federal Reserve uses the tools of monetary policy (discount rate, reserve requirement, open market operations) to promote price stability, full employment, and economic growth. SS.912.E.1.12 Examine the four phases of the business cycle (peak, contraction - unemployment, trough, expansion - inflation). SS.912.E.1.13 Explain the basic functions and characteristics of money, and describe the composition of the money supply in the United States. SS.912.E.1.14 Compare credit, savings, and investment services available to the consumer from financial institutions. SS.912.E.1.15 Describe the risk and return profiles of various investment vehicles and the importance of diversification. SS.912.E.1.16 Construct a one-year budget plan for a specific career path including expenses and construction of a credit plan for purchasing a major item. SS.912.E.2.1 Identify and explain broad economic goals. SS.912.E.2.2 Use a decision-making model to analyze a public policy issue affecting the student&apos;s community that incorporates defining a problem, analyzing the potential consequences, and considering the alternatives. SS.912.E.2.3 Research contributions of entrepreneurs, inventors, and other key individuals from various gender, social, and ethnic backgrounds in the development of the United States. SS.912.E.2.4 Diagram and explain the problems that occur when government institutes wage and price controls, and explain the rationale for these controls. SS.912.E.2.5 Analyze how capital investments may impact productivity and economic growth. SS.912.E.2.6 Examine the benefits of natural monopolies and the purposes of government regulation of these monopolies. SS.912.E.2.7 Identify the impact of inflation on society. SS.912.E.2.8 Differentiate between direct and indirect taxes, and describe the progressivity of taxes (progressive, proportional, regressive). SS.912.E.2.9 Analyze how changes in federal spending and taxation affect budget deficits and surpluses and the national debt. SS.912.E.2.10 Describe the organization and functions of the Federal Reserve System. SS.912.E.2.11 Assess the economic impact of negative and positive externalities on the local, state, and national environment. SS.912.E.2.12 Construct a circular flow diagram for an open-market economy including elements of households, firms, government, financial institutions, product and factor markets, and international trade. SS.912.E.3.1 Demonstrate the impact of inflation on world economies. SS.912.E.3.2 Examine absolute and comparative advantage, and explain why most trade occurs because of comparative advantage. SS.912.E.3.3 Discuss the effect of barriers to trade and why nations sometimes erect barriers to trade or establish free trade zones. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="28"> <text><![CDATA[ Economics Next Generation Sunshine State StandardsSS.912.E.3.4 Assess the economic impact of negative and positive externalities on the international environment. SS.912.E.3.5 Compare the current United States economy with other developed and developing nations. SS.912.E.3.6 Differentiate and draw conclusions about historical economic thought theorized by economists. SS.912.G.2.2 Describe the factors and processes that contribute to the differences between developing and developed regions of the world. SS.912.G.3.3 Use geographic terms and tools to explain differing perspectives on the use of renewable and non-renewable resources in Florida, the United States, and the world. SS.912.G.4.4 Use geographic terms and tools to analyze case studies of issues in globalization. SS.912.FL.1.1 Discuss that people choose jobs or careers for which they are qualified based on non-income factors, such as job satisfaction, independence, risk, family, or location. SS.912.FL.1.2 Explain that people vary in their willingness to obtain more education or training because these decisions involve incurring immediate costs to obtain possible future benefits. Describe how discounting the future benefits of education and training may lead some people to pass up potentially high rates of return that more education and training may offer. SS.912.FL.1.3 Evaluate ways people can make more informed education, job, or career decisions by evaluating the benefits and costs of different choices. SS.912.FL.1.4 Analyze the reasons why the wage or salary paid to workers in jobs is usually determined by the labor market and that businesses are generally willing to pay more productive workers higher wages or salaries than less productive workers. SS.912.FL.1.5 Discuss reasons why changes in economic conditions or the labor market can cause changes in a workers income or may cause unemployment. SS.912.FL.1.6 Explain that taxes are paid to federal, state, and local governments to fund government goods and services and transfer payments from government to individuals and that the major types of taxes are income taxes, payroll (Social Security) taxes, property taxes, and sales taxes. SS.912.FL.1.7 Discuss how peoples sources of income, amount of income, as well as the amount and type of spending affect the types and amounts of taxes paid. SS.912.FL.2.1 Compare consumer decisions as they are influenced by the price of a good or service, the price of alternatives, and the consumers income as well as his or her preferences. SS.912.FL.2.2 Analyze situations in which when people consume goods and services, their consumption can have positive and negative effects on others. SS.912.FL.2.3 Discuss that when buying a good, consumers may consider various aspects of the product including the products features. Explain why for goods that last for a longer period of time, the consumer should consider the products durability and maintenance costs. SS.912.FL.2.4 Describe ways that consumers may be influenced by how the price of a good is expressed. SS.912.FL.2.5 Discuss ways people incur costs and realize benefits when searching for information related to their purchases of goods and services and describe how the amount of information people should gather depends on the benefits and costs of the information. SS.912.FL.2.6 Explain that people may choose to donate money to charitable organizations and other not-forprofits because they gain satisfaction from donating. SS.912.FL.2.7 Examine governments establishing laws and institutions to provide consumers with information about goods or services being purchased and to protect consumers from fraud. SS.912.FL.3.1 Discuss the reasons why some people have a tendency to be impatient and choose immediate spending over saving for the future. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="29"> <text><![CDATA[ SS.912.FL.3.2 Examine the ideas that inflation reduces the value of money, including savings, that the real interest rate expresses the rate of return on savings, taking into account the effect of inflation and that the real interest rate is calculated as the nominal interest rate minus the rate of inflation. SS.912.FL.3.3 Compare the difference between the nominal interest rate which tells savers how the dollar value of their savings or investments will grow, and the real interest rate which tells savers how the purchasing power of their savings or investments will grow. SS.912.FL.3.4 Describe ways that money received (or paid) in the future can be compared to money held today by discounting the future value based on the rate of interest. SS.912.FL.3.5 Explain ways that government agencies supervise and regulate financial institutions to help protect the safety, soundness, and legal compliance of the nations banking and financial system. SS.912.FL.3.6 Describe government policies that create incentives and disincentives for people to save. SS.912.FL.3.7 Explain how employer benefit programs create incentives and disincentives to save and how an employees decision to save can depend on how the alternatives are presented by the employer. SS.912.FL.4.1 Discuss ways that consumers can compare the cost of credit by using the annual percentage rate (APR), initial fees charged, and fees charged for late payment or missed payments. SS.912.FL.4.2 Discuss that banks and financial institutions sometimes compete by offering credit at low introductory rates, which increase after a set period of time or when the borrower misses a payment or makes a late payment. SS.912.FL.4.3 Explain that loans can be unsecured or secured with collateral, that collateral is a piece of property that can be sold by the lender to recover all or part of a loan if the borrower fails to repay. Explain why secured loans are viewed as having less risk and why lenders charge a lower interest rate than they charge for unsecured loans. SS.912.FL.4.4 Describe why people often make a cash payment to the seller of a good&ndash;called a down payment&ndash;in order to reduce the amount they need to borrow. Describe why lenders may consider loans made with a down payment to have less risk because the down payment gives the borrower some equity or ownership right away and why these loans may carry a lower interest rate. SS.912.FL.4.5 Explain that lenders make credit decisions based in part on consumer payment history. Credit bureaus record borrowers credit and payment histories and provide that information to lenders in credit reports. SS.912.FL.4.6 Discuss that lenders can pay to receive a borrowers credit score from a credit bureau and that a credit score is a number based on information in a credit report and assesses a persons credit risk. SS.912.FL.4.7 Describe that, in addition to assessing a persons credit risk, credit reports and scores may be requested and used by employers in hiring decisions, landlords in deciding whether to rent apartments, and insurance companies in charging premiums. SS.912.FL.4.8 Examine the fact that failure to repay a loan has significant consequences for borrowers such as negative entries on their credit report, repossession of property (collateral), garnishment of wages, and the inability to obtain loans in the future. SS.912.FL.4.9 Explain that consumers who have difficulty repaying debt can seek assistance through credit counseling services and by negotiating directly with creditors. SS.912.FL.4.10 Analyze the fact that, in extreme cases, bankruptcy may be an option for consumers who are unable to repay debt, and although bankruptcy provides some benefits, filing for bankruptcy also entails considerable costs, including having notice of the bankruptcy appear on a consumers credit report for up to 10 years. SS.912.FL.4.11 Explain that people often apply for a mortgage to purchase a home and identify a mortgage is a type of loan that is secured by real estate property as collateral. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="30"> <text><![CDATA[ Economics Next Generation Sunshine State Standards SS.912.FL.4.12 Discuss that consumers who use credit should be aware of laws that are in place to protect them and that these include requirements to provide full disclosure of credit terms such as APR and fees, as well as protection against discrimination and abusive marketing or collection practices. SS.912.FL.4.13 Explain that consumers are entitled to a free copy of their credit report annually so that they can verify that no errors were made that might increase their cost of credit. SS.912.FL.5.1 Compare the ways that federal, state, and local tax rates vary on different types of investments. Describe the taxes effect on the after-tax rate of return of an investment. SS.912.FL.5.2 Explain how the expenses of buying, selling, and holding financial assets decrease the rate of return from an investment. SS.912.FL.5.3 Discuss that buyers and sellers in financial markets determine prices of financial assets and therefore influence the rates of return on those assets. SS.912.FL.5.4 Explain that an investment with greater risk than another investment will commonly have a lower market price, and therefore a higher rate of return, than the other investment. SS.912.FL.5.5 Explain that shorter-term investments will likely have lower rates of return than longer-term investments. SS.912.FL.5.6 Describe how diversifying investments in different types of financial assets can lower investment risk. SS.912.FL.5.7 Describe how financial markets adjust to new financial news and that prices in those markets reflect what is known about those financial assets. SS.912.FL.5.8 Discuss ways that the prices of financial assets are affected by interest rates and explain that the prices of financial assets are also affected by changes in domestic and international economic conditions, monetary policy, and fiscal policy. SS.912.FL.5.9 Examine why investors should be aware of tendencies that people have that may result in poor choices, which may include avoiding selling assets at a loss because they weigh losses more than they weigh gains and investing in financial assets with which they are familiar, such as their own employers stock or domestic rather than international stocks. SS.912.FL.5.10 Explain that people vary in their willingness to take risks because the willingness to take risks depends on factors such as personality, income, and family situation. SS.912.FL.5.11 Describe why an economic role for a government may exist if individuals do not have complete information about the nature of alternative investments or access to competitive financial markets. SS.912.FL.5.12 Compare the Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC), the Federal Reserve, and other government agencies that regulate financial markets. SS.912.FL.6.1 Describe how individuals vary with respect to their willingness to accept risk and why most people are willing to pay a small cost now if it means they can avoid a possible larger loss later. SS.912.FL.6.2 Analyze how judgment regarding risky events is subject to errors because people tend to overestimate the probability of infrequent events, often because theyve heard of or seen a recent example. SS.912.FL.6.3 Describe why people choose different amounts of insurance coverage based on their willingness to accept risk, as well as their occupation, lifestyle, age, financial profile, and the price of insurance. SS.912.FL.6.4 Explain that people may be required by governments or by certain types of contracts (e.g., home mortgages) to purchase some types of insurance. SS.912.FL.6.5 Describe how an insurance contract can increase the probability or size of a potential loss because having the insurance results in the person taking more risks, and that policy features such as deductibles and copayments are cost-sharing features that encourage the policyholder to take steps to reduce the potential size of a loss (claim). ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="31"> <text><![CDATA[ SS.912.FL.6.6 Explain that people can lower insurance premiums by behaving in ways that show they pose a lower risk. SS.912.FL.6.7 Compare the purposes of various types of insurance, including that health insurance provides for funds to pay for health care in the event of illness and may also pay for the cost of preventative care; disability insurance is income insurance that provides funds to replace income lost while an individual is ill or injured and unable to work; property and casualty insurance pays for damage or loss to the insureds property; life insurance benefits are paid to the insureds beneficiaries in the event of the policyholders death. SS.912.FL.6.8 Discuss the fact that, in addition to privately purchased insurance, some government benefit programs provide a social safety net to protect individuals from economic hardship created by unexpected events. SS.912.FL.6.9 Explain that loss of assets, wealth, and future opportunities can occur if an individuals personal information is obtained by others through identity theft and then used fraudulently, and that by managing their personal information and choosing the environment in which it is revealed, individuals can accept, reduce, and insure against the risk of loss due to identity theft. SS.912.FL.6.10 Compare federal and state regulations that provide some remedies and assistance for victims of identity theft. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="32"> <text><![CDATA[ A Profile of Florida Today Florida is a state full of energy, diversity, and bright ideas for the future. In many ways, it is unlike any other state in the country. The following pages provide snapshots of Florida&apos;s geography, people, government, economy, and place in the world. So read on, and discover why there is so much to celebrate about Florida! Celebrate Florida’s GEOGRAPHY SS.912.G.3.3, LAFS.1112.WHST.1.2, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.7, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.8 Florida’s geography is unique. Most of the state occupies a peninsula separating the Atlantic Ocean and the Gulf of Mexico. Its coastline is one of the longest of the fifty states, and includes the most southerly point in the continental United States. Much of Florida is less than 100 feet above sea level, although northern and central areas are higher in elevation. While the northwestern part of the state is informally known as the “Panhandle,” Florida has seven regions. As you read, locate each region on the map. P A N H A N D L E Choctawhatchee River PerdidoR. Florida’s Regions 1 The Western Highlands extend from the Perdido River on the Alabama border to the Choctawhatchee River. Like other areas in the Panhandle, this hilly terrain produces field crops. 2 The Marianna Lowlands lie between the Choctawhatchee River in the west and the Apalachicola River in the east. 3 The Tallahassee Hills stretch from the Apalachicola River east to the Suwannee River. Like the Western Highlands, this is an important agricultural area. 4 The Central Highlands extend east from the Suwannee River to Saint Johns River. The highlands also extend south through central Florida, where most of Florida’s citrus production is located. 5 The Kissimmee Lowlands The Kissimmee River basin supplies Lake Okeechobee with water and provides land for citrus groves and cattle ranches. Its canals, dikes, and pumping stations comprise a complex system of water resource use and management overseen by the South Florida Water Management District. The district works to protect and restore the river basin ecosystem, manage the basin’s plant life and land, improve water quality, and regulate the water supply. 6 The Lake Okeechobee- Everglades Basin South of Lake Okeechobee the land is devoted to agricultural production of crops such as sugarcane. Further south is the Everglades National Park, protecting the fragile ecosystem of the Everglades—a shallow, slow-moving river that provides a habitat for hundreds of species of animals. 7 The Coastal Lowlands occupy about three-quarters of Florida’s land area, as you can see from the darker shading on the map. Offshore barrier bars and islands protect lagoons and bays and help create Florida’s famous beaches. xxxii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="33"> <text><![CDATA[ G u l f o f M e x i c o Kissimmee River restoration project, South FL Water Management District. The Florida Everglades National Park FloridaKeys THEEVERGLADES Gulf of Mexico BiscayneBay ATLANTIC OCEAN FloridaStraits KissimmeeR. St.Johns R. SuwanneeR. St.MarysR. ApalachicolaR. Lake Okeechobee Miami Bradenton Tallahassee Jacksonville Tampa Key West St. Augustine St. Petersburg Orlando Vero Beach Sebring SUBTROPICAL TROPICAL CLIMATE LINE 2 3 4 7 The Florida Everglades National Park Kissimmee River restoration project, South FL Water Management District. 6 5 State capital Other city 100 75 50 25 10 0 328 246 164 82 31 0 FeetMetersElevationxxxiii FloridaKeys THEEVERGLADES Gulf of Mexico BiscayneBay ATLANTIC OCEAN FloridaStraits KissimmeeR. St.Johns R. SuwanneeR. St.MarysR. ApalachicolaR. Lake Okeechobee Miami Bradenton Tallahassee Jacksonville Tampa Key West St. Augustine St. Petersburg Orlando Vero Beach Sebring SUBTROPICAL TROPICAL CLIMATE LINE 2 3 4 7 6 5 Elevation Feet Meters State capital Other city 328 246 164 82 31 0 100 75 50 25 10 0   xxxiii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="34"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida&apos;s Climate La Florida Florida&apos;s gentle climate and lush vegetation inspired Spanish explorer Juan Ponce de León to name the peninsula La Florida after the Spanish phrase for “Season of Flowers” when he landed during Easter of 1513. Florida can be divided into two climate regions, north and south of a line running from Bradenton to Vero Beach (see map on previous page). The northern region is cooler, while southern Florida is warmer. TEMPERATURE CHART Average Tallahassee Temperatures 1981–2010 Jan April Jul Oct Dec Max Max 63.5 74.7 79.9 81.6 92.1 89.1 81.4 84.3 65.3 76.2  Jan April  Jul  Oct  Dec Min Min 39.0 58.6 52.3 67.7 72.0 77.1 57.3 72.5 41.1 62.3 Average Miami Temperatures 1981–2010 Source: Florida Climate Center; Florida State University  Gulf of Mexico CapeHatterasGulf of Mexico ATLANTIC OCEAN GulfStream FloridaCurrent MS NC AL SC Florida LA TN GA BAHAMAS CUBA Azimuthal Equal-Area Projection 300 mi0 300 km0 NEWSStraits of Florida Ocean Currents Florida&apos;s relatively mild winters are influenced by the proximity of the Gulf Stream, a powerful current of warm water flowing up from the Gulf of Mexico, through the Straits of Florida and into the Atlantic Ocean. The “Florida Current” is part of the Gulf Stream system. xxxiv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="35"> <text><![CDATA[ Clay tiles on the roof create an air pocket to keep the house cool. Walls are covered in stucco, a kind of cement that protects walls from rain and heat. Tall doors and windows catch the breezes to cool the house. Mediterranean Revival Style Florida&apos;s climate has influenced the style and materials of its buildings. As new residents arrived in the state during the land boom of the 1920s, a Mediterranean Revival style spread. With its low-pitched, red tiled roofs and stucco walls, this style was perfectly suited to Florida&apos;s history and climate, and helped give the state its distinct look. Power and Fury Hurricane Andrew caused widespread damage in South Florida in August, 1992. Like much of the southeast and east coast of the United States, Florida lies in the path of hurricanes that form in the Caribbean, the Gulf of Mexico, or off the west coast of Africa. As these storms drift toward Florida, their terrifying energy is intensified by the ocean&apos;s warm waters and especially by the Gulf Stream. The hurricane season lasts from June to November, although September is the month when many storms strike the state. xxxv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="36"> <text><![CDATA[ Geography Shapes History Florida&apos;s geography has shaped every aspect of its history, contributing to the state&apos;s population increase and economic growth. Its northern soils provided fertile ground for the cash crops grown on plantations that depended on the labor of enslaved African Americans. The state&apos;s climate helped launch a series of land booms as vacationers and new residents swelled its population and fueled its economy. For centuries, its strategic location has conferred on Florida a range of military roles, from protecting Spain&apos;s treasure fleet to training U.S. troops during the conflicts of the twentieth century. Castillo de San Marcos in St. Augustine Florida&apos;s strategic military importance was established by the Spanish fort of St. Augustine, founded in 1565, partly to protect the route of the Spanish treasure fleet, whose loot-laden ships sailed back to Spain on the fast-moving currents of the Gulf Stream. xxxvi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="37"> <text><![CDATA[ Bannerman Plantation, built soon after 1827 Planters Move to Florida Attracted by the rich soils of the northern uplands, thousands of American planters moved into northern parts of the state after 1821. It was here that their enslaved African American workforce grew cash crops, including cotton. By 1850 there were about 1,000 cotton plantations in Florida. Rocket Launch at Cape Canaveral Florida Aeronautics During the conflicts and Cold War tensions of the twentieth century, Florida&apos;s geographical location increased its strategic importance. The state&apos;s flat terrain and wide beaches encouraged early flight testing and air force training, an aeronautic tradition that led to the establishment of Cape Canaveral for missile testing and space exploration. ASSESSMENT Key Ideas 1. Why is Florida a strategic location for the military? Critical Thinking 2. Infer The South Florida Water Management District is a government agency that oversees water resources in southern Florida. The state has four other water management districts. Use this information and the map on these pages to answer the following question: Why do you think Florida&apos;s government has stepped in to provide policies and programs for managing Florida&apos;s water resources? Use geographic terms such as resources and ecosystem in your answer. Writing 3. Explain Perspectives Gather information from a variety of print and online sources, including maps, on the use of renewable and non-renewable resources in Florida. Analyze each source for its strengths and weaknesses&ndash; for example, is it based on fact or opinion? Then write a few paragraphs describing the different perspectives you found, making sure to avoid plagiarizing and citing your sources in standard format. Do not rely too heavily on any one source and be sure to use geographic terms in your answer. xxxvii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="38"> <text><![CDATA[ Celebrate Florida’s Floridians today live in a multi-racial and multi-ethnic society in which a variety of languages are spoken&ndash;not surprising in a state whose geographic location has made it a crossroads of cultures. Florida&apos;s demographics, or population data, have been shaped by a history of migrations in which geography has played an important role. Race and Language RACE IN FLORIDA VS. THE U.S.: A COMPARISON Population, 2014* White, percent Asian alone, percent Black or African American percent Native American, percent 77.8 77.4 19,893,297 318,857,056 Florida U.S. 2.8 5.4 16.8 13.2 0.5 1.2 Two or more races, percent 2.0 2.5 Hispanic or Latino, percent** 24.1 17.4 Source: United States Census *estimates ** People who identify their origin as Spanish, Hispanic, or Latino may be of any race. Native Hawaiian/Pacific Islander alone, percent 0.1 0.2 How Does Florida Compare? While the percentage of white Americans in Florida and the U.S. as a whole is nearly identical, the similarity ends there. Overall, Florida has higher percentages of every racial group, except Native Americans, than the U.S. as a whole. xxxviii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="39"> <text><![CDATA[ MOST COMMONLY SPOKEN LANGUAGES IN FLORIDA, AFTER ENGLISH Florida Languages Key Spanish 73.35% French Creole 6.91% French 2.25% Portuguese 1.88% German 1.58% Tagalog 1.16% Vietnamese 1.16% Italian 1.16% Arabic 0.83% Chinese 0.75% Russian 0.68% Polish 0.53% Other 7.76% Source: MLA Language Map Data Center Language Diversity Over the centuries, Florida&apos;s geography and economy have attracted a variety of ethnic groups&ndash;political and economic refugees from Latin America, Greeks drawn to jobs in the sponge industry in Tarpon Springs, immigrants from Spain and Italy, Haitians, and white non-Hispanic people who make up Florida&apos;s largest population group. Many ethnic groups speak the language of their former homelands. In 2010, English was spoken by 73 percent of people over 5 years old in Florida. Twenty-seven percent spoke languages other than English. That 27 percent was divided as shown in the graph. Age and Birthplace  FLORIDA&apos;S POPULATION BY AGE, 2014* Age 0–4 5–19 20–44 45–64 65–84 85 and up Florida Number Number Percent Percent 1,077,572 19,773,0105.4 6.2 3,466,935 62,660,39317.4 19.6 6,252,832 106,772,48731.4 33.5 5,305,004 83,436,27326.6 26.2 3,266,698 40,168,92316.4 12.6 524,256 6,045,9702.6 1.9 Source: U.S. Census Bureau *estimates The Lure of Florida&apos;s Climate Florida&apos;s gentle climate has, of course, attracted a huge population of retirees from more northerly parts of the country, a trend that began in the late 1800s. xxxix ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="40"> <text><![CDATA[ BIRTHPLACE OF FLORIDA RESIDENTS 1950 Born in Florida = 43% Other South = 16% Georgia = 13% Northeast = 12% Midwest = 10% Outside U.S. = 6% Born in Florida = 36% Outside U.S. = 21% Northeast = 19% Midwest = 11% Other South = 8% West = 3% Other = 2% 20121950 Source: The New York Times BIRTHPLACE OF FLORIDA RESIDENTS Born in Florida = 43% Other South = 16% Georgia = 13% Northeast = 12% Midwest = 10% Outside U.S. = 6% Born in Florida = 36% Outside U.S. = 21% Northeast = 19% Midwest = 11% Other South = 8% West = 3% Other = 2% 2012 Source: The New York Times Immigration and Migration The graph shows that the number of Floridians born outside the U.S. began to change after 1950. Florida&apos;s People Throughout History Florida Seminoles The population of Florida&apos;s first people dwindled rapidly under the onslaught of disease and warfare during colonial times. By the early 1700s, Creek Indians and some runaway slaves had formed Seminole communities. Although only a few hundred Seminoles escaped Andrew Jackson&apos;s Indian Removal in the 1800s, about 2,500 of their descendants live on reservations in southern Florida. xl ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="41"> <text><![CDATA[ African Americans in Florida Enslaved African Americans were brought to northern Florida in large numbers after the U.S. gained control of the territory in 1821, as cotton planters moved onto land that had been vacated by Native American groups. At first, cotton plantations, with their huge enslaved populations, were roughly concentrated in the counties between the Apalachicola and the Suwannee Rivers. Today, African Americans constitute some 17 percent of the population of Florida. POPULATION OF FLORIDA: 1830–2000 Source: U.S. Census Bureau *estimate 20,000,000 15,000,000 10,000,000 5,000,000 1830 1860 1840 1870 1850 1880 1890 1900 1910 1920 1930 1940 1950 1960 1970 1980 1990 2000 A Growing Population In 1830, only Arkansas and Michigan had smaller populations than Florida. One hundred years later, Florida had a larger population than 18 other states. Historical events in both the United States and the world have often had an impact on Florida&apos;s population. xli ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="42"> <text><![CDATA[ A Changing Population Florida&apos;s Hispanic Population Throughout history, Florida&apos;s racial demographics have undergone dramatic changes. By the year 2030, it is predicted that Hispanics/ Latinos will comprise some 28 percent of Florida&apos;s population. What do these two maps reveal about changes in Florida&apos;s demographics between 2000 and 2010? Hispanic/Latino Population in Florida, by County 2000 Holmes Gulf DeSoto Glades Nassau Jefferson Monroe Madison Jackson Lake Flagler Hillsborough Taylor Hardee Duval Walton Sumter Alachua Lafayette Suwannee Hernando Washington Miami- Dade Seminole Calhoun Wakulla Manatee Polk Leon Baker Orange Pasco Broward Indian River Hamilton Palm Beach Escambia Levy Marion Liberty Okaloosa Okeechobee Brevard Collier Sarasota Lee Osceola Putnam Gadsden Pinellas Bay St. Lucie Franklin Clay Bradford Dixie Charlotte Santa Rosa Columbia Martin Union St. Johns Volusia Hendry Highlands Citrus Gilchrist County with the Greatest % of Hispanic/Latino Population: 2000 Miami-Dade 57.3% 2010 Miami-Dade 65.0% Counties with the least % of Hispanic/Latino Population: 2000 Nassau & Taylor 1.5% 2010 Baker 1.9% 2010 Percent County Population 1.5% - 3.9% 4.0% - 7.4% 7.5% - 12.4% 12.5% - 29.4% 29.5% - 65.0% Source: The Florida Legislature Office of Economic and Demographic Research Holmes Gulf DeSoto Glades Nassau Jefferson Monroe Madison Jackson Lake Flagler Hillsborough Taylor Hardee Duval Walton Sumter Alachua Lafayette Suwannee Hernando Washington Miami- Dade Seminole Calhoun Wakulla Manatee Polk Leon Baker Orange Pasco Broward Indian River Hamilton Palm Beach Escambia Levy Marion Liberty Okaloosa Okeechobee Brevard Collier Sarasota Lee Osceola Putnam Gadsden Pinellas Bay St. Lucie Franklin Clay Bradford Dixie Charlotte Santa Rosa Columbia Martin Union St. Johns Volusia Hendry Highlands Citrus Gilchrist xlii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="43"> <text><![CDATA[ Cuban Americans Although there have always been strong connections between Cuba and Florida, Cuban refugees began settling first in Key West and then Tampa as political turmoil engulfed their homeland in the late 1800s. New waves of Cuban immigrants arrived in the late 1950s, this time fleeing Fidel Castro&apos;s regime. ASSESSMENT Key Ideas 1. In what ways did history and geography contribute to Florida&apos;s population growth? Critical Thinking 2. Compare and Contrast What factors might explain the difference between the demographics of Florida and the rest of the United States shown in the “Demographics for Florida and the United States Compared” chart? Writing 3. Predict Future Trends Write a few paragraphs based on your research concerning future trends in Florida&apos;s population and demographics. Be sure to estimate the rate of population growth in the years to come, based on the statistics for the last few decades. xliii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="44"> <text><![CDATA[ Celebrate Florida’s GOVERNMENT LAFS.1112.WHST.3.7, LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10 A hurricane is forecast to hit the Florida coast in the next 24 hours and you need a list of emergency shelters. You are planning a fishing trip and would like information on top spots to find black bass. You see smoke coming from the back of a store and immediately alert the fire department. On a road trip to the Everglades, you notice that the speed limit has changed from 65 to 70 mph. What do all of these scenarios have in common? They all involve work done by Florida&apos;s State and local governments, which undertake an astonishing variety of duties every day. Legislative Branch Senate office building Senate chamber, where the Senate meets Senate fast facts: &bull;40 members &bull;Must be 21 years old &bull;Serve 4 year terms Offices of the Governor, Lt. Governor, Cabinet, and other executive offices; committee rooms House chamber, where the House meets House fast facts: &bull;120 members &bull;Must be 21 years old &bull;Serve 2 year terms House office building Historic Capitol &bull;museum &bull;eventspace Florida Capitol Complex, Tallahassee The Florida State Capitol Complex pays tribute to Florida&apos;s past while also looking to the future. The Florida legislature, made up of a House of Representatives and a Senate, meets in the Capitol. Its senators and representatives pass laws that make Florida a welcoming place for visitors, protect Florida&apos;s beaches and other natural areas, make it possible for people and businesses to thrive, and many other things. xliv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="45"> <text><![CDATA[ Executive Branch Day in the life of Governor rick Scott 7:00 am Staff briefing 8:00 am Radio show appearance 9:15 am Visit to Clearwater MarineAquarium to promote tourism 10:00 am Meeting with Mayor of Tampa 10:30 am Coffee and doughnuts with the press corps 11:00 am Cabinet meeting 11:30 am Informal press briefing 12:00 pm Working lunch 1:00 pm Meeting with legislative black caucus 2:00 pm Groundbreaking ceremony for new Vietnam War Memorial 4:00 pm Meeting with commissioner of agriculture regarding pay raises for forestry firefighters 5:30 pm Dinner with state and local community leaders 8:00 pm Republican party fundraiser at the Governors Club Day in the life of Governor rick Scott 7:00 am Staff briefing 8:00 am Radio show appearance 9:15 am Visit to Clearwater MarineAquarium to promote tourism 10:00 am Meeting with Mayor of Tampa 10:30 am Coffee and doughnuts with the press corps 11:00 am Cabinet meeting 11:30 am Informal press briefing 12:00 pm Working lunch 1:00 pm Meeting with legislative black caucus 2:00 pm Groundbreaking ceremony for new Vietnam War Memorial 4:00 pm Meeting with commissioner of agriculture regarding pay raises for forestry firefighters 5:30 pm Dinner with state and local community leaders 8:00 pm Republican party fundraiser at the Governors Club All in a Day s Work The executive branch is headed by the governor and lieutenant governor. It deals with a dizzying array of issues daily, such as children and families, revenue, military matters, farming, the elderly, education, the environment, transportation and highways, fish and wildlife, tourism, space and the list goes on! Here, Florida Governor Rick Scott visits the Clearwater Marine Aquarium where the governor held a press conference about Florida s tourism. xlv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="46"> <text><![CDATA[ EXECUTIVE BRANCH GOVERNOR LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR CABINET ATTORNEY GENERAL CHIEF FINANCIAL OFFICER COMMISSIONER OF AGRICULTURE executive office of the governor Large number of commissions, boards, and depart ments, including: Dept. of Legal Affairs Dept. of Financial Services Dept. of Ag riculture and Consumer Services Large number of departments, commissions, and agencies, including: Dept. of Health Dept. of Transportation Dept. of Elder Affairs DEPT. OF CITRUS Dept. of Juvenile Justice Florida’s Executive Branch Florida’s executive branch is headed by the governor, assisted by the lieutenant governor. Both the governor and the lieutenant governor serve a four-year term and are limited to two consecutive terms. The three members of the Cabinet are elected, rather than appointed. They work together to make decisions for the state. Each Cabinet member serves a four-year term with a two-term limit. xlvi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="47"> <text><![CDATA[ Judicial Branch The Rule of Law Florida&apos;s judicial branch ensures that Florida&apos;s laws are interpreted fairly. The Supreme Court is the highest court in the state. Due to the combined efforts of Florida&apos;s law enforcement officers and the courts, Floridians and visitors to the state can feel secure in the knowledge that justice and law are the order of the day in Florida. THE FLORIDA COURT SYSTEM &bull; Constitutionalquestions&bull; Capital cases&bull; Bond validations&bull; Public utility cases &bull; All matters not directly applicable to the Supreme Court &bull; Final actions of state agencies &bull; Felonies &bull; Family law matters &bull; Civil cases (over $15,000) &bull; Probate/guardianship/mental health &bull; Juvenile dependency and delinquency &bull; Appeals from county court &bull; Misdemeanors &bull; Small claims (up to and including $5,000) &bull; Civil (up to and including $15,000) &bull; Traffic SUPREME COURT DISTRICT COURTS OF APPEAL CIRCUIT COURTS COUNTY COURTS Source: floridasupremecourt.org Justice for All Florida has a four-tier court system, with the Florida Supreme Court at the top. The majority of cases are heard in the circuit and county courts. While the Supreme Court has discretion over which cases it will take, some types of cases must be reviewed by the court, such as cases involving: 1) the validity of a state law or a part of the state constitution; 2) the death penalty; and 3) any Public Service Commission action on rates or service of electric, gas, or telephone services. xlvii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="48"> <text><![CDATA[ Local Government Below these branches of state government can be found the complex and bustling world of local government. These are the officials who hand each voter a ballot on election day and who make sure the pothole on your road is fixed, the many historical treasures in Florida are properly cared for, schools have enough money, and much more. A SNAPSHOT OF FLORIDA STATE AND LOCAL SPENDING (IN BILLIONS) STATE GOVERNMENT AMOUNT LOCAL GOVERNMENT AMOUNT Education Public welfare Utilities Hospitals Transportation Public safety Environment and housing Unemployment, retirement, workers&apos; compensation All others combined TOTAL SPENDING, all categories 10.0 22.5 0.14 0.82 9.4 3.0 1.6 9.2 23.7 80.4 27.5 1.2 10.8 7.1 6.7 11.4 13.0 2.1 15.0 94.8 Source: Census Bureau, 2013 Juggling the Numbers Overall, the size of a county&apos;s population is not an indicator of spending. Some of Florida&apos;s least populous counties, such as Walton County on the Florida panhandle, are among the highest in the State in terms of spending. What factors might account for this? Which of these expenditures might impact tourism in Florida? xlviii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="49"> <text><![CDATA[ FLORIDA VOTER TURNOUT VS. NATIONAL TURNOUT 100 90 80 70 60 50 40 30 20 10 Percent 2004 2006 2008 2010 2012 2014 Election Key Florida election for U.S. President, U.S. Congress, Florida congress, Florida judges Florida election for U.S. Congress, Florida Governor and Cabinet, Florida congress, Florida judges National election for U.S. Congress National election for U.S. President, U.S. Congress Voting Happens at the Local Level All elections, whether for federal, state, or local offices, are held at the local level. Voters are assigned to a precinct, which determines where they go to cast their ballots. Elections are supervised by a local precinct election board, which also counts the votes and sends the results to the county clerk or board of elections. ASSeSSmenT Key Ideas 1. To which courts do county court appeals go? Critical Thinking 2. Draw Conclusions How does government affect the daily life of citizens at the state and local levels? Give examples to illustrate your answer. Writing 3. Evaluate an Election Follow or research either an ongoing election or a recent election at the state or federal level. Write several paragraphs to answer the following questions: What office is being filled? How were the people running nominated for office? How did they conduct their campaigns (did they use the Internet, television, debates, etc.?)? Who was allowed to vote in the election? And finally, who won the election? xlix ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="50"> <text><![CDATA[ Celebrate Florida’s ECONOMY LAFS.1112.SL.1.2, SS.912.E.2.2 Florida&apos;s economy is one of the largest and most diverse in the United States. It offers its residents a rich variety of jobs and business opportunities, and it offers investors many ways to contribute to, and benefit from, the state&apos;s growth. Florida&apos;s economy is also unique. It is especially strong in services, and particularly in services related to tourism and consumption. Measuring and Locating Florida&apos;s Economy TOP 10 STATES BY GDP, 2014* California 2,113 Texas 1,467 New York 1,280 Florida 770 Illinois 680 Pennsylvania 609 Ohio 532 New Jersey 504 North Carolina 440 Georgia 436 Billions of Dollars in 2014 Estimate *estimate Source: U.S. Bureau of Economic Analysis Goods and Services Produced Gross domestic product (GDP) is a measure of an economy&apos;s size. Florida has the fourth-largest GDP in the United States. Florida&apos;s large GDP means that it offers a wide range of economic opportunities. l ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="51"> <text><![CDATA[ WHERE MONEY IS MADE IN FLORIDA, BY COUNTY 2014 Personal Income, Billions of Dollars $100 billion $80 billion $20 billion $60 billion $40 billion Income Across Florida Most GDP is earned by people in the form of personal income. Personal income is closely related to economic activity. This map shows bars for each county in Florida. The height of each bar shows the amount of income earned in that county. Most of the money is earned in Florida&apos;s urban areas. These urban areas line the coasts and also cluster around Orlando in the center of the state. The county with the highest bar, and the most income, is Miami-Dade. Tourism and Jobs Florida&apos;s strong tourism industry means lots of jobs for hotel maids like these. Agriculture in Florida Farming is a top industry in Florida, contributing more than $100 billion to the state&apos;s economy. Farm workers in Florida and across the nation, however, often earn wages that are below the poverty line. li ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="52"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida&apos;s Businesses Contributors to Florida&apos;s Economy Florida&apos;s economy is both similar to and different from the economy of the United States as a whole. For both Florida and the nation, the sector that contributes most to GDP is finance, insurance and real estate. For both, government is the next largest sector. Florida&apos;s economy also differs in some ways. Florida has much smaller shares for its mining and manufacturing sectors than the United States as a whole. On the other hand, its retail sector has a larger share than it does for the United States as a whole, and its sector for arts, entertainment, recreation, accommodation, and food services has a much larger share than in the overall U.S. economy. This reflects Florida&apos;s specialization in tourism. GDP BY SECTOR, 2014* United States Florida Industry Key Agriculture, forestry, fishing, and hunting Mining (including oil and gas) Utilities Construction  Manufacturing Wholesale trade Retail trade Transportation and warehousing Information and Communications Finance, insurance, real estate Professional and business services Private educational and social services and healthcare Arts, entertainment, recreation, accommodation, and food services Other services, except government Government *estimate Source: U.S. Bureau of Economic Analysis lii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="53"> <text><![CDATA[ How Florida Compares GDP PER CAPITA, FLORIDA AND THE UNITED STATES Dollars in 2014 Estimate United States $49,469 Florida $38,690  Sources: U.S. Bureau of Economic Analysis and U.S. Census Bureau Per Person GDP If you divide the GDP by the number of people in a region, you get what is called its GDP per capita, a measure of the region&apos;s productivity and standard of living. Florida&apos;s GDP per capita ranks 43rd among the 50 states. Real Estate Jobs Tourists and retirees bring money to Florida. Some just want to shop while they are in the state. Others decide to buy seasonal and year-round homes. This helps explain why Florida has a larger-than-average share of jobs for salespeople like this real-estate agent. A Wide Range of Incomes Floridians have a wide range of incomes. Fisher Island, near Miami, is the most affluent zip code in the United States, with average household income over $1 million. liii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="54"> <text><![CDATA[ How Floridians Make a Living What Jobs Do Floridians Do? Florida&apos;s employment structure is similar to that of the United States as a whole, with a few exceptions: Compared to all Americans, a much smaller percentage of Floridians have jobs working in computers, engineering, science, education, the media, and production. By contrast, the percentage of Floridians working in property cleaning and maintenance and sales is much higher than the national average. JOB CATEGORIES, 2014* Job Category United States Florida Key Management, business, and financial Computer, engineering, and science Education, legal, community service, arts, and media Healthcare practitioners and technicians Healthcare support Protective service Food preparation and serving related Building and grounds cleaning and maintenance Personal care and service Sales and related Office and administrative support Farming, fishing, and forestry Construction and extraction Installation, maintenance, and repair Production Transportation Material moving Source: U.S. Census Bureau *estimate liv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="55"> <text><![CDATA[ Disney World Every year, Florida attracts about 100 million tourists to sites such as Disney World and the state&apos;s famous beaches. Tourism is more important to Florida&apos;s economy than it is to any other state. Shopping in Florida The retail sector also makes up a larger-thanaverage share of Florida&apos;s economy. Its size is partly due to sales to tourists, who are drawn to shopping districts like this one in Miami. ASSESSMENT Key Ideas 1. How does Florida&apos;s tourism industry affect its job market? Critical Thinking 2. Draw Conclusions Consider how Florida&apos;s economy differs from the national average, especially the importance of sectors related to tourism in Florida. How might these differences help to explain the state&apos;s higher poverty rate and lower GDP per capita? Writing 3. Solve Problems Consider the information presented in this economy section. What are the sources of the information presented in the graphs? Are these sources reliable? Why or why not? Based on this information or information from reliable sources, write at least one paragraph suggesting decisions Florida&apos;s policy makers and entrepreneurs might make to build on its economic strengths and increase its GDP. lv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="56"> <text><![CDATA[ Celebrate Florida&apos;s PLACE IN THE WORLD As a member of the global community, Florida&apos;s role is largely defined by its successful tourism industry and strong international trade. With a subtropical climate and nearly half a year of sunny days, it is not surprising that tourism is a critical part of Florida&apos;s economy. Along with tourism, trade has assumed an equally critical role in the state&apos;s economic wellbeing. Like the economies of California, New York and Texas, Florida&apos;s economy is of global importance. International trade, including exports and imports, supports nearly 2.4 million jobs in the state. Destination: Florida TOP 25 THEME AND AMUSEMENT PARKS IN THE WORLD Visitors (Millions) Up to 5 m 6 m–10 m 11 m–16 m over 16 m Key 10 17 3 18 3 PARKS CALIFORNIA, U.S. 7 PARKS FLORIDA, U.S. 5 PARKS EUROPE 2 PARKS SOUTH KOREA 2 PARKS CHINA 2 PARKS HONG KONG 4 PARKS JAPAN 11 12 22 1 6 7 8 9 25 24 23 21 19 2 4 5 20 13 15 14 16 Source: 2015 TEA/AECOM Fun in Florida As the home of numerous theme parks, Florida has set the yardstick for national and international theme parks. The size, construction, entrance fees, varied resorts, and innovative attractions that use technology in creative ways continue to bring visitors. As the most visited theme park in North America and the world, The Magic Kingdom at Disney World in Florida receives, on average, about 17 million visitors a year. lvi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="57"> <text><![CDATA[ INTERNATIONAL VISITORS TO FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL VISITORS TO FLORIDA 16,000,000 14,000,000 12,000,000 10,000,000 8,000,000 6,000,000 4,000,000 13.9 14.8 12.6 9.6 11.1 11.5 8.1 6.3 6.4 6.2 7.2 Source Line: Visit Florida 2014–2015 Marketing Plan To Florida from Around the World Beyond its theme parks, Florida&apos;s appeal extends to its wonderful beaches, historic cities, cruises, and cultural tourism. As shown on the graph, the number of international visitors is steadily rising. The first nine months of 2015 saw an estimated 8.3 million international visitors to Florida. Florida&apos;s Role in International Trade In May 2015, Governor Rick Scott, along with members of the Florida Chamber of Commerce proudly declared May as Florida World Trade Month. This special recognition pointed out the strength and successful growth of the state&apos;s economy, which is the fourth largest in the United States. Benefits from Trade Many Florida jobs are supported by the export trade. Manufacturing, agriculture, service and retail industries all thrive because many of those goods and services are sold overseas. The import trade is equally as important, creating jobs in the wholesale, retail, and transportation industries. Consumers benefit from products that come from South America including fresh fruit, vegetables, fish, and flowers. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="58"> <text><![CDATA[ FLORIDA&apos;S SHARE OF U.S. EXPORTS LATAM/Caribbean South America Central America Caribbean 36.4% 32.7% 24.8% 27.5% Source: WISER Trade; U.S. Department of Commerce, Census Bureau, Foreign Trade Division Gateway to Latin America In seeking to attract international businesses, Florida is often labeled the “gateway” to Latin America. Nearly one third of all U.S. exports (products that the United States manufactures and sends to Latin America) move through Florida. Florida exports of merchandise in 2014 reached $58.6 billion. The state&apos;s largest export markets are Brazil, Canada and Switzerland. Florida imports, or buys, about $32.9 billion of product from Latin America and the Caribbean. The graph shows Florida&apos;s share of the export trade between the United States and Latin America and the Caribbean. Florida is the second largest importer of products from Latin America and the Caribbean. Texas ranks first. FLORIDA&apos;S EXPORTS TO SOUTH KOREA COMMODITY EXPORTS (2014) Resins, rubbers and synthetic fibers Navigational and measuring instruments Aerospace products and parts Medical equipment and supplies Engines, turbines and power transmission equipment Fruits and vegetable preserves Industrial machinery Commercial and service industry machinery Fabricated metal products $78.8 million $71.7 million $64.7 million $53 million $42.6 million $41.8 million $31.5 million $14.5 million $13.7 million Source: United States Census Bureau Made in Florida The 2012 U.S.-Korea Free Trade Agreement opened new opportunities for Florida. Aside from the immediate boost in exports to and imports from Korea, there are other advantages. Job and business opportunities increased. Beyond mere numbers, however, the human factor is also beneficial&ndash;nearly 24,000 Koreans and Korean Americans live in Florida. Cooperation between the two governments is also growing&ndash;for example, a Florida citizen with a driver&apos;s license who chooses to live in Korea can exchange the Florida license for a Korean one without taking a driving test. Look for information in Topic 10 that explains global trade agreements. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="59"> <text><![CDATA[ The Panama Canal Expansion The Panama Canal, first opened in 1914, underwent a major renovation from 2007 to 2016. The expanded canal allows bigger ships to travel the waterway. It is also expected to bring significant change to domestic businesses and global trade. As the only state to border both the Atlantic Ocean and the Gulf of Mexico, Florida&apos;s coastal cities will benefit from the expansion. Changes are being made in its ports to accommodate the expected increase in trade. Currently, many companies with offices in Latin America have set up offices in Miami. With the canal expansion, it is expected that companies might consider other cities in which to locate new offices. Tampa Bay is one suggested location. Assessment Key Ideas 1. Based on what you have learned about Florida, how has the natural environment of Florida helped its tourism industry? Critical Thinking 2. Draw Conclusions As popular theme parks attract more visitors, what might be the positive and negative consequences of that expanded tourism? Writing 3. Analyze Information Review what you have learned about free trade agreements in Topic 10. In 2006 when a decision was being considered to initiate a free trade agreement with Seoul, Korea, many people were braced for bitter debates both for and against it. Write several paragraphs to answer the following questions. Work in small teams to discuss and research the topic. Why do you think there was opposition? What arguments may have been used to support the measure? Consider what arguments might have been used in the U.S. and in Korea regarding the agreement. lix ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="60"> <text><![CDATA[ A Quest is a search… a search for truth, understanding, or meaning. In the context of economics, a Quest is a search to understand the causes and meaning of major economic events, debates, or decisions. In this program, each Topic begins with one of three types of Quests: Document-Based Question Quests, Civic Action Project Quests, and Civic Discussion Quests. The introduction to each Topic&apos;s Quest can be found at the start of each Topic in this text. Economics is the study of how people seek to satisfy their needs and wants by making choices among scarce resources. Although it may seem that economics has very little to do with you, in fact, you make economic decisions every day. Every economic decision involves trade-offs. That&apos;s why it is important to understand basic economic concepts. As you complete these Quests, you will gain greater insight into the various economic forces and events that have shaped both the history of Florida and the United States. As you conduct research for some of these Quests, be sure to consult the Florida Memory website of the State Library and Archives of Florida (https://www.floridamemory.com/), as well as other digital and print resources. The materials you need to complete each Quest can be found online in the Quest folders, including complete instructions, sources, rubrics, and lots of other resources. ALL THREE TYPES OF QUESTS FOLLOW THESE FOUR STEPS: STEP 1 Develop Questions and Plan the Quest STEP 2 Investigate through Primary Sources or Develop a Plan to Solve the Issue STEP 3 Use Evidence to Formulate Conclusions STEP 4 Communicate Conclusions in writing, in a project, or in a discussion VIDEO ASSESSMENT ETEXT WRITING RUBRIC PDF ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for complete Quest materials Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="61"> <text><![CDATA[ QUESTS INCLUDED IN THIS PROGRAM FLORIDA QUEST Deciding Whether to Cut Taxes TOPIC 1 Civic Action Project TOPIC 2 Civic Discussion: Laissez Faire? TOPIC 3 Civic Action Project TOPIC 4 Document-Based Question: Was an antitrust lawsuit against Microsoft necessary? TOPIC 5 Civic Action Project TOPIC 6 Civic Discussion: Reinstate Glass-Steagall? TOPIC 7 Civic Action Project TOPIC 8 Civic Action Project TOPIC 9 Document-Based Question: How well did the federal government respond to the Great Recession? TOPIC 10 Civic Action Project lxi ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="62"> <text><![CDATA[ Your Florida LAFS.1112.WHST.3.8, SS.912.E.2.2 Deciding Whether to Cut Taxes Florida&apos;s state legislature cut taxes in 2015. Floridians debated whether additional tax cuts would be good for the state and its economy. Some felt they would boost growth, while others felt they would force cuts in state spending that could hurt growth. In this Quest, you will define the problem of whether to cut taxes, research and assess different arguments on the costs and benefits of tax cuts, and decide on a position. You will write up your position, citing your sources. Are Tax Levels and Economic Growth Related? FLORIDA STATE TAX LEVELS AND ECONOMIC GROWTH, 12 10 8 6 4 2 0 -2 -4 -6 Revenue as % of GDP Annual GDP Growth Rate 1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 2009 2010 2011 2012 2013 lxii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="63"> <text><![CDATA[ Using reliable print and digital sources, research the different arguments about tax cuts and the economy, some of which may have addressed this issue since 2015. Be sure to find some arguments specific to Florida. Assess the strengths and weaknesses of each source. Decide your own position on the issue. Then combine the insights offered by different sources into a paper arguing for your position. STEP 1 Find arguments on the costs and benefits of tax cuts in reliable sources. STEP 2 Consider the task, purpose, and audience of each source and assess the strengths and weaknesses of its arguments. STEP 3 Identify the problems around tax cuts, analyze potential results and alternatives, and decide on your own position on the issue. STEP 4 Write a position paper, citing your sources, arguing for your position. RUBRIC VIDEO ASSESSMENT PDF ETEXT WRITING Go ONLINE for complete Quest materials Savvas.com/FloridaSS lxiii ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="64"> <text><![CDATA[ Celebrate Freedom We hold these Truths to be self- evident, that all Men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the Pursuit of Happiness. That to secure these Rights, Governments are instituted among Men, deriving their just Powers from the Consent of the Governed.” &ndash;Declaration of Independence Declaration of Independence When the Continental Congress issued the Declaration of Independence in 1776, they did more than announce the separation of the 13 American colonies from Great Britain. They also summed up the most basic principles that came to underlie American government. This section, the preamble, is sometimes called the “social contract” section. You can read the words at left. The Declaration, largely written by Thomas Jefferson, is one of the most important documents in the history of the world. It not only declared the independence of a colony from its mother country&ndash; thereby setting a precedent for other oppressed peoples around the world to do the same&ndash;it also established the first government of, by, and for the people. The ideas expressed in the Declaration of Independence also had a profound effect on later developments in American history. You will notice the relationship of the ideas behind the Declaration of Independence to the American Revolution, the writing of the U.S. Constitution, including the Bill of Rights, and the movements to end slavery and to give women the right to vote. You&apos;ll see how the United States became a nation of immigrants, with its rich diversity of people, and the ways this development relates to the ideas of the Declaration of Independence. Read the first three paragraphs of the Declaration of Independence. Then recite words from the Declaration of Independence quoted at left. Consider their meaning and then answer these questions. ASSESSMENT 1. Identify Central Idea What do the words of the preamble (left) say to you about the American ideal of individual liberty? 2. Contrast How does the idea of government based on a “social contract” differ from the idea behind a monarchy? A dictatorship? 3. Apply Information Identify two ways that your federal, state, or local government protect the rights to life, liberty, or the pursuit of happiness. lxiv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="65"> <text><![CDATA[ Constitution Day Assembly September 17 is Constitution Day, and your school may hold an assembly or other celebration in honor of the day. As part of this celebration, your teacher may ask you to participate in planning and holding a Constitution Day assembly. Organize As a class, create the basic plan for your assembly. Discuss the following: 1. When and where should the assembly take place? 2. How long should it take? Should you plan on a short program taking a single class period, or a longer program? 3. Who should be involved? Will other classes or other grades take part? Will you invite outsiders, such as parents or people from the community? 4. What activities might be included? Plan After your discussion, divide the class into committees to complete jobs such as getting permission from the school administration, preparing a program, inviting any guests, advertising the plan beforehand, and blogging about it afterward. Give thought to the types of activities that might be included in the assembly. You might invite a guest speaker from your community. You might run an essay contest among students and have the winners read their essays during the assembly. Some students might prepare a video presentation about the Bill of Rights. Others might write and perform a skit about what the Declaration of Independence or U.S. Constitution mean to them. You might start your assembly by asking everyone to rise to say the Pledge of Allegiance to the United States flag. One student might give a brief speech about how the pledge reflects the ideas of the Declaration of Independence and the U.S. Constitution. >> Your school may hold a Constitution Day assembly like the one shown here. Communicate Present your Constitution Day assembly. After the assembly is over, discuss the event with the class. Ask yourselves questions such as these: 1. How well was the assembly planned and organized? What imporvements could we have made? 2. How would you rate each of the presentations or other activities of the assembly? 3. Was the audience engaged? 4. How effectively did the class work together? lxv ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="66"> <text><![CDATA[ AUDIO VIDEO WRITING ETEXT ASSESSMENT GAMESA CTIVITY PDF Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS [ ESSENTIAL QUESTION ] How does economics affect everyone? Fundamentals of Economics 1 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="67"> <text><![CDATA[ Next Generation Sunshine State Standards SS.912.E.1.1, SS.912.E.1.2, SS.912.E.1.7, SS.912.E.2.3, LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, LAFS.1112.RH.3.7, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10,LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9, LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10 Enduring Understandings • Economics is the study of how people seek to satisfy their needs and wants by making choices among scarce resources. • Every economic decision involves trade-offs; the most desirable choice given up is the opportunity cost. • Production possibilities curves show how efficiently an economy uses its resources. >> A customer at a cafe pays with a credit card. The fundamentals of economics. Bounce to Activate My Story Video 1 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="68"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 1 Overview In this topic, you will learn that economics is about making choices, and that the economic decisions we make shape our economy. Look at the lesson outline and explore the flow chart. As you study this topic, you&apos;ll complete the quest team project. LESSON OUTLINE 1.1 Scarcity SS.912.E.1.1, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 1.2 Opportunity Cost and Trade-Offs SS.912.E.1.7, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 1.3 Production Possibilities Curves SS.912.E.1.2, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 Fundamentals of Economics Wants are things that people desire but are not necessary for survival. UNLIMITED NEEDS AND WANTS Needs are things that are essential for survival. Capital is any human-made resource used to produce goods or services. LIMITED RESOURCES Economists use the term land to describe natural resources used to produce goods or services. Labor is the effort people devote to tasks for which they are paid. The scarcity of resources means that everyone has to make choices, such as the choice this farmer has to make about what crops to grow. TRADE-OFFS 2 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="69"> <text><![CDATA[ TEAM PROJECT Civic Action Project What does economics have to do with you? In fact, you make economic decisions every day. That&apos;s why it&apos;s important to understand economic concepts. In this quest, you will consider basic economic concepts as you complete a civic action project on an issue that concerns you. STEP 1 What is an issue you care about? Research an economic issue at the local, state, or federal level, then analyze existing public policy solutions. Are they sufficient? STEP 2 Brainstorm! Come up with some new ways to address the issue. Seek out experts or reliable sources on this issue and get their input. How can you improve the situation? STEP 3 Ramp up interest! Raise awareness through opinion polls, a web site, social media, or fliers. Try to get your local newspaper, radio, and television to cover the issue. STEP 4 Make something happen! Build support for your plan with a petition, panel discussion, and letters to or meetings with public officials. NGSSS ELD.K12.ELL.SI.1, ELD.K12.ELL.SS.1, LAFS.1112.SL.2.4 RUBRIC VIDEO ASSESSMENT PDF ETEXT WRITING Go ONLINE for complete Quest materials Savvas.com/FloridaSS 3 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="70"> <text><![CDATA[ 1.1 You have so many different ways you can spend your money. You really want that new video game. You also want to upgrade to the newest smartphone model. At the same time, you need to pay your car insurance. With limited funds, you can&apos;t have it all. How will you choose? >> Even in an affluent society like the United States, everyone must make economic choices. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS SS.912.E.1.1, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 >> Objectives Explain why scarcity and choice are the basis of economics in every society. Summarize how entrepreneurs fuel economic growth. Describe the three economic factors of production and the differences between physical and human capital. Explain how scarcity affects the factors of production. >> Key Terms need want goods services scarcity economics shortage entrepreneur factors of production land labor capital physical capital human capital Scarcity Scarcity Means Making Choices What&apos;s true for you is also true for your neighbors, your school, the gas station on the corner, a major television network, and the U.S. Congress. That&apos;s what economics is all about. Economics is the study of how individuals, businesses, and governments make choices when faced with a limited supply of resources. Scarcity forces us all to make choices by making us decide which options are most important to us. In this section, you will examine the problem of scarcity as it relates to such varied resources as water and the ingredients needed to make a ham and cheese sandwich. Unlimited Wants, Limited Resources The study of economics begins with the fact that people cannot have everything they need and want. A need is something essential for survival, such as food or medical care. A want is something that we desire but that is not necessary for survival, such as video games or stylish haircuts. People satisfy their needs and wants with goods and services. Goods are physical objects that someone produces, such as food, clothing, or video games. Services are actions or activities that one person performs for another. Medical care and haircuts are services. Savvas.com/FloridaSS VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="71"> <text><![CDATA[ People&apos;s needs and wants are unlimited. When one want is satisfied, others arise. After eating lunch, you might want to go to a movie or buy some clothes. Goods and services, however, are limited. No one can have an endless supply of anything. Sooner or later, a limit is always reached. The fact that limited amounts of goods and services are available to meet unlimited wants is called scarcity. At many different levels, scarcity forces people to make choices. For example, you have to decide how to spend your time. If you decide to study for a test, you cannot go to the mall or do volunteer work at the same time. A store must choose between hiring ten new workers or paying for more advertising to attract new customers. A city council debates whether to use its money to fix an aging school building or to hire more firefighters. Economics is the study of how people seek to satisfy their needs and wants by making choices. Because people act individually, in groups (such as businesses), and through governments, economists study all three of these arenas for economic decisionmaking. Scarcity Does Not Mean Shortage Scarcity is not the same thing as shortage. A shortage occurs when consumers want more of a good or service than producers are willing to make available at a particular price. Fans of a top singer will find a shortage of $25 seats at one of his or her concerts. Performers and promoters are simply not willing to provide many seats at that price. Shortages may be temporary or long-term. Unlike shortages, scarcity always exists and is a problem faced by all societies. There simply are not enough goods and services to supply all of society&apos;s needs and wants. Each of that singer&apos;s fans not only wants to go to the concert, but also wants to download the singer&apos;s songs, have dinner, buy a new top, and purchase other goods and services. Scarcity is unavoidable, because the resources that go into making goods and services are themselves scarce. Synthesize What is the main focus of economics? Entrepreneurs Use Factors of Production How are scarce resources turned into goods and services? Entrepreneurs play a key role. Entrepreneurs are people who decide how to combine resources to create new goods and services. Anyone who opens a business, large or small, is an entrepreneur. To make a profit, entrepreneurs Examples of Scarcity Around the World UNITED STATES BRAZIL JORDAN JAPAN GERMANY AUSTRALIA AFRICA SOUTH AMERICA ASIA EUROPE NORTH AMERICA KEY Petroleum Infrastructure Water Mineral resources Skilled labor >> Analyze Maps Germany faces a scarcity of what resource? What might be a possible cause of that scarcity? Bounce to Activate Map 1.1 Scarcity 5 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="72"> <text><![CDATA[ are willing to take risks. They develop new ideas, start businesses, and, if they are successful, even create new industries. By producing new goods and services and hiring workers, they fuel economic growth. The first task facing an entrepreneur is to assemble factors of production, or the resources used to make all goods and services. The three main factors of production are land, labor, and capital. Jean-Baptiste Say, an eighteenth-century French economist, thought the risk-taking entrepreneur so important that he should be considered a fourth factor of production. Land Economists use the term land to refer to all natural resources used to produce goods and services. Natural resources are any materials found in nature that people use to make things or to provide services. These resources include fertile land for farming, as well as resources found in or on the land such as oil, iron, coal, water, and forests. Labor The second factor of production is labor. Labor is the effort people devote to tasks for which they are paid. Labor includes the medical care provided by a doctor, the classroom instruction provided by a teacher, and the tightening of a bolt by an assembly-line worker. Labor is also an artist&apos;s creation of a painting or a technician&apos;s repair of a television. Capital The term capital refers to any human-made resource that is used to produce other goods and services. Economists divide capital into two types&ndash; physical capital and human capital. Human-made objects used to create other goods and services are physical capital. (Sometimes economists use the term capital goods for physical capital.) The buildings that house a computer manufacturing company are physical capital, as are all the equipment and tools needed to make those computers. In addition to producing physical capital, people can also invest in themselves. The knowledge and skills a worker gains through education and experience are human capital. Computer designers go to college to study engineering, electronics, and computers. They increase their human capital, making it possible for them to design and build faster and more powerful computers. Auto mechanics also increase their human capital through schooling and experience. This knowledge gives them the skills to diagnose and fix an engine that is not running properly. An economy requires both physical and human capital to produce goods and services. Doctors need both stethoscopes and schooling to provide healthcare. Carpenters require both tools and the skills they gain through training and practice. WHAT DOES AN ENTREPRENEUR DO? 1 RECOGNIZE A NEED OR WANT A new business starts with an idea. 2 ASSEMBLE THE FACTORS OF PRODUCTION LAND Natural resources LABOR People to do the work CAPITAL Human-made resources HUMAN CAPITAL Acquired knowledge and skills PHYSICAL CAPITAL Objects used to create goods or to supply services 3 PROVIDE THE GOODS OR SERVICES >> Entrepreneurs combine the three factors of production to produce goods and services. Bounce to Activate Chart 6 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="73"> <text><![CDATA[ Machinery Improves Productivity Dish Washing Over Time Time Washing by Hand Time Using Dishwasher Time Saved 1 Day 1 Week 1 Month 6 Months 1 Year 3 hours 21 hours 84 hours 546 hours 1,092 hours 1 hour 7 hours 28 hours 182 hours 364 hours 2 hours 14 hours 56 hours 364 hours 728 hours >> Analyze Charts What resource becomes less scarce as a result of using a dishwasher to wash dishes every day? The Effectiveness of Capital Capital is a key factor of production because people and companies can use it to save a great deal of time and money. Physical capital such as machines and tools helps workers produce goods and services more easily and at less cost. Businesses that buy and use these kinds of business property usually become more productive. Human capital such as technical knowledge has the same result. The more skills a worker gains, the more productive he or she becomes. Many businesses provide training for their employees for this reason. To understand the benefit of purchasing capital, consider the following example: A family washes dishes by hand after every meal&ndash;breakfast, lunch, and dinner. That is a total of 21 meals per week. It takes 30 minutes per meal for two family members working together to scrape, stack, wash, rinse, dry, and put away the dishes. As a result, the family spends 21 hours a week cleaning dishes&ndash;time that could have been spent on other, more productive activities. Now, suppose that the family saves up and spends $400 on a piece of physical capital&ndash;a dishwasher. Using the dishwasher, it takes only one family member a mere 15 minutes after each meal to stack the dishwasher and another family member just 15 minutes at the end of the day to empty the machine and put the dishes away, for a total of 1 hour a day. A chore that used to require 21 hours a week to complete now takes only 7 hours a week. This example shows the typical benefits of using capital: 1. Extra time The family saves 14 hours a week. This is time that can be used for other activities. 2. More knowledge By learning how to use the dishwasher, family members learn more about using household appliances in general. They can apply that knowledge to using washing machines, dryers, and other appliances. In the same way that a family benefits from investing in a piece of physical capital like a dishwasher, a business usually benefits from purchasing and using business property. When a business invests in technology, such as new machinery, it often benefits by saving time. In addition, workers are likely to gain new types of knowledge. 3. More productivity With extra time and more knowledge, family members can use their resources and labor to do other chores, to learn other skills, or simply to enjoy themselves. Every member of the family benefits. IdENTIfy A plow used to prepare soil for planting is an example of what factor of production? All Resources Are Scarce All goods and services are scarce because the resources used to produce them are scarce. Consider a fresh sandwich made at a restaurant. The sandwich roll might have started as wheat in a field in Kansas and then been milled into flour and later baked in an oven. The cheese might have been made from milk from Wisconsin cows, and the chicken may have been raised in Arkansas. The lettuce and tomatoes may have been grown in California. All of these ingredients may have been shipped 1.1 Scarcity 7 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="74"> <text><![CDATA[ >> Even though this woman has an abundance of sandwich ingredients, scarcity still exists here. The land, labor, and capital resources used to produce these ingredients are all scarce. to a restaurant in Seattle, where a chef made the sandwich and served it to a hungry customer. All the factors of production used to produce the sandwich are scarce. First, the amount of land and water available for growing crops and raising livestock is limited. Second, the labor available to grow the crops, mill the flour, bake the rolls, and serve the food is limited by the size, time, age, and energy of the population. Finally, the amount of physical capital available to produce the sandwich, such as farm machines or baking equipment, is also limited. The same principles apply to a pair of blue jeans, a tablet computer, or a space shuttle. No matter what good or service we look at, the supplies of land, labor, and capital used to produce it are scarce. We also notice another fact about those resources &ndash;each one has many alternative uses. The land could have been used to grow yams or parsnips. The farm workers could have chosen to work in the timber industry. Physical capital could have been put to other uses as well. Individuals, businesses, and governments have to choose which alternative they most want. IdENTIfy MAIN IdEAS Why are goods and services scarce? ASSESSMENT 1. Apply Concepts Give two examples of needs and two examples of wants. 2. Distinguish What is the difference between scarcity and a shortage? 3. Identify Why do entrepreneurs take the risk to start or expand a business? 4. Categorize What are the factors of production? 5. Infer If increasing physical capital increases productivity, why would a company not buy newer, faster computers for all its workers every year? 8 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="75"> <text><![CDATA[ 1.2 You are cleaning your bedroom. Boxes, clothes, and other items cover your bed, the floor, the entire room. Suddenly, your phone rings, and a friend invites you to a party. You consider your options and quickly decide that going to the party will be more fun than cleaning your room. >> When business owners decide what goods to sell in their store, they give up the profits they might have made if they had decided to sell other items. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video Opportunity Cost and Trade-Offs Making Decisions Later, tired but happy, you enter your bedroom and realize that you now have to clear off your bed when all you want to do is sleep. Your decision to go to the party cost you the time you needed to clean up your room. Was the benefit of your choice worth the cost? Every time we choose to do something, we give up the opportunity to do something else. As you will see, even such a simple decision as how late to sleep in the morning involves weighing costs and benefits. Economists point out that all individuals, businesses, and large groups of people&ndash;even governments&ndash;make decisions that involve trade-offs. A trade-off is the act of giving up one benefit in order to gain another, greater benefit. Trade-offs often involve things that can be easily measured, such as money, property, or time. But trade-offs may also involve values that are not so easy to measure. Such intangibles include enjoyment, job satisfaction, or the feeling of well-being that comes from helping somebody. Individual Decisions At every stage of life, you have to make trade-offs. Taking a part in the school play prevents you from NGSSS SS.912.E.1.7, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 >> Objectives Identify why every decision involves trade-offs. Explain the concept of opportunity cost. Describe how people make decisions by thinking at the margin. >> Key Terms trade-off guns or butter opportunity cost thinking at the margin cost/benefit analysis marginal cost marginal benefit VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="76"> <text><![CDATA[ playing soccer or getting a part-time job. A few years from now, you might decide to turn down an exciting but low-paying job in favor of a less interesting job that pays better. Still later, you may choose to give up a vacation in order to put more money away for your retirement. Business Decisions The decisions that businesses make about how to use their factor resources&ndash;land, labor, and capital&ndash;also involve trade-offs. A farmer who plants broccoli cannot at the same time use the same area of land to grow squash. A furniture company that decides to use all of its equipment to make chairs eliminates the possibility of using the same equipment to build tables or desks. Government Decisions National, state, and local governments also make decisions that involve trade-offs. Economists and politicians use the term “guns or butter” to describe one of the common choices facing governments: the choice between spending money on military or domestic needs. A country that decides to produce more military goods (“guns”) has fewer resources to devote to consumer goods (“butter”) and vice versa. The steel needed to produce a tank cannot then be used to produce a tractor. >> The phrase “guns or butter” refers to the trade-off that governments make between military and domestic spending. Bounce to Activate Gallery For example, as the war in Afghanistan began drawing to a close in 2013, the United States began debating how to rein in military spending and government spending in general. One commentator described this debate: “Guns versus butter” has come back in vogue politically. “Guns” basically means spending on security concerns (military defense needs) as opposed to welfare pursuits or “butter” (education, hospitals, housing, schools, etc.). The choice for nations isn&apos;t usually either “guns” or “butter” but rather how many guns and how much butter . . . . But the question remains: How many guns are necessary to maintain a high level of security for the U.S., and how much butter can the nation afford without hurting guns and vice versa? &ndash;David Briceno, “‘Guns vs. Butter,&apos; America&apos;s Political Dilemma,” The Union In the end, the reason for the “guns or butter” trade-off is the same as the reason for any other trade-off: scarcity. Goods and services are limited, but our needs and wants are unlimited. dEfINE What are trade-offs? Opportunity Cost In most trade-off situations, one of the rejected alternatives is more desirable than the rest. The most desirable alternative somebody gives up as the result of a decision is the opportunity cost. Take the farmer in the example above. If squash is the most profitable alternative to broccoli, then the opportunity cost of deciding to plant broccoli is the chance to plant squash. Even simple decisions carry opportunity costs. Consider the following choices: Sleep late or wake up early to study for a test? Sleep late or wake up early to eat breakfast? Sleep late or wake up early to go on a ski trip? Most likely, you did not choose “sleep late” for all three decisions. Your decision depended on the specific opportunity cost&ndash;the value to you of what you were willing to sacrifice. 10 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="77"> <text><![CDATA[ Karen&apos;s Decision-Making Grid ALTERNATIVES BENEFITS BENEFITS FORGONE OPPORTUNITY COST SLEEP LATE &bull; Enjoy more sleep &bull; Have more energy during the day &bull; Better grade on test &bull; Teacher and parental approval &bull; Personal satisfaction Extra study time WAKE UP EARLY TO STUDY &bull; Better grade on test &bull; Teacher and parental approval &bull; Personal satisfaction &bull; Enjoy more sleep &bull; Have more energy during the day Extra sleep time >> Figure 1.1 Analyze Charts What would you do if you were Karen? Why? Bounce to Activate Chart Using a Decision-Making Grid At times, the opportunity cost of a decision may be unclear or complicated. Using a decision-making grid can help you determine whether you are willing to accept the opportunity cost of a choice you are about to make. In Figure 1.1, a high school student named Karen is trying to decide whether to sleep late or get up early to study for a test. Because of the scarcity of time, she cannot do both. To help her make her decision, Karen lists the benefits of each alternative on the grid. Waking up early to study will probably result in her receiving a better grade. She will also receive teacher and parental approval and experience a sense of personal satisfaction. On the other hand, Karen enjoys sleeping. In addition, the extra sleep would give her more energy during the day. She would have to give up these benefits if she decided to get up earlier. Making the Decision Karen is a practical person. After considering the opportunity cost of each alternative, she decides that waking up early to study offers her the most desirable benefits. She knows that she is giving up the pleasure of more sleep and the extra energy it would provide. But she is willing to accept this opportunity cost. If Karen faced other decisions with other opportunity costs, she might choose differently. What if the choice were between sleeping late and getting up early to have breakfast? What if her decision to sleep late or study were on a Saturday rather than on a school day? With each different set of alternatives, the possible benefits and opportunity costs change as well. One thing does not change, though. We always face an opportunity cost. As economists say, “Choosing is refusing.” When we select one alternative, we must sacrifice at least one other alternative and its benefits. IDENTIFY MAIN IDEAS Why does every choice involve an opportunity cost? Thinking at the Margin When economists look at decisions, they point out one more characteristic in addition to opportunity cost. Many decisions involve adding or subtracting one unit, such as one hour or one dollar. From an economist&apos;s point of view, when you decide how much more or less to do, you are thinking at the margin. To understand what it means to think at the margin, think about folding a piece of paper with important notes on it to put in your pocket. If you fold the paper in half and then in half again, it can just squeeze into your pocket and will lay fairly flat. If you continued folding it in half two or three more times, it would fit more easily in your pocket. But the paper would also become more bulky with each additional fold. The question is, how many folds is the best number for fitting easily into your pocket and laying flat once inside? Analyzing Costs and Benefits Deciding by thinking at the margin is just like making any other decision. Decision makers have to compare the opportunity costs and the benefits&ndash;what they will 1.2 Opportunity Cost and Trade-Offs 11 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="78"> <text><![CDATA[ Decision Making at the Margin OPTIONS 1st hour of extra study time 2nd hour of extra study time 3rd hour of extra study time BENEFIT Grade of C on test Grade of B on test Grade of B+ on test OPPORTUNITY COST 1 hour of sleep 2 hours of sleep 3 hours of sleep >> Figure 1.2 Karen decides to wake up two hours earlier to study with the expectation of raising her grade to a B. Analyze Charts Do you agree with that decision? Why or why not? sacrifice and what they will gain. This decision- making process is sometimes called cost/benefit analysis. To make rational, or sensible, decisions at the margin, you must weigh marginal costs against marginal benefits. The marginal cost is the extra cost of adding one unit, whether it be sleeping one extra hour or building one extra house. The marginal benefit is the extra benefit of adding the same unit. As long as the marginal benefits exceed the marginal costs, it pays to add more units. Making Decisions at the Margin Look again at the example of Karen&apos;s decision on how late to sleep. The decision-making grid used an “all or nothing” approach. Either Karen was going to wake up early to study, or she was going to sleep late and not study at all that morning. In reality, Karen could have decided from among several options rather than just two. She could have decided to get up one, two, or three hours earlier. Making a decision about each extra hour would involve thinking at the margin. To make a decision at the margin, Karen should look at the marginal cost of each extra hour of studying and compare it to the marginal benefit. In Figure 1.2, we can see that one hour of studying means an opportunity cost of an hour of sleep, while the probable benefit would be passing the test with a C. Two hours of studying means losing two hours of sleep and perhaps getting a B. When Karen gives up three hours of sleep, however, the probable benefit rises only slightly, to a grade of B+. Karen concludes that the marginal cost of losing three hours of sleep is no longer worth the marginal benefit because her grade will improve only slightly. Based on her cost/benefit analysis, Karen decides to awaken two hours earlier. Like opportunity cost, thinking at the margin applies not just to individuals, but to businesses and governments as well. Employers think at the margin when they decide how many extra workers to hire. Legislators think at the margin when deciding how much to increase spending on a government program. ChECK UNdERSTANdINg How can a cost/ benefit analysis help people make decisions? ASSESSMENT 1. Express Problems Clearly Give an example of a “guns or butter” trade-off your school or local government might have to make. Describe the issues on each side of the debate. 2. Apply Concepts Suppose a friend is trying to decide whether to purchase a car. Use what you know about opportunity cost to help your friend arrive at a wise decision. 3. Support Ideas With Examples Can all opportunity costs be evaluated using a cost/ benefit analysis? Use an example to explain your answer. 4. Analyze Information Think of a recent decision you made. Review your decision in terms of opportunity cost. Do you think you made a wise decision? 5. Apply Concepts What marginal costs and benefits might a retail business owner have to consider when trying to decide whether to stay open an additional hour? 12 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="79"> <text><![CDATA[ 1.3 Your class decides to sponsor a community breakfast as a fundraiser. Can you make more money by serving eggs or pancakes? Should you offer both? To decide, you&apos;ll have to look at the cost of ingredients, the number of workers you have, and the size of the kitchen. Also, does it take more time to scramble eggs or to flip pancakes? What you decide will affect how much money you raise. >> New technology, such as these robots, can increase the efficiency of a nation s production and lead to economic growth. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video Possibilities Production Possibilities Nations face similar decisions about what to produce. For nations, however, the consequences of these decisions can be far more serious. To decide what and how much to produce, economists use a tool known as a production possibilities curve. You will see how an imaginary country uses this tool to decide between producing two very different products: shoes and watermelons. Economists often use graphs to analyze the choices and trade- offs that people make. Why? Because graphs help us see how one value relates to another value. A production possibilities curve is a graph that shows alternative ways to use an economy&apos;s productive resources. The axes of the graph can show categories of goods and services, such as farm goods and factory goods or capital goods and consumer goods. The axes can also display any pair of specific goods or services, such as hats on one axis and shoes on the other. Drawing a Production Possibilities Curve To draw a production possibilities curve, an economist begins by deciding which goods NGSSS SS.912.E.1.2, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 >> Objectives Interpret a production possibilities curve. Explain how production possibilities curves show efficiency, growth, and opportunity cost. Explain why a country&apos;s production possibilities depend on its resources and technology. >> Key Terms production possibilities curve production possibilities frontier efficiency underutilization law of increasing costs VIDEO ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources AUDIO ACTIVITYSavvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="80"> <text><![CDATA[ or services to examine. In this example, we will look at a fictional country called Capeland. Government economists in Capeland must decide whether to use the nation&apos;s scarce resources to manufacture shoes or to grow watermelons. The economists determine that, if Capeland used all of its resources to produce only shoes, it could produce 15 million pairs of shoes. At the other extreme, if Capeland used all of its resources to produce only watermelons, it could produce 21 million tons of watermelons. The Capeland economists use this information to create a production possibilities curve (Figure 1.3). The vertical axis of the graph represents how many millions of pairs of shoes Capeland&apos;s factories can produce. The horizontal axis shows how many millions of tons of watermelons Capeland&apos;s farmers can grow. At point a, Capeland is producing 15 million pairs of shoes but no watermelons. At point c, Capeland is producing 21 million tons of watermelons but no shoes. There is a third, more likely alternative. The citizens of Capeland can use their resources to produce both shoes and watermelons. The table shows four different ways that Capelanders could use their resources to produce both shoes and watermelons. Using the made-up data from the table, we can plot points on the graph. This line, called the production possibilities frontier, shows combinations of the production of both shoes and watermelons. Any spot on that line represents a point at which Capeland is using all of its resources to produce a maximum combination of those two products. Trade-Offs Along the Production Possibilities Frontier Each point on the production possibilities frontier reflects a trade-off. Near the top of the curve, factories produce more shoes, but farms grow fewer watermelons. Farther down the curve, farms grow more watermelons, but factories make fewer pairs of shoes. These trade-offs are necessary because factors of production are scarce. Using land, labor, and capital to make one product means that fewer resources are left to make something else. dEfINE Why is a production possibilities curve helpful to economists? Changing Production Possibilities Production possibilities curves give useful information. They can show how efficient an economy is, whether an economy is growing, and the opportunity cost of producing more of one good or service. Efficiency A production possibilities frontier represents an economy working at its most efficient level. Efficiency is the use of resources in such a way as to maximize the output of goods and services. However, sometimes economies operate inefficiently. For example, suppose some workers were laid off. The farms or factories where they worked would produce fewer goods. The Production Possibilities Curve WATERMELONS (TONS) 0 8 million 14 million 18 million 20 million 21 million SHOES (PAIRS) 15 million 14 million 12 million 9 million 5 million 0 Shoes (millions of pairs) 0 5 10 15 20 25 Watermelons (millions of tons) 0 5 10 15 20 25 a No watermelons, all possible shoes b Production possibilities frontier c No shoes, all possible watermelons  >> Figure 1.3 Analyze Graphs Is it more efficient to produce 8 million tons of watermelons and 14 million pairs of shoes or 21 million tons of watermelons and no shoes? Explain your answer. Bounce to Activate Chart 14 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="81"> <text><![CDATA[ Economic Growth Shoes (millions of pairs) 0 5 10 15 20 25 Watermelons (millions of tons) 0 5 10 15 20 25 a Production possibilities frontier 15 before economic growth b Point of 10 underutilization 5 c Production possibilities frontier after economic growth >> Figure 1.4 Analyze Graphs Based on this curve, how would you describe a situation in which Capeland produces 10 million tons of watermelons and 10 million pairs of shoes? Bounce to Activate 3D Model economic policies that a nation enacts can also affect efficiency. For example, if laws that lowered manufacturing costs were passed, the businesses might hire back those laid-off workers. In that case, the economy could become more efficient and return to the production possibilities frontier. Any point inside the production possibilities frontier indicates underutilization, or the use of fewer resources than the economy is capable of using. At point b in Figure 1.4, Capeland is growing 5 million tons of watermelons and making 8 million pairs of shoes. This is inefficient because it is less than the maximum possible production. Growth A production possibilities curve is a snapshot. It reflects current production possibilities as if a country&apos;s resources were frozen in time. In the real world, however, available resources are constantly changing. If the quantity or quality of land, labor, or capital changes, then the curve will move. For example, a wave of immigration may increase a nation&apos;s labor supply. This rise in a factor of production increases the maximum amount of goods the nation can produce. When an economy grows, economists say that the production possibilities frontier has “shifted to the right.” To see such a shift, look at line c in Figure 1.4. Notice that the possible output of both shoes and watermelons has increased at each point along the line. However, when a country&apos;s production capacity decreases, the curve shifts to the left. A decrease could occur, for example, when a country goes to war and loses part of its land as a result. Opportunity Cost We can also use production possibilities graphs to determine the cost involved in a decision. Remember that cost does not necessarily mean money. To an economist, cost nearly always means opportunity cost. Looking at the production possibilities table for Capeland, we can see that the opportunity cost of moving from producing no watermelons to producing 8 million tons of watermelons is 1 million pairs of shoes. In other words, in order to produce 8 million tons of watermelons, Capeland had to sacrifice the opportunity to produce 1 million pairs of shoes. In the same way, if Capeland later decides to increase watermelon production from 8 million tons to 14 million tons&ndash;an increase of only 6 million tons&ndash;it costs 2 million pairs of shoes. In the first step, those 8 million tons of watermelons cost 1 million pairs of shoes. In the second step, an increase of only 6 million tons of watermelons costs an additional 2 million pairs of shoes. This amounts to 3 million pairs of shoes for 14 million tons of watermelons. Every additional step of switching from shoes to watermelons has an increasing cost. Each time Capeland grows more watermelons, the sacrifice in terms of shoes increases. Eventually, it costs Capeland an additional 5 million pairs of shoes to increase watermelon production by only 1 million tons. 1.3 Production Possibilities 15 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="82"> <text><![CDATA[ >> Automation, the use of equipment that runs largely on its own, increases efficiency. Analyze Political Cartoons What concern might the cartoonist be expressing about this technology? Economists explain these increasingly expensive trade-offs through the law of increasing costs. This principle states that as production shifts from making one item to another, more and more resources are necessary to increase production of the second item. Therefore, the opportunity cost increases. Why does the cost increase? The reason is that some resources are better suited for use in farming while others are more appropriate for manufacturing. Moving resources from factory to farm production means that farmers must use resources that are not as suitable for farming. For example, when deciding to produce 8 million tons of watermelons, Capeland devoted its most fertile land to this crop. That shift used up the country&apos;s best land, so with each additional step, farmers had to use poorer land that produced less per acre than the fertile land could. To increase output on the poorer land, farmers had to use more land and other resources. This left even fewer resources for producing shoes. The law of increasing costs explains why production possibilities curve. As we move along the curve, we trade off more and more for less and less added output. Technology and Training When economists collect data to create production possibilities curves, they must first determine which goods and services a country can produce with its current resources. A country&apos;s resources include its land and natural resources, its workforce, and its physical and human capital. Both human and physical capital reflect a vital ingredient of economic growth&ndash;technology. Technology is the process used to create goods and services. At any time, countries have used different forms of technology to produce shoes or watermelons or any of the thousands of products that are made. So economists must assess each country&apos;s level of technological know-how. Do workers in Capeland pick watermelons by hand? Do they use assembly lines to make shoes? Technology is one of the factors that can increase a nation&apos;s efficiency. Therefore, many governments spend money investing in new technology. For the same reason, they may also invest in education and training so that people can develop and use new technologies. Highly skilled workers can increase efficiency and lead to economic growth. CHECK UNDERSTANDING Why is it important to pair advances in technology with education and training? ASSESSMENT 1. Generate Explanations How does a production possibilities frontier show efficient uses of a country&apos;s resources? 2. Express Problems Clearly Suppose that a country has the resources to produce 3 million cars and 100 million tons of iron ore every year. Why is it a problem if the country produces 2 million cars and 75 million tons of iron ore one year? 3. Apply Concepts Explain how the law of increasing costs would apply in Capeland if the country decided to direct more resources into making shoes than into growing watermelons. 4. Predict Consequences How would the widespread use of a new type of chemical fertilizer affect a nation&apos;s production possibilities frontier? Why? 5. Determine Relevance Why is there so much emphasis on education in the modern world? 16 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="83"> <text><![CDATA[ Savvas.com/FloridaSS Go online to Savvas.com/FloridaSS and use the texts, quizzes, interactivities, Interactive Reading Notepads, Flipped Videos, and other resources from this Topic to prepare for the Topic Test. Etexts Quizzes Interactivities Interactive Reading Notepads Flipped Videos While online you can also check the progress you&apos;ve made learning the topic and course content by viewing your grades, test scores, and assignment status. ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="84"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 1 Quick Study Guide LESSON SUMMARIES Use these lesson summaries, and the longer versions available online, to review the key ideas for each lesson in this topic. Lesson 1: Scarcity LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, SS.912.E.1.1 Scarcity exists because there is a limited amount of goods and services available to meet people&apos;s needs. Scarcity affects the factors of production, or the resources used to make goods and services. These factors of production are land, labor, and capital. Capital is any human-made resource that is used to make goods and services and includes both human capital, or education and experience, and physical capital, such as buildings and machinery. Lesson 2: Opportunity Cost and Trade-Offs LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9, SS.912.E.1.7 Making and distributing goods and services requires many decisions. Decisions involve trade-offs between one possibility and another. Opportunity cost, or the cost of giving up one option for another, shape economic decisions. Economic decisions also involve thinking at the margin&ndash;that is, thinking about the cost and benefit of adding one more item or subtracting an item. Lesson 3: Production Possibilities LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, SS.912.E.1.2 Production possibilities&ndash;which are limited by scarcity and trade-offs&ndash;can be shown graphically for two categories of products in a production possibilities curve. The curve shows the production possibilities frontier, or the amount of each category that can produced in an economy with the most efficient possible use of resources. If a society can increase the supply of resources or find ways to use them more efficiently, then the production possibilities frontier rises, and economic growth results. Savvas.com/FloridaSS Go ONLINE for lesson summaries AUDIO READING GAMES]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="85"> <text><![CDATA[ VISUAL REVIEW Use these graphics to review some of the key terms and ideas from this topic. Needs and wants are unlimited. Resources, goods, and services are scarce. Need to make trade-offs and identify opportunity costs. Impact on Individuals &bull; Make personal trade-offs (time, money) &bull; Make decisions at the margin. Impact on Businesses &bull; Balance factors of production: land, labor, capital &bull; Identify marginal costs and benefits Impact on Nations &bull; Make budgetary trade-offs (“guns or butter”) &bull; Determine production possibilities Law of Increasing Costsproduction shifts from one item to another more resources are necessary to increase production of second item opportunity cost increases Factors of Production Land All natural resources used to produce goods and services Labor The effort that people devote to tasks for which they are paid Capital Any human- made resource that is used to produce other goods and services Physical capital Human capital A worker&apos;s knowledge and skills Human-made objects used to create other goods and services ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="86"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 1 Assessment KEY TERMS AND IDEAS Production Possibilities Curve SS.912.E.1.1 1. How do goods differ from services? 25 2. Why is scarcity an important concept in economics? 3. Why is the role of an entrepreneur so important? 4. List the three main factors of production. 5. How do opportunity costs shape economic decisions? 6. What is marginal cost and what is its role in decision making? 7. What does a production possibilities curve show? 8. Why is efficiency an important economic goal? 0 a b c CRITICAL THINKING LAFS.1112.WHST.4.10, SS.912.E.1.1, SS.912.E.1.2, SS.912.E.2.3 9. Draw Inferences Why are the factors of production necessary for the production of goods and services? 10. Support a Point of View With Evidence List three qualities that you think an entrepreneur needs in order to succeed. Provide evidence showing why each quality is important. 11. Support Ideas With Examples What is scarcity, as the term is used in economics? What is an everyday example of scarcity that demonstrates why scarcity is a basic economic problem that faces every society? 12. Apply Concepts Cars that weigh more tend to be safer than lightweight cars. At the same time, they use more gasoline because they are heavier. (a) Identify the tradeoffs and opportunity costs involved in choosing either kind of car. (b) Based on this information, which kind of car would you choose to buy and why? 13. Summarize Write a paragraph that explains the idea of opportunity costs in your own words. 14. Apply Concepts What marginal costs and benefits might a tour boat operator consider when deciding whether to purchase a new boat? 15. Express Problems Clearly Explain the tradeoffs that people may face when choosing a house or an apartment. 16. Synthesize The graph below shows a production possibilities curve for shoes and watermelons. Explain how the curve shows the principles of choice, scarcity, and opportunity costs. Production Possibilities Curve Shoes (millions of pairs) 20 15 10 5 0 Watermelons (millions of tons) 0 5 10 15 20 25 17. Analyze Graphs If the economy shown in the graph is producing at full efficiency, how many tons of watermelons are being produced when 14 million pairs of shoes are being produced? 18. Apply Concepts What is the opportunity cost of producing 14 million tons of watermelons, according to the graph? 19. Analyze Information From 2000 to 2010, the economy of the United States grew at an average annual rate of 3.4 percent. What do you think happened to the production possibilities frontier? 20. Hypothesize Assume that a drought struck a country. (a) What would happen to the production possibilities curve of all farmers in the country? (b) Would the production possibilities curve of other industries be affected by this drought? Why or why not? 21. Writing Activity In this topic, you learned about the importance of entrepreneurs to the economy. Inventors also contribute to economic growth. Using reliable sources as directed by your teacher, research the lives and work of Madam C.J. Walker, an entrepreneur, and Thomas Edison, an inventor and entrepreneur. Explain their contributions to the development of the United States. Write an article meant for an adult audience suitable for publication in a magazine. 20 TOPIC 1 Fundamentals of Economics ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="87"> <text><![CDATA[ DOCUMENT-BASED QUESTIONS LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, LAFS.1112.RH.3.7 Human space flight is a great achievement, but some question its expense. Read the documents below, then answer the questions that follow. DOCUMENT A Charles Bolden, the head of NASA, the U.S. space agency, discusses the agency&apos;s plans and budget. . . . President Obama is proposing an FY2016 budget of $18.5 billion dollars for NASA, building on the significant investments the Administration has made in America&apos;s space program over the past six years. That&apos;s a half billion-dollar increase over last year&apos;s enacted budget, and it is a clear vote of confidence in you&ndash;the employees of NASA&ndash;and the ambitious exploration program you are executing. . . . &ndash;NASA Administrator Charles Bolden, February 2, 2015 DOCUMENT B This image of Earth over the moon was taken by astronauts on NASA&apos;s Apollo 11 in 1969. DOCUMENT C This statement, entitled “Why We Explore,” appeared on NASA&apos;s website. Human space exploration helps to address fundamental questions about our place in the Universe and the history of our solar system. Through addressing the challenges related to human space exploration we expand technology, create new industries, and help to foster a peaceful connection with other nations. Curiosity and exploration are vital to the human spirit. . . &ndash;NASA, webpage last updated September 30, 2013 DOCUMENT D In this article, a journalist cites physicist Steven Weinberg, a critic of spending on human space flight. Manned space flight crowds out real science, Weinberg argues. As an example, he points out that in 2004, . . . Nasa revealed it was making major cutbacks in its programmes of unmanned research in astronomy . . . In other words, to support manned missions science projects were cut back. Even worse, says Weinberg, was the example of the US Superconducting Super-Collider, which was designed to study the structure of matter. . . Congress decided the US could not build the SSC and the International Space Station . . . at the same time. So it chose to build the space station, mainly for political reasons. &ndash;Robin McKie, The Guardian, December 6, 2014 22. Which of the following statements about the space program is most factually accurate? A. Images of Earth from space have inspired millions. B. The International Space Station cost more than the Superconducting Super-Collider. C. Because of scarcity, the space program involved opportunity costs. D. Human space flight is less valuable than other scientific research. 23. Analyze Photographs How is Document B connected to the arguments in Document C? A. The photograph created a sense of wonder for people around the world. B. The photograph offered a new perspective on humanity&apos;s place in the universe. C. The photograph showed other nations the superiority of American technology. D. The beauty of the photograph was worth the expense required to make it. 24. How do the claims and reasoning in Document C differ from those in Document D? A. Document D appeals more to readers&apos; emotions. B. Document C appeals more to readers&apos; emotions. C. Document D acknowledges counterarguments. D. Document C acknowledges counterarguments. 25. Writing Task Integrating these documents and what you have learned in this topic about opportunity costs, evaluate the claims, reasoning, and evidence presented in Documents C and D. Do you think space exploration is worth the cost? Why or why not? Savvas.com/FloridaSS Go ONLINE to practice ASSESSMENT]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="88"> <text><![CDATA[ AUDIO VIDEO WRITING ETEXT ASSESSMENT GAMES ACTIVITY PDFGo ONLINE for digital resources Savvas.com/FloridaSS [ ESSENTIAL QUESTION ] Who benefits from the free market economy? 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="89"> <text><![CDATA[ Next Generation Sunshine State Standards SS.912.E.1.3, SS.912.E.1.8, SS.912.E.2.1, SS.912.E.2.11, SS.912.E.2.12, LAFS.1112.RH.1.1, LAFS.1112.RH.1.2, LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, LAFS.1112.RH.3.8, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10, LAFS.1112.SL.1.1, LAFS.1112.WHST.2.4 Enduring Understandings &bull; Because societies answer the key economic questions differently, multiple economic systems have developed. &bull; Competition helps regulate markets and gives producers incentives to make what consumers want. &bull; Because pure market and pure centrally planned economies have drawbacks, nations tend to have mixed economies. &bull; Under the American free enterprise system, the government preserves economic freedoms while protecting the public interest through limited regulation of the economy. >>Two young men stand andsmile at their bicycle shop. Leslie Bradshaw and the importance of innovation. Bounce to Activate My Story Video ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="90"> <text><![CDATA[ Florida Topic 2 Overview In this topic, you will learn that the United States relies mainly on free markets to answer basic economic questions. Look at the lesson outline and explore the flow chart. As you study this topic, you&apos;ll complete the quest team project. LESSON OUTLINE 2.1 The Three Key Economic Questions SS.912.E.1.3, SS.912.E.2.1, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9 2.2 Free Markets SS.912.E.1.3, SS.912.E.1.8, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 2.3 Centrally Planned Economies SS.912.E.1.3, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 2.4 Mixed Economies SS.912.E.1.3, SS.912.E.2.12 2.5 Benefits of Free Enterprise LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 2.6 Supporting Economic Growth LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 2.7 Public Goods and Externalities SS.912.E.2.11, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems What goods and services should be produced? How should these goods and services be produced? Who consumes these goods and services? 24 TOPIC 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="91"> <text><![CDATA[ CONTINUUM O F MIXED ECONOMIES SOME ECONOMIES ARE MOSTLY CENTRALLY PLANNED SOME ECONOMIES ARE A MIXTURE OF CENTRAL PLANNING AND FREE MARKETSSOME ECONOMIES ARE MOSTLY FREE MARKETS NORTH KOREA IRAN MEXICO UNITED STATES, CANADA SINGAPORE TEAM PROJECT Civic Discussion: Laissez Faire? The United States’ system is a mixed economy that leans toward the free market. Should the U.S. economy move toward or away from laissez faire, or an economy without government involvement? In this quest, you will consider various viewpoints on this question and discuss with your classmates the pros and cons of laissez faire. STEP 1 Read the Discussion Launch and decide with your group which are the major points in the reading. STEP 2 Read and analyze the source documents. Determine the central idea of each and evaluate the authors’ differing points of view. STEP 3 Find evidence in the sources for your assigned position. Prepare your arguments. Consider both sides of the question. STEP 5 Participate in a thoughtful, wellreasoned exchange of ideas with group members. Present your arguments and evidence and consider and challenge those presented by others. NGSSS LAFS.1112.RH.2.6, LAFS.1112.SL.1.1 Savvas.com/FloridaSS Go ONLINE for complete Quest materials VIDEO ETEXT WRITING RUBRIC PDF ASSESSMENT 25 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="92"> <text><![CDATA[ 2.1 When you go to a supermarket, you see rows of shelves stacked with a variety of foods and products. But suppose the government limited your choice to just one brand of cereal and one brand of soap. Or what if the only goods available to you were what you and your neighbors could grow or make yourselves? All of these examples represent ways different societies have dealt with the challenge of meeting people&apos;s needs and wants. >> In the United States, we have chosen to make a public education available to all young people. Bounce to Activate Flipped Video NGSSS SS.912.E.1.3, SS.912.E.2.1, LAFS.1112.WHST.3.9, SS.912.FL.6.8 >> Objectives Identify the three basic economic questions that all societies must answer. Describe the economic goals that determine how a society answers the three economic questions. Define the characteristics of a traditional economy. >> Key Terms economic system factor payments profit safety net standard of living innovation traditional economy The Three Key Economic Questions Three Basic Economic Questions In fact, every society faces three basic questions about the production and consumption of goods and services. How people answer these questions shapes our freedom of choice&ndash;and what we have to choose from. Resources are scarce everywhere. As a result, every society must answer three basic economic questions: &bull; What goods and services should be produced? &bull; How should these goods and services be produced? &bull; Who consumes these goods and services? The way a society answers these questions defines its economic system. An economic system is the structure of methods and principles a society uses to produce and distribute goods and services. What Goods and Services Should Be Produced? Every society must decide what to produce in order to satisfy society&apos;s needs and wants. While all people need food and shelter, societies face additional considerations. Which consumer goods should we produce? How much of our resources should we devote to national VIDEO ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT Go ONLINE for digital resources AUDIO ACTIVITY Savvas.com/FloridaSS ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="93"> <text><![CDATA[ defense, education, or consumer goods? Because resources are limited, each decision comes with an opportunity cost. How Should Goods and Services Be Produced? A society must also decide how to produce goods and services. Is education best delivered through public schools or private schools? What fuel should we use to generate electricity&ndash;oil, solar power, or nuclear power? Although there are many ways to produce goods and services, all require land, labor, and capital. These factors of production can be combined in different ways. For example, look at Figure 2.1. Before the introduction of modern farming equipment, producing 15 bushels of wheat may have required 56 hours of labor, 1 acre of land, and simple hand tools. Today, mechanical equipment and other technologies make farming more efficient. Farmers can use just 2.9 hours of labor to produce 40 bushels of wheat on that same acre of land. While the amount of land used remains the same, labor has gone down, and the amount of capital needed has gone up. These decisions involve trade-offs, too. What else could the society produce with those 56 hours of work in the time of hand tools? What could today&apos;s society make if the capital employed as mechanized farm equipment were used in some other way? Who Consumes the Goods and Services That Are Produced? Societies also make decisions that determine how goods and services are consumed. How can people meet their needs for food and medical care? Who gets to drive a new luxury car and who can only afford bus fare? Who gets access to a college education? The answers to such questions are largely determined by how societies distribute income. Factor payments are the income people receive in return for supplying factors of production&ndash;land, labor, or capital. Landowners collect rent, workers earn wages, and those who lend money receive payments called interest. Factor payments also include the profits that entrepreneurs earn if their enterprises succeed. Profit is the amount of money a business receives in excess of its expenses. Profits are the rewards entrepreneurs receive for taking the risk of starting a business. How much should we pay the owners of the factors of production? How do we decide how much teachers should earn versus how much doctors should earn? The answers to such questions tell us a great deal about a society&apos;s values. IDENTIFY MAIN IDEAS What are the three basic economic questions? COMBINING FACTOR RESOURCES HAND TOOLS 1ACRE OF LAND + 56WORKER HOURS + CAPITAL = 15 BUSHELS OF WHEAT MODERN MECHANICAL EQUIPMENT 1ACRE OF LAND + 2.9 WORKER HOURS + CAPITAL = 40 BUSHELS OF WHEAT>> Figure 2.1 This illustration shows two different approaches to the question of how to combine the factors of production. Analyze Information Which approach is most efficient? Explain your answer. Bounce to Activate Chart 2.1 The Three Key Economic Questions 27 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="94"> <text><![CDATA[ Economic Goals of Society Different societies answer the three economic questions based on the importance they attach to various economic goals. These goals include efficiency, freedom, security, equity, and growth. All societies pursue each of these goals to some degree. Efficiency Because resources are always scarce, societies try to maximize what they can produce using the resources they have. If a society can accurately assess what its people need and want, it increases its economic efficiency. A manufacturer would be wasting resources producing desktop computers if people prefer laptops. The goal of reducing waste also involves the second and third economic questions. Producers seek better ways to create goods and to make them available to consumers. An economy that cannot deliver the right goods in the right quantity to the right people at the right price is not efficient. Freedom Most people value the opportunity to make their own choices. Still, people all over the world face limits to their economic freedom. Americans face limits as well. But in general, individual freedom is a key cultural value for Americans. We prize the freedom to buy what we can pay for, to seek work where we want, to own property, and to become entrepreneurs. In order to obtain these benefits, we accept the costs that come with freedom&ndash;for example, the potential of failure. Not everyone is able to prosper, and some people experience poverty. Security Most people do not like uncertainty. We want to know we can get milk or bread every time we go to the store. We want the security of knowing we will get our paychecks every payday. Ideally, economic systems seek to reassure people that goods and services will be available when needed and that expected payments will arrive on time. We also want the security of knowing that help is available if we are in need. Many governments provide a safety net, or set of programs to protect people who face unfavorable economic conditions such as layoffs, injuries, or natural disasters. Many countries also provide some sort of base income for retired persons to ensure that they can support themselves in retirement. Equity Equity, or fairness, is another economic goal that is defined differently in different societies. (See Figure 2.2 for information about one measure of equity in the United States in recent years.) Each society must decide how to divide its economic pie. Should everyone get the same share of the goods Changes in Economic Equity, 1976–2011 Mean Household Income (2011 dollars) $200,000 $175,000 $150,000 $125,000 $100,000 $75,000 $50,000 $25000 $0 Year 1976 1981 1986 1991 1996 2001 2006 2011 Mean Household Income Highest 20% Fourth 20% ThirdSeco 20% nd 20% Lowest 20% Year SOURCE: United States Census Bureau >> Figure 2.2 Household income rose between 1976 and 2011 at all five income levels&ndash;but not at equal rates. Analyze Graphs Which income group saw the greatest change? 28 TOPIC 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="95"> <text><![CDATA[ and services a nation produces? Or should one&apos;s consumption depend on how much one produces? How much should society provide for those who are unable or unwilling to produce? How are the benefits of economic freedom compromised by the goal of economic equity&ndash;or is inequity possibly a cost of freedom? Growth A nation&apos;s economy must grow with its population so it can provide jobs for the new people joining the workforce. A nation&apos;s economy must grow if people are going to have more income. When that occurs, the nation improves its standard of living, or level of economic prosperity. Innovation plays a huge role in economic growth. Innovation is the process of bringing new methods, products, or ideas into use. During the Industrial Revolution of the 1700s and 1800s, innovations in technology increased the efficiency of production and introduced new goods and services. Many problems arose, such as harsh conditions in factories and crowded cities, as well as increased pollution of air and water. Yet, the Industrial Revolution also sparked economic growth and led to an overall rise in standards of living. Today, innovations in computer and networking technology are changing how people work, do business, find information, and communicate. Conflicting Economic Goals A society may value goals other than these. Environmental protection, full employment, or protecting national industries may be among a nation&apos;s chief economic goals. Sometimes, economic goals conflict with one another. For example, when a society provides a safety net for all citizens, the added cost may slow economic growth. To protect the environment, a government may impose regulations on manufacturers that curb economic freedom. Thus, all nations must prioritize their economic goals, or arrange them in order of importance. Each choice comes with some kind of trade-off. Choosing among conflicting economic goals is a basic economic problem that every society must face. Traditional Economies Societies have developed four different economic systems to address the three basic economic questions. Each system reflects a different prioritization of economic goals. It also reflects the values of the societies in which these systems are found. The oldest and simplest of economic systems is the traditional economy. A traditional economy relies on habit, custom, or ritual to answer the three >> This U.S. National Guard soldier is helping to deliver aid to victims of a storm. This is one way government helps maintain people&apos;s economic security in times of need. >> Traditional economies still exist in many parts of the world. This Inuit man lives in North America and depends on hunting and fishing, much as his ancestors did hundreds of years ago. 2.1 The Three Key Economic Questions 29 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="96"> <text><![CDATA[ basic economic questions. There is little room for innovation or change. The traditional economic system revolves around the family unit&ndash;often an extended family made up of several generations. Work tends to be divided along gender lines. Boys tend to take up the occupations of their fathers, while girls follow those of their mothers. Traditional economies are usually found in communities that tend to stay relatively small and close. Often people in these societies work to support the entire community, rather than just themselves or their immediate families. In these societies, agricultural and hunting practices usually lie at the center of people&apos;s lives, laws, and religious beliefs. Societies with traditional economies are economically successful if they meet their own needs. But they have few mechanisms to deal effectively with the effects of environmental disaster, such as a flood or drought. They also tend to be slow to adopt new ideas or technology. They may not have access to a wide range of goods. In most cases, these communities lack modern conveniences and have a relatively low standard of living. IDENTIFY What are two examples of economic goals? ASSESSMENT 1. Apply Concepts A clothing company produces a new line of inexpensive jeans using a special process that is environmentally friendly. In this example, how has society answered the three basic economic questions? 2. Analyze Information (a) Why would it be inefficient today for a manufacturer to produce music CDs instead of digital MP3 music files? (b) What role does scarcity play in a manufacturer&apos;s decision to produce MP3 files and not CDs? 3. Generate Explanations (a) What are some examples of types of investments on the part of manufacturers that result in growth? (b) How does this help improve a nation&apos;s standard of living? 4. Draw Conclusions What economic goals might come into conflict if a factory polluted a local water supply? 5. Apply Concepts Which basic economic goals can be achieved easily in a traditional economy? Which cannot? Explain. 30 TOPIC 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="97"> <text><![CDATA[ 2.2 Do you value freedom? If you thought about this question in terms of freedom of speech or freedom of religion, you probably said yes. What about the freedom to own property, to get a job, or to spend your money the way you want? To Americans, economic freedom is also highly valued. It has shaped the system under which we live. >> Specialized skill and knowledge enables this man to fix complex refrigeration equipment and to earn a living. Draw Conclusions How does this worker benefit from having specialized skill and knowledge? Bounce to Activate Flipped Video Free Markets Why Do Markets Exist? Indeed, economic freedom is the chief characteristic of a free market economy. You will soon see how the free market affects every household and community in the United States, including yours. Markets Defined What do a farmer&apos;s market, a sporting goods store, the New York Stock Exchange, and a community bulletin board where you posted a sign advertising baby-sitting services have in common? All are examples of markets. A market is any arrangement that allows buyers and sellers to exchange things. Markets eliminate the need for any one person to be self- sufficient. None of us produces all we require to satisfy our needs and wants. You probably did not grow cotton plants, process that cotton into cloth, or weave that cloth into the shirt you are wearing. Instead, you purchased your shirt at a store. Markets allow us to exchange the things we have for the things we want. The Role of Specialization Instead of being self-sufficient, each of us specializes in a few products or services. Specialization is the concentration of the productive efforts of individuals and businesses on a limited number of activities. A baker specializes in making breads, cakes, and cookies. A nurse specializes in NGSSS SS.912.E.1.3, SS.912.E.1.8, LAFS.1112.RH.4.10 >> Objectives Explain why markets exist. Explain a circular flow model of a free market economy. Describe how self-interest and competition lead to the self-regulating nature of the marketplace. Identify the advantages of a free market economy. >> Key Terms market non-price specialization competition free market consumer economy sovereignty household firm factor market product market Adam Smith self-interest incentive competition price competition Savvas.com/FloridaSS Go ONLINE for digital resources VIDEO AUDIO ACTIVITY ETEXT WRITING ASSESSMENT ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="98"> <text><![CDATA[ caring for the sick. An aircraft plant manufactures only airplanes&ndash;not airplanes, refrigerators, and bicycles. Specialization leads to efficiency in the use of capital, land, and labor. It is better for people to learn one task or a few tasks very well than to learn a little about many tasks. Because they concentrate on one or a few tasks, they can do their work more efficiently, saving resources by avoiding waste. For this reason, the top performers in most fields are specialists who have worked hard to sharpen their particular skills. Specialization also benefits businesses. Focusing on a limited number of related products or services allows them to use their limited capital and labor more efficiently. Buying and Selling People in primitive cultures had to make everything they needed from materials they gathered from nature. Even in more recent times, some people strive for self-sufficiency. However, because most of us in the modern world specialize in producing just a few goods or services, we need a mechanism that allows us to sell what we have produced and to buy what we want. Figure 2.3 illustrates this concept. In a modern market-based economy, people typically earn income by specializing in particular jobs. They then use this income to buy the products that they want to consume. IdENTIfy MAIN IdEAS Why do markets exist? Elements of a Free Market Economy In a free market economy, answers to the three basic economic questions are made by voluntary exchange in markets. The choices made by individuals determine what gets made, how it is made, and how much people can consume of the goods and services produced. Individuals and businesses make their own decisions about what to buy or sell. Market economies are also called capitalist economies because the capital that entrepreneurs invest in businesses is a vital part of the system. In a free market system, individuals and privately owned businesses own the factors of production, make what they want, and buy what they want. In other words, individuals answer the three basic >> Figure 2.3 This farmer specializes in raising one crop, using income from its sale to purchase equipment and other goods. Test Conclusions What evidence can you see that the farmer earns income from the specialized production of one crop? Bounce to Activate Illustration 32 TOPIC 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="99"> <text><![CDATA[ >> Figure 2.4 The circular flow model shows the interaction between households and firms in a free market. Analyze Charts What is the primary item that changes hands in the monetary flow? Bounce to Activate 3D Model questions of what to produce, how to produce it, and who consumes what is produced. The United States has a free market economic system. This system is commonly referred to as the United States free enterprise system. In general, free enterprise, free market, and capitalism are all synonyms for the economic system of the United States. Households and Firms The participants in a free market economy are households and firms. A household is a person or group of people living in a single residence. Households own the factors of production&ndash;land, labor, and capital. They are also consumers of goods and services. A business, or firm, is an organization that uses resources to produce a product or service, which it then sells. Firms transform inputs, or factors of production, into outputs, or goods and services. We can represent the exchanges that take place in a free market economy in a diagram called a circular flow model. Look at Figure 2.4. The diagram shows how households and firms exchange money, resources, and products in the marketplace. The inner ring of the diagram represents the flow of resources and products. Note that both households and firms are resource owners in this model. The outer ring represents the flow of money. Factor and Product Markets As you can see from the lower half of the model, firms purchase factors of production from households. This arena of exchange is called the factor market. An example of this is when firms purchase or rent land. They hire workers, paying them wages or salaries for their labor. They also borrow money from households to purchase capital, paying households interest or profits in return. Now look at the top half of the circular flow model. The arena in which households buy the goods and services that firms produce is the product market. So, when you buy food at a supermarket, you are taking part in the product market physical flow. If you follow the rings of the diagram, you will see that in the product market, households purchase the products made by firms with the money they receive from firms in the factor market. The monetary and physical flows through the factor and product markets are truly circular. EXPRESS IDEAS CLEARLY What is the role of firms in the free market economy? 2.2 Free Markets 33 ]]></text>
   </page>
    <page pageNumber="100"> <text><![CDATA[ How Markets Self- Regulate Firms and households usually cooperate to give each other what they want&ndash;factor resources from households to firms, and goods and services from firms to households. Why should they cooperate when we live in such a competitive society? According to Adam Smith, competition and our own self-interest actually help to keep the marketplace functioning. Self-Interest Adam Smith was a Scottish social philosopher. In 1776, he published a book titled The Wealth of Nations that described how markets function. Smith observed that an economy is made up of countless individual transactions. In each of these exchanges, the buyer and seller consider only their own self-interest, that is, their own personal gain. Smith observed: Give me that which I want, and you shall have this which you want . . . and it is in this manner that we obtain from one another the far greater part of those good [services] which we stand in need of. It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest. &ndash;Adam Smith, The Wealth of Nations Self-interest, in other words, is the motivating force in the free market&ndash;the push that leads people to act. Incentives and Competition Consumers, pursuing their self-interest, have the incentive to look for lower prices. Look at Figure 2.5. An incentive is the hope of reward or fear of penalty that encourages a person to behave in a certain way. Many incentives are monetary, or based on money, such as the promise of higher wages or profits. Others are nonmonetary, such as the prestige and personal satisfaction one gets from running a successful business. Adam Smith observed that people respond in a predictable way to both positive and negative incentives. Consumers, for instance, will respond to the positive incentive of lower prices by buying WHAT ARE INCENTIVES? ADMIT ONE ADMIT ONE Maria&apos;s parents promise to buy her concert tickets if she improves her grades. POSITIVE INCENTIVE $+ State government offers a tax credit for commuters who use public transportation to get to work. Maria spends more time studying for school. RESPONSE Gas consumption drops as commuters drive less and use public transportation more. Maria&apos;s parents threaten to ground her if her grades do not improve. NEGATIVE INCENTIVE –$ State government increases the tax on gasoline. >> Figure 2.5 In a free market, incentives of all sorts influence individuals to act in their own self-interest. Identify Central Ideas Use one of the examples from this diagram to explain how the incentive given leads to the response indicated. Bounce to Activate Gallery 34 TOPIC 2 Free Enterprise and Other Economic Systems ]]></text>
   </page>
    </eBook>